<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ! CCPL HEADER START
  !
  ! This work is licensed under the Creative Commons
  ! Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 3.0 Unported License.
  ! To view a copy of this license, visit
  ! http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/
  ! or send a letter to Creative Commons, 444 Castro Street,
  ! Suite 900, Mountain View, California, 94041, USA.
  !
  ! You can also obtain a copy of the license at
  ! src/main/resources/legal-notices/CC-BY-NC-ND.txt.
  ! See the License for the specific language governing permissions
  ! and limitations under the License.
  !
  ! If applicable, add the following below this CCPL HEADER, with the fields
  ! enclosed by brackets "[]" replaced with your own identifying information:
  !      Portions Copyright [yyyy] [name of copyright owner]
  !
  ! CCPL HEADER END
  !
  !      Copyright 2013 ForgeRock AS
  !
-->
<chapter xml:id='chap-first-steps'
         xmlns='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook'
         version='5.0'
         xml:lang='en'
         xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'
         xsi:schemaLocation='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook
          http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd'
         xmlns:xlink='http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink'>
 <title>Protecting a Web Site With OpenAM</title>

 <para>You can get started with OpenAM using this chapter. Follow the steps in
 this chapter to learn how to protect a web site with OpenAM.</para>

 <important>
  <para>You need a Linux, Solaris, or Windows system that can run the web policy
  agent (see the <link xlink:show="new"
  xlink:href="web-release-notes#platform-requirements-web-agents"
  xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"
  ><citetitle>Web Agents Platform Requirements</citetitle></link> if your system
  does not have an x86 or x64 based processor for example) with a minimum of 1
  GB of free RAM memory, a few hundred MB of free disk space, a web browser and
  Internet connection to download software.</para>

  <para>If you are running Mac OS X, set up a virtual machine running Linux to
  try these procedures because the web policy agent is not built for Apache HTTP
  Server on Mac OS X.</para>
 </important>

 <section xml:id="how-openam-helps-manage-access">
  <title>How OpenAM Helps Manage Access to Resources</title>

  <para>OpenAM provides a service called <firstterm>access management</firstterm>,
  which involves managing access to resources available over the network.
  Once you set up OpenAM to manage access, you have a centralized service to
  take control of who can access what resources, when, and under what
  conditions. In this chapter you manage access to a single web page. Yet, a
  resource can be just about anything accessible over the network from a
  web page, to an application, to a web service.</para>

  <para>OpenAM centralizes access control by handling both
  <firstterm>authentication</firstterm> and also
  <firstterm>authorization</firstterm>. Authentication is confirming an
  identity, for example confirming that a user has successfully logged in.
  Authorization is determining whether to grant access to someone who has
  authenticated.</para>

  <para>OpenAM centralizes authentication by using a variety of authentication
  modules. Authentication modules connect to identity repositories that store
  identities and provide authentication services. The identity repositories can
  be implemented as LDAP directories, relational databases, RADIUS, Windows
  authentication, one-time password services, other standards-based access
  management systems and much more. OpenAM lets you chain together the
  authentication services used. Authentication chains let you configure
  stronger authentication for more sensitive resources for example. They also
  let you set up modules that remember a device when the user logs in
  successfully. Or that evaluate the risk given the login circumstances and
  therefore can require more credentials when a user is logging in from an
  unusual location. This chapter uses OpenAM's built-in identity repository
  and authentication modules to make it easier to get started.</para>

  <para>OpenAM centralizes authorization by letting you use OpenAM to manage
  access policies separate from applications and resources. Instead of building
  access policy into a web application, you install a policy agent with the
  web application to request policy decisions from OpenAM. This way you can
  avoid issues that could arise when developers must embed policy decisions
  into their applications. With OpenAM, if policy changes or an issue is found
  after the application is deployed, you have only to change the policy
  definition in OpenAM, not deploy a new version of the application. OpenAM
  makes the authorization decisions, and policy agents enforce the decisions
  on OpenAM's behalf.</para>

  <para>The rest of this chapter has you demonstrate OpenAM access management
  by installing OpenAM, creating a policy, and installing a policy agent on
  a web server to enforce the policy for a web page.</para>
 </section>

 <section xml:id="software-you-need">
  <title>Software Required To Try Out OpenAM</title>

  <para>In order to set up OpenAM to protect a web page, you install the
  following software, all of which is freely available. This chapter covers
  how to install the software, with the exception of the Java Development
  Kit.</para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>Java Development Kit</para>

    <para>OpenAM is a Java web application, and requires a Java Development Kit
    installed on the system where it runs.</para>

    <para>The web policy agent installer is also a Java program.</para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>Apache HTTP Server</para>

    <para>Apache HTTP Server serves the web page to protect with OpenAM.</para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>Apache Tomcat</para>

    <para>As a Java web web application OpenAM runs inside a web container,
    in this case Apache Tomcat.</para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>OpenAM core server with OpenAM Console</para>

    <para>This is the main web application for OpenAM. OpenAM sets up an OpenDJ
    directory server at configuration time to use in this case both to hold
    OpenAM's configuration and also to serve as an identity store and
    authentication service.</para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>OpenAM Apache Policy Agent</para>

    <para>You install a policy agent in Apache HTTP Server. The policy agent
    intercepts requests from users, and enforces access policy decisions made
    by OpenAM. The policy agent enforces policy both by redirecting users to
    OpenAM for authentication and by contacting OpenAM to get authorization
    decisions for resources such as the web page to protect.</para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>Follow the steps in the next sections of this chapter to see how
  OpenAM can protect a web site without changing the web site itself.</para>
 </section>

 <section xml:id="software-setup">
  <title>Setting Up the Software</title>

  <para>This section includes the following procedures that detail how to
  set up OpenAM to protect a web page.</para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem><para><xref linkend="prepare-etc-hosts" /></para></listitem>
   <listitem><para><xref linkend="install-apache-http" /></para></listitem>
   <listitem><para><xref linkend="install-apache-tomcat" /></para></listitem>
   <listitem><para><xref linkend="install-openam" /></para></listitem>
   <listitem><para><xref linkend="configure-policy" /></para></listitem>
   <listitem><para><xref linkend="create-web-policy-agent-profile" /></para></listitem>
   <listitem><para><xref linkend="install-web-policy-agent" /></para></listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>The procedures in this section are written for use on a Linux system.
  If you are running Microsoft Windows, adapt the examples accordingly.</para>

  <procedure xml:id="prepare-etc-hosts">
   <title>To Prepare Your Hosts File</title>

   <para>OpenAM requires that you use fully qualified domain names when
   protecting web resources. This is because OpenAM uses <link xlink:show="new"
   xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/HTTP_cookie">HTTP cookies</link>
   to keep track of sessions for single sign on, and setting and reading
   cookies depends on the server name and domain.</para>

   <para>You can get started with OpenAM however without setting up separate
   systems for each fully qualified domain name. Instead, give your system
   <literal>openam.example.com</literal> and <literal>www.example.com</literal>
   aliases by editing your <link xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hosts_(file)"
   xlink:show="new">hosts file</link>.</para>

   <para>Alternatively, if you already have DNS set up, you can use that
   instead of using your hosts file.</para>

   <step>
    <para>Add the aliases to your hosts file using your preferred text
    editor.</para>

    <screen>$ sudo vi /etc/hosts
Password:

### Edit /etc/hosts ###

$ cat /etc/hosts | grep openam
127.0.0.1    localhost openam.example.com www.example.com</screen>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <procedure xml:id="install-apache-http">
   <title>To Install Apache HTTP Server</title>

   <para>Apache HTTP Server is a popular web server, and one that is well
   supported by OpenAM's web policy agents. Apache HTTP Server might already
   be installed on your system, but since you are installing software only
   to get started with OpenAM, install the web server separately rather than
   modify any existing installations.</para>

   <para>Full installation instructions are available <link xlink:show="new"
   xlink:href="http://httpd.apache.org/docs/2.2/install.html">online</link>.
   The following steps are inspired by the <citetitle>Overview for the
   impatient</citetitle> for Apache HTTP Server 2.2 in the online
   documentation.</para>

   <step>
    <para>Make sure you have the tools installed to build Apache HTTP Server
    2.2 from source.</para>

    <para>On Linux distributions, you need development tools including the C
    compiler. How you install these depends on your distribution.</para>

    <para>This might work for Red Hat and CentOS distributions:</para>
    <screen># yum groupinstall 'Development Tools'</screen>

    <para>This might work for Ubuntu distributions:</para>
    <screen>$ sudo apt-get install build-essential checkinstall</screen>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>Download Apache HTTP Server 2.2 sources from <link xlink:show="new"
    xlink:href="http://httpd.apache.org/download.cgi">the Apache download
    page</link>.</para>

    <para>The OpenAM web policy agent requires Apache Portable Runtime 1.3 or
    later, so make sure you download Apache HTTP Server 2.2.9 or later.</para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>Extract the download.</para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>Configure the sources for compilation.</para>

    <para>The <option>--prefix</option> option can be used so that the
    web server is installed in a location where you can write files.</para>

    <screen>$ cd ~/Downloads/httpd-2.2.25
$ ./configure --prefix=/path/to/apache</screen>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>Compile Apache HTTP Server.</para>

    <screen>$ make</screen>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>Install Apache HTTP Server.</para>

    <screen>$ make install</screen>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>Edit the configuration to set the server name to
    <literal>www.example.com</literal> and the port to one such as 8000 that
    the web server process can use when starting with your user ID.</para>

    <screen>$ vi /path/to/apache/conf/httpd.conf
$ grep 8000 /path/to/apache/conf/httpd.conf
Listen 8000
ServerName www.example.com:8000</screen>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>Test that Apache HTTP Server is working.</para>
    
    <substeps>
     <step>
      <para>Start the web server.</para>
      
      <screen>$ /path/to/apache/bin/apachectl -k start</screen>
     </step>
     
     <step>
      <para>Browse to the home page, such as
      <literal>http://www.example.com:8000</literal>.</para>

      <mediaobject xml:id="figure-web-server-home-page">
       <alt>Apache HTTP Server home page stating It works!</alt>
       <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/web-server-home-page.png" format="PNG"/>
       </imageobject>
       <textobject>
        <para>If the web server works correctly, it displays a page stating,
        "It works!"</para>
       </textobject>
      </mediaobject>

      <para>This is the page to protect with OpenAM. Make sure you have
      successfully gotten to this point before you proceed.</para>
     </step>
    </substeps>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <procedure xml:id="install-apache-tomcat">
   <title>To Install Apache Tomcat</title>

   <para>OpenAM runs as a Java web application inside an application container.
   Apache Tomcat is one such application container that runs on a variety of
   platforms. The following instructions are loosely based on the
   <filename>RUNNING.txt</filename> file delivered with Tomcat.</para>

   <step>
    <para>Make sure you have a recent Java Development Kit release installed.</para>

    <para>One way of checking the version of the Java Development Kit is to
    list the version of the <command>javac</command> compiler.</para>

    <screen>$ javac -version</screen>

    <para>If the <command>javac</command> compiler is not found, then either
    you do not have a Java Development Kit installed, or it is installed but
    not on your <literal>PATH</literal>.</para>

    <para>The <link xlink:show="new" xlink:href="release-notes#java-requirements"
    xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"><citetitle>OpenAM Release
    Notes</citetitle></link> indicate what versions of Java Development Kit
    are supported. Supported Java Development Kit versions also work for Apache
    Tomcat.</para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>Download Apache Tomcat 7 from its <link xlink:show="new"
    xlink:href="http://tomcat.apache.org/download-70.cgi">download page</link>.</para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>Extract the download.</para>

    <screen>$ cd /path/to
$ unzip ~/Downloads/apache-tomcat-7.0.42.zip
$ mv apache-tomcat-7.0.42 tomcat</screen>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>On UNIX-like systems, make the scripts in Tomcat's
    <filename>bin/</filename> directory executable.</para>

    <screen>$ chmod +x /path/to/tomcat/bin/*.sh</screen>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>Set the <literal>JAVA_HOME</literal> environment variable to the
    file system location of the Java Development Kit.</para>

    <para>On Linux, you might set <literal>JAVA_HOME</literal> as follows.</para>
    <literallayout class="monospaced">export JAVA_HOME=/path/to/jdk</literallayout>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>Edit Tomcat's <filename>catalina.sh</filename> script to set the
    <literal>JAVA_HOME</literal> environment variable to the file system
    location of the Java Development Kit, and to set the heap and permanent
    generation size appropriately.</para>

    <screen>$ vi /path/to/tomcat/bin/catalina.sh
$ grep ^JAVA_HOME /path/to/tomcat/bin/catalina.sh
JAVA_HOME=/path/to/jdk
$ grep ^CATALINA /path/to/tomcat/bin/catalina.sh
CATALINA_OPTS="-Xmx1024m -XX:MaxPermSize=256m"</screen>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>Start Tomcat.</para>

    <screen>$ /path/to/tomcat/bin/startup.sh</screen>

    <para>It might take Tomcat several seconds to start. When Tomcat has
    successfully started, you should see an informational message indicating
    how long initialization took in the
    <filename>/path/to/tomcat/logs/catalina.out</filename> log file:</para>

    <literallayout class="monospaced"
    >INFO: Initialization processed in 4655 ms</literallayout>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>Browse to Tomcat's home page, such as
    <literal>http://openam.example.com:8080</literal>.</para>

    <mediaobject xml:id="figure-tomcat-home-page">
     <alt>Apache Tomcat home page</alt>
     <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="images/tomcat-home-page.png" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <textobject>
      <para>If Apache Tomcat works correctly, it displays a page stating,
      "If you're seeing this, you've successfully installed Tomcat.
      Congratulations!"</para>
     </textobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <para>Apache Tomcat is going to serve the OpenAM web application. Make sure
    you have successfully gotten to this point before you proceed.</para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <procedure xml:id="install-openam">
   <title>To Install OpenAM</title>

   <para>OpenAM is a web application that you deploy into Apache Tomcat and then
   configure for use.</para>

   <step>
    <para>Download the OpenAM .war (web archive) file either from the ForgeRock
    <link xlink:show="new" xlink:href="http://forgerock.com/download-stack/"
    ><citetitle>Enterprise Downloads</citetitle></link> page, or from the
    project nightly <link xlink:href="http://forgerock.org/openam.html"
    xlink:show="new"><citetitle>Builds</citetitle></link> page.</para>

    <para>Enterprise downloads are tested, stable releases.</para>

    <para>Nightly builds include the very latest features, but are not
    thoroughly tested. Some functionality might not be finished.</para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>Deploy the .war file in Tomcat as <filename>openam.war</filename>.</para>

    <screen>$ mv ~/Downloads/openam*.war /path/to/tomcat/webapps/openam.war</screen>

    <para>Tomcat deploys OpenAM under the
    <filename>/path/to/tomcat/webapps/openam/</filename> directory, and you can
    access the web application in a browser at
    <literal>http://openam.example.com:8080/openam/</literal>.</para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>Browse to OpenAM where it is deployed in Tomcat, for example
    <literal>http://openam.example.com:8080/openam/</literal>, to configure
    the application.</para>

    <mediaobject xml:id="figure-openam-home-page">
     <alt>OpenAM home page</alt>
     <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="images/openam-home-page.png" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <textobject>
      <para>The very first time you visit the OpenAM home page, you can choose
      either Default Configuration or Custom Configuration.</para>
     </textobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>On the OpenAM home page, click the link to Create Default
    Configuration, set the Default User [amAdmin] password to
    <literal>password</literal> and the Default Policy Agent [UrlAccessAgent]
    password to <literal>secret12</literal>, and then click Create
    Configuration to configure OpenAM.</para>

    <mediaobject xml:id="figure-openam-default-configuration">
     <alt>OpenAM Default Configuration</alt>
     <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="images/openam-default-configuration.png" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <textobject>
      <para>The Default Configuration is the quickest way to configure OpenAM.</para>
     </textobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <para>If you were configuring OpenAM for real-world use, you would not use
    either of those passwords, but this is only to get started with OpenAM. The
    <literal>amadmin</literal> user is the OpenAM administrator, who is like
    a super user in that <literal>amadmin</literal> has full control over
    the OpenAM configuration.</para>

    <para>The <literal>UrlAccessAgent</literal> is not used in this guide.</para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>When you see the Configuration Complete! dialog, click the Proceed to
    Login link, and then log in as <literal>amadmin</literal> with password
    <literal>password</literal>.</para>

    <para>After login, OpenAM should direct you to the console at
    <literal>http://openam.example.com:8080/openam/console</literal> and then
    to the common tasks page.</para>

    <mediaobject xml:id="figure-openam-common-tasks">
     <alt>OpenAM Common Tasks</alt>
     <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="images/openam-common-tasks.png" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <textobject>
      <para>The home page for the OpenAM Console shows links to common
      administrative tasks.</para>
     </textobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <para>In your home directory, you find that OpenAM has stored its
    configuration, including the embedded OpenDJ directory server, in a
    folder named after the server instance, <filename>~/openam/</filename>. It
    has also added a hidden folder, <filename>~/.openamcfg/</filename>, with
    a file used by OpenAM when it starts up. If you ruin your configuration
    of OpenAM somehow, the quickest way to start over is to stop Tomcat,
    delete these two folders, and configure OpenAM again.</para>

    <para>OpenAM core server and OpenAM Console is now configured. Make sure
    you have successfully logged in to OpenAM Console before you proceed.</para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <procedure xml:id="configure-policy">
   <title>To Configure a Policy in OpenAM</title>

   <para>OpenAM authenticates users and then makes authorization decisions.
   The authorization decisions are based on access policies that indicate
   who can do what, when, and under what conditions. Follow these steps to
   create a policy that allows all authenticated users to perform an HTTP GET
   (for example, to browse) the Apache HTTP home page that you set up
   earlier.</para>

   <step>
    <para>In OpenAM Console, click the Access Control tab, then in the Realms
    table click the link to / (Top Level Realm).</para>

    <para>OpenAM allows you to organize identities, policies, and policy agent
    profiles into realms as described in the <citetitle>Administration
    Guide</citetitle> chapter, <link xlink:show="new"
    xlink:href="admin-guide#chap-realms"
    xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"><citetitle>Configuring
    Realms</citetitle></link>. For now, use the default top level realm.</para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>In the Console page for the top level realm, click the Policies tab,
    and then click New Policy.</para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>Give your new policy the name <literal>Authenticated users can get
    Apache HTTP home page</literal>.</para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>In the Rules table, click New, select URL Policy Agent (with
    resource name), click Next, and then create a rule for resource
    <literal>http://www.example.com:8000/</literal> that allows HTTP GET, and
    then click Finish to save your work.</para>

    <mediaobject xml:id="figure-openam-policy-rule">
     <alt>OpenAM Policy Rule</alt>
     <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="images/openam-policy-rule.png" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <textobject>
      <para>Create a rule as described in the instructions.</para>
     </textobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <para>OpenAM applies this rule to subjects that you specify next.</para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>In the Subjects table, click New, select Authenticated Users and
    click Next, then name your rule <literal>All Authenticated Users</literal>,
    and click Finish to save your work.</para>

    <mediaobject xml:id="figure-openam-policy-subjects">
     <alt>OpenAM Policy Subjects</alt>
     <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="images/openam-policy-subjects.png" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <textobject>
      <para>Create a subject setting as described in the instructions.</para>
     </textobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <para>Your policy now specifies who (subject) can perform what actions on
    what resources (rule). You can ignore Conditions and Response Providers
    for now.</para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>On the Edit Policy page, click OK to save your policy.</para>

    <para>Next you must create a web policy agent profile before installing
    the agent in Apache HTTP Server to enforce your new policy.</para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <procedure xml:id="create-web-policy-agent-profile">
   <title>To Create a Web Policy Agent Profile</title>

   <para>OpenAM stores profile information about policy agents centrally by
   default. You can then manage the policy agent profile through OpenAM Console.
   The policy agent can retrieve its configuration from its OpenAM profile at
   installation time and when it starts up, and OpenAM can notify the policy
   agent of changes to its configuration. Following these steps before
   installing the policy agent itself.</para>

   <step>
    <para>In OpenAM Console, browse to Access Control > / (Top Level Realm) >
    Agents > Web, and then click New in the Agents table.</para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>In the page to configure your new web policy agent, set the following
    values.</para>

    <variablelist>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Name</term>
      <listitem>
       <para><literal>WebAgent</literal></para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>

     <varlistentry>
      <term>Password</term>
      <listitem>
       <para><literal>password</literal></para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>

     <varlistentry>
      <term>Configuration</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>Keep the default, <literal>Centralized</literal></para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>

     <varlistentry>
      <term>Server URL</term>
      <listitem>
       <para><literal>http://openam.example.com:8080/openam</literal></para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>

     <varlistentry>
      <term>Agent URL</term>
      <listitem>
       <para><literal>http://www.example.com:8000</literal></para>

       <para>8000 is the port number you set previously for Apache HTTP
       Server.</para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <mediaobject xml:id="figure-web-agent-profile">
     <alt>New Web Agent Profile</alt>
     <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="images/web-agent-profile.png" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <textobject>
      <para>Create a web policy agent profile as described in the instructions.</para>
     </textobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>Click Create to save the new web policy agent profile in OpenAM.</para>

    <para>Next you must install a policy agent in Apache HTTP Server to enforce
    your new policy.</para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <procedure xml:id="install-web-policy-agent">
   <title>To Install OpenAM Web Policy Agent</title>

   <para>OpenAM policy agents enforce policies defined in OpenAM. The agent's
   job is to make sure that users have the right to access resources they
   request. And yet the agent does not make the policy decisions. Instead, the
   agent calls on OpenAM for policy decisions, using the information presented
   by the user (or the user's client application), such as the single sign on
   token in the HTTP cookie that OpenAM uses to keep track of user sessions.
   In essence the agent is a gatekeeper for OpenAM.</para>

   <para>The agent runs inside of Apache HTTP Server as a library that the
   server loads at startup time. When a request comes in, the agent redirects
   users to OpenAM for authentication and calls on OpenAM for policy decisions
   as necessary.</para>

   <step>
    <para>Download the OpenAM policy agent for your version of Apache HTTP
    Server either from the ForgeRock <link xlink:show="new"
    xlink:href="http://forgerock.com/download-stack/"
    ><citetitle>Enterprise Downloads</citetitle></link> page, or from the
    project nightly <link xlink:href="http://forgerock.org/openam.html"
    xlink:show="new"><citetitle>Builds</citetitle></link> page.</para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>Create a password file that the agent installer reads when first
    connecting to OpenAM to read its profile.</para>

    <para>The password file should be read-only by the user who installs
    the policy agent.</para>

    <screen>$ echo password > /tmp/pwd.txt
$ chmod 400 /tmp/pwd.txt</screen>

    <para>The password is stored encrypted after installation.</para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>Make sure OpenAM is running.</para>

    <para>You can check for example by logging into OpenAM Console.</para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>Stop Apache HTTP Server while you install the policy agent.</para>

    <screen>$ /path/to/apache/bin/apachectl stop</screen>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>Extract the download.</para>

    <screen>$ cd /path/to
$ unzip ~/Downloads/apache_v22_Linux_agent*.zip</screen>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>Install the web policy agent in Apache HTTP Server, making sure that
    you provide the correct information to the installer as shown in the
    following example.</para>

    <screen>$ cd /path/to/web_agents/apache22_agent/bin
$ ./agentadmin --install
...

-----------------------------------------------
SUMMARY OF YOUR RESPONSES
-----------------------------------------------
Apache Server Config Directory : /path/to/apache/conf
OpenAM server URL : http://openam.example.com:8080/openam
Agent URL : http://www.example.com:8000
Agent Profile name : WebAgent
Agent Profile Password file name : /tmp/pwd.txt

...</screen>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>Start Apache HTTP Server, and check that the web policy agent seems
    to be correctly configured.</para>

    <screen>$ /path/to/apache/bin/apachectl -k start
$ tail /path/to/apache/logs/error_log
...[notice] Apache/2.2.25 (Unix) Web Policy Agent/3.0 configured -- resuming
 normal operations</screen>

    <para>Assuming everything up to now has worked correctly, you can now try
    your installation to see OpenAM in action.</para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </section>

 <section xml:id="try-it-out">
  <title>Trying It Out</title>

  <orderedlist>
   <para>Now that you have completed <xref linkend="software-setup" />,
   you can try accessing the protected web page to see OpenAM at work.</para>

   <listitem>
    <para>Log out of OpenAM Console so that you can see the need to login when
    you try to access the Apache "It works!" page.</para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>Browse to <literal>http://www.example.com:8000</literal> to attempt
    to access the Apache "It works!" page.</para>

    <para>At this point, the policy agent intercepts your request for the page.
    Your browser does not return a cookie indicating an OpenAM session, so the
    policy agent redirects you to OpenAM to authenticate.</para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>Log in as the built-in default OpenAM demonstration user
    <literal>demo</literal> with password <literal>changeit</literal>.</para>

    <mediaobject xml:id="figure-openam-login">
     <alt>OpenAM Login Page</alt>
     <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="images/openam-login.png" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <textobject>
      <para>Log in as the default demonstration user as described in the
      instructions.</para>
     </textobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <para>On successful login, OpenAM sets a session cookie named
    <literal>iPlanetDirectoryPro</literal> in your browser for the domain
    <literal>.example.com</literal>. The cookie is then returned to servers
    in the <literal>example.com</literal> domain such as
    <literal>openam.example.com</literal> and
    <literal>www.example.com</literal>.</para>

    <para>If you examine this cookie in your browser, you notice that it has
    a value such as
    <literal>AQIC5wM2LY4SfcwciyfvJcQDUIB7kIWEH187Df_txqLdAVc.*AAJTSQACMDEAAlNLABMxMDYwNzY1MjQ0NTE0ODI2NTkx*</literal>.
    This is the SSO Token value. The value is in fact an encrypted reference to
    the session that is stored only by OpenAM. So only OpenAM can determine
    whether you are actually logged in, or instead that the session is no longer
    valid and you need to authenticate again.</para>

    <para>The OpenAM session is used for single sign on. When the browser
    presents the cookie to a server in the domain, the agent on the server can
    check with OpenAM using the SSO Token as a reference to the session. This
    allows OpenAM to make policy decisions based on who is authenticated, or
    to prompt for additional authentication as necessary.</para>

    <para>Your single sign on session can end in a few ways.  For example, when
    examining the cookie in your browser, you should notice that it expires when
    the browser session ends (when you shut down your browser). Alternatively,
    you can log out of OpenAM explicitly. Sessions can also expire. OpenAM
    sets two limits, one that causes your session to expire if it remains
    inactive for a configurable period of time (default: 30 minutes), and
    another that caps the session lifetime (default: 2 hours).</para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>After successful login, notice that you are redirected to the Apache
    "It works!" page.</para>

    <mediaobject xml:id="figure-web-server-home-page-again">
     <alt>Apache HTTP Server home page stating It works!</alt>
     <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="images/web-server-home-page.png" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <textobject>
      <para>If everything works correctly you see the "It works!" page after
      successful login.</para>
     </textobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <para>In the background, OpenAM redirected your browser again to the page
    you tried to access originally, <literal>http://www.example.com:8000</literal>.
    This time the web policy agent intercepted the request and found the SSO
    Token, so it could request a policy decision from OpenAM regarding whether
    the user with the SSO Token has access to get
    <literal>http://www.example.com:8000/</literal>. OpenAM replied to the policy
    agent that it could allow access, and the policy agent allowed Apache HTTP
    Server to send back the web page.</para>
   </listitem>
  </orderedlist>

   <para>Congratulations on protecting your first web site with OpenAM! Notice
   that you had only to install software and to configure things in OpenAM. You
   did not have to change your web site at all in order to add single sign on
   and to set up access policies.</para>

   <para>OpenAM can do much more than protect web pages. Read the next chapter
   to learn more.</para>
 </section>
</chapter>
