<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ! CCPL HEADER START
  !
  ! This work is licensed under the Creative Commons
  ! Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 3.0 Unported License.
  ! To view a copy of this license, visit
  ! http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/
  ! or send a letter to Creative Commons, 444 Castro Street,
  ! Suite 900, Mountain View, California, 94041, USA.
  !
  ! You can also obtain a copy of the license at
  ! src/main/resources/legal-notices/CC-BY-NC-ND.txt.
  ! See the License for the specific language governing permissions
  ! and limitations under the License.
  !
  ! If applicable, add the following below this CCPL HEADER, with the fields
  ! enclosed by brackets "[]" replaced with your own identifying information:
  !      Portions Copyright [yyyy] [name of copyright owner]
  !
  ! CCPL HEADER END
  !
  !      Copyright 2013 ForgeRock AS
  !
-->
<chapter xml:id='chap-where-to-go-from-here'
         xmlns='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook'
         version='5.0'
         xml:lang='en'
         xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'
         xsi:schemaLocation='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook
          http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd'
         xmlns:xlink='http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink'>
 <title>Where To Go From Here</title>

 <para>OpenAM can do much more than protect web pages. In addition to being
 the right foundation for building highly available, Internet-scale access
 management services, OpenAM has a rich set of features that make it the right
 choice for a variety of different deployments. This chapter describes some of
 the features of OpenAM and indicates where in the documentation you can find
 out more about them.</para>

 <section xml:id="user-self-service-features">
  <title>User Self-Service Features</title>

  <para>The easier it is for users to handle their own registration, to reset
  forgotten passwords, and to access the applications they need without a call
  to your help desk, the more you save when supporting them for these
  tasks.</para>

  <para>OpenAM has access to the identity repositories where user profiles are
  stored. OpenAM is therefore well placed to help you manage self-service
  features that involve user profiles.</para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>OpenAM provides user self-registration as an authentication module
    and also as a feature of OpenAM's REST APIs. New users can safely sign up
    in OpenAM without your administrators or help desk having to get
    involved.</para>

    <para>For information on configuring self-registration as an authentication
    module, see the <citetitle>Administration Guide</citetitle> section,
    <link xlink:show="new" xlink:href="admin-guide#membership-module-conf-hints"
    xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"><citetitle>Hints For the
    Membership Authentication Module</citetitle></link>. You then specify
    the module in the link to your "sign up" page.</para>

    <para>For details on building your own self-registration application using
    the REST API, see the <citetitle>Developer's Guide</citetitle> section,
    <link xlink:show="new" xlink:href="dev-guide#rest-api-self-registration"
    xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"><citetitle>User
    Self-Registration</citetitle></link>.</para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>OpenAM can help users reset their passwords on their own. OpenAM
    handles both the case where a user knows their password and wants to change
    it, and also the case where the user has forgotten their password and needs
    to reset it, possibly after answering security questions.</para>

    <para>For details on setting up password reset capabilities, see the
    <citetitle>Administration Guide</citetitle> chapter, <link xlink:show="new"
    xlink:href="admin-guide#chap-pwd-reset"
    xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"><citetitle>Configuring
    Password Reset</citetitle></link>.</para>

    <para>For details on building your own application to handle password reset
    using the REST API, see the <citetitle>Developer's Guide</citetitle> section,
    <link xlink:show="new" xlink:href="dev-guide#rest-api-password-reset"
    xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"><citetitle>Resetting
    Forgotten Passwords</citetitle></link>.</para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>Users often have a number of applications assigned to them, especially
    if your organization has standardized on software as a service, for example
    for email, document sharing, support ticketing, customer relationship
    management, web conferencing, and so forth. It can be handy to present these
    applications on a user's web-based dashboard with the user's profile, and
    to assign applications to the user's dashboard automatically based on the
    user's profile.</para>

    <para>The OpenAM cloud dashboard service makes this relatively easy to
    set up. For basic information on using the service, see the
    <citetitle>Administration Guide</citetitle> chapter, <link xlink:show="new"
    xlink:href="admin-guide#chap-dashboard"
    xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"><citetitle>Configuring the
    Dashboard Service</citetitle></link>.</para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>OpenAM's user-facing pages are fully customizable and easy to skin
  for your organization. The <link xlink:show="new"
  xlink:href="install-guide#install-guide"
  xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"><citetitle>Installation
  Guide</citetitle></link> has details on how to customize user-facing
  pages.</para>
 </section>

 <section xml:id="sso-features">
  <title>Single Sign On</title>

  <para>Single sign on (SSO) is a core feature of OpenAM. Once you have set up
  OpenAM you protect as many applications in the network domain as you want.
  Simply install policy agents for the additional servers, and add policies
  for the resources served by the applications. Users can then authenticate
  to start a session on any site in the domain, and they remain authenticated
  for all sites in the domain. No need to log in again (unless the session
  ends, or unless a policy requires stronger authentication). See the
  <citetitle>Administration Guide</citetitle> chapter, <link xlink:show="new"
  xlink:href="admin-guide#chap-sso"
  xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"><citetitle>Configuring
  Single Sign-On within One Domain</citetitle></link> for details.</para>

  <para>Many organizations manage more than one domain. When you have multiple
  distinct domains in a single organization, cookies set in one domain are not
  returned to servers in another domain. Also in many organizations, sub-domains
  are controlled independently, leading to the need to protect against someone
  setting up a rogue sub-domain to hijack session cookies. OpenAM's cross
  domain single sign on (CDSSO) provides a safe mechanism for your OpenAM
  servers in one domain to work with policy agents from other domains,
  protecting against potential session cookie hijacking. CDSSO allows users to
  sign on in one of your domains and not have to sign on again when they visit
  another of your domains.</para>

  <para>CDSSO works through cooperation between policy agents and the
  <literal>CDCServlet</literal> in OpenAM. Together, the policy agents and
  OpenAM use federation capabilities to translate from one domain to another.
  For details on how to configure policy agents for CDSSO, see the
  <citetitle>Administration Guide</citetitle> chapter, <link xlink:show="new"
  xlink:href="admin-guide#chap-cdsso"
  xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"><citetitle>Configuring
  Cross-Domain Single Sign On</citetitle></link>.</para>
 </section>

 <section xml:id="federation">
  <title>Standards-Based Federation</title>

  <para>When you need to federate identities across not just different domains
  but instead across different organizations with separate access management
  solutions, then you need interoperable federation technologies. Perhaps your
  organization acts as an identity provider for other organizations providing
  services. Perhaps you provide the services and allow users to use their
  identity from another organization to access your services. Either way OpenAM
  has the capability to integrate well in federated access management
  scenarios.</para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <para>OpenAM supports standards-based federation technologies.</para>

   <listitem>
    <para>Security Assertion Markup Language (SAML) 2.0 grew out of earlier
    work on SAML 1.x and in the Liberty Alliance. SAML defines XML-based,
    standard formats and profiles for federating identities. SAML 2.0 is
    supported by a wide range of applications including major software as a
    service (SaaS) offerings. OpenAM supports SAML 2.0 and earlier standards,
    and can function as a hub in deployments where different standards are
    used. For details on OpenAM's SAML 2.0 capabilities, see the
    <citetitle>Administration Guide</citetitle> chapter, <link xlink:show="new"
    xlink:href="admin-guide#chap-federation"
    xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"><citetitle>Managing SAML
    2.0 Federation</citetitle></link>.</para>

    <para>When your deployment serves as an identity provider for a SAML
    federation, OpenAM makes it easy to develop applications called Fedlets that
    your service providers can easily deploy to participate in the federation.
    For details see the <citetitle>Developer's Guide</citetitle> chapters,
    <link xlink:show="new" xlink:href="dev-guide#chap-fedlet-java"
    xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"><citetitle>Using Fedlets
    in Java Web Applications</citetitle></link> and <link xlink:show="new"
    xlink:href="dev-guide#chap-fedlet-dotnet"
    xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"><citetitle>Using Fedlets
    in .NET Web Applications</citetitle></link>.</para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>OAuth 2.0 and OpenID Connect 1.0 are open standards for authorization
    using REST APIs to allow users to authorize third-party access to their
    resources. These standards make it easier to federate modern web
    applications. OAuth for example is widely used in social applications.</para>

    <para>OpenAM offers support both for OAuth 2.0 and also for OpenID Connect
    1.0. OpenAM can play the roles of authorization server and of client in
    OAuth 2.0, while managing the profiles of the resource owners. When acting
    as a client, OpenAM policy agents can be used on resource servers to enforce
    authorization. For details see the <citetitle>Administration Guide</citetitle>
    chapter, <link xlink:show="new" xlink:href="admin-guide#chap-oauth2"
    xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"><citetitle>Managing OAuth
    2.0 Authorization</citetitle></link>.</para>

    <para>OpenAM can play the OpenID Connect 1.0 provider role as well, with
    support for Basic and Implicit client profiles as well as discovery,
    dynamic registration, and session management. For details see the
    <citetitle>Administration Guide</citetitle> chapter, <link xlink:show="new"
    xlink:href="admin-guide#chap-openid-connect"
    xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"><citetitle>Managing OpenID
    Connect 1.0 Authorization</citetitle></link>.</para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </section>

 <section xml:id="policy-and-xacml">
  <title>Access Policies</title>

  <para>In the first chapter of this guide you created an OpenAM access policy
  and saw how it worked. OpenAM can handle large numbers of access policies,
  each of which gives you centralized control over who can access what
  resources, when, and under what circumstances. For details see the
  <citetitle>Administration Guide</citetitle> chapter, <link xlink:show="new"
  xlink:href="admin-guide#chap-authz-policy"
  xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"><citetitle>Defining
  Authorization Policies</citetitle></link>.</para>

  <para>OpenAM also supports standards-based access policies defined using the
  eXtensible Access Control Markup Language (XACML). XACML defines an XML
  Attribute-Based Access Control (ABAC) language with Role-Based Access Control
  (RBAC) features as well. For details on using XACML policies with OpenAM see
  the <citetitle>Administration Guide</citetitle> chapter, <link
  xlink:show="new" xlink:href="admin-guide#chap-entitlements"
  xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"><citetitle>Defining
  Entitlements</citetitle></link>.</para>
 </section>

 <section xml:id="protect-any-application">
  <title>Protect Any Web Application</title>

  <para>In the first chapter of the guide you installed a web policy agent to
  enforce OpenAM's authorization decisions on Apache HTTP Server. That web
  policy agent is only one of many policy agents that work with OpenAM.
  As described in the <citetitle>Administration Guide</citetitle> chapter, <link
  xlink:show="new" xlink:href="admin-guide#chap-agents"
  xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"><citetitle>Configuring Policy
  Agent Profiles</citetitle></link>, you find policy agents for different web
  servers, for a variety of Java EE web application containers, for protecting
  SOAP-based web services, and for OAuth 2.0 clients.</para>

  <para>For details about web policy agents also see the <link xlink:show="new"
  xlink:href="web-install-guide#web-install-guide"
  xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"><citetitle>Web Policy Agent
  Installation Guide</citetitle></link>.</para>

  <para>For details about Java EE policy agents also see the
  <link xlink:show="new" xlink:href="jee-install-guide#jee-install-guide"
  xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"><citetitle>Java EE Policy
  Agent Installation Guide</citetitle></link>.</para>

  <para>Furthermore <link xlink:show="new" xlink:href="http://openig.forgerock.org"
  >OpenIG Identity Gateway</link> works with applications where you want to
  protect access, but you cannot install a policy agent. For example, you might
  have a web application running in a server for which no policy agent has been
  developed. Or you might be protecting an application where you simply cannot
  install a policy agent. In that case, OpenIG functions as a flexible reverse
  proxy with standard SAML 2.0 capabilities. For details see the <link
  xlink:show="new" xlink:href="http://docs.forgerock.org/en/openig/"
  ><citetitle>OpenIG documentation</citetitle></link>.</para>
 </section>

 <section xml:id="modern-api">
  <title>Modern APIs For Developers</title>

  <itemizedlist>
   <para>For client application developers, OpenAM offers REST, Java, and C
   APIs.</para>

   <listitem>
    <para>OpenAM REST APIs make the common CRUD (create, read, update,
    delete) easy to use in modern web applications. They also offer extended
    actions and query capabilities for access management functionality.</para>

    <para>To get started, see the <citetitle>Developer's Guide</citetitle>
    chapter, <link xlink:show="new" xlink:href="dev-guide#chap-rest"
    xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"><citetitle>Using RESTful
    Web Services</citetitle></link>.</para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>OpenAM Java APIs provided through the OpenAM Java SDK let your Java
    and Java EE applications call on OpenAM for authentication and authorization
    in both OpenAM and federated environments.</para>

    <para>To get started, see the <citetitle>Developer's Guide</citetitle>
    chapter, <link xlink:show="new" xlink:href="dev-guide#chap-jdk"
    xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"><citetitle>Using the
    OpenAM Java SDK</citetitle></link>.</para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>The OpenAM C SDK provides APIs for native applications, such as new
    web server policy agents. The C SDK is built for Linux, Solaris, and Windows
    platforms.</para>

    <para>To get started, see the <citetitle>Developer's Guide</citetitle>
    chapter, <link xlink:show="new" xlink:href="dev-guide#chap-csdk"
    xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"><citetitle>Using the
    OpenAM C API</citetitle></link>.</para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>OpenAM provides built-in support for many identity repositories,
  web servers and web application containers, access management standards,
  and all the flexible, configurable capabilities mentioned in this chapter.
  Yet, for some deployments you might still need to extend what OpenAM can do.
  For such cases OpenAM defines Service Provider Interfaces (SPIs) where you
  can integrate your own plugins. See the <citetitle>Developer's Guide</citetitle>
  section, <link xlink:show="new" xlink:href="dev-guide#openam-spis"
  xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"><citetitle>OpenAM
  SPIs</citetitle></link>, for a list of extension points, and the related
  documentation in that guide for examples.</para>
 </section>

 <section xml:id="getting-help">
  <title>Getting Help With Your Project</title>

  <para>You can purchase OpenAM support subscriptions and training courses
  from ForgeRock and from consulting partners around the world and in your
  area. To contact ForgeRock, send mail to <link
  xlink:href="mailto:info@forgerock.com">info@forgerock.com</link>. To find a
  partner in your area, see <link xlink:show="new"
  xlink:href="http://forgerock.com/partners/find-a-partner/" />.</para>
 </section>
</chapter>
