<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ! CCPL HEADER START
  !
  ! This work is licensed under the Creative Commons
  ! Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 3.0 Unported License.
  ! To view a copy of this license, visit
  ! http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/
  ! or send a letter to Creative Commons, 444 Castro Street,
  ! Suite 900, Mountain View, California, 94041, USA.
  !
  ! You can also obtain a copy of the license at
  ! src/main/resources/legal-notices/CC-BY-NC-ND.txt.
  ! See the License for the specific language governing permissions
  ! and limitations under the License.
  !
  ! If applicable, add the following below this CCPL HEADER, with the fields
  ! enclosed by brackets "[]" replaced with your own identifying information:
  !      Portions Copyright [yyyy] [name of copyright owner]
  !
  ! CCPL HEADER END
  !
  !      Copyright 2011-2013 ForgeRock, Inc.
  !    
-->
<chapter xml:id='chap-whats-new'
 xmlns='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook' version='5.0' xml:lang='en'
 xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'
 xsi:schemaLocation='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd'
 xmlns:xlink='http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink'
 xmlns:xinclude='http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude'>
 <title>What's New in OpenAM <?eval ${serverDocTargetVersion}?></title>

 <para>OpenAM <?eval ${serverDocTargetVersion}?> fixes a number of issues, and
 provides the following additional features.</para>

 <itemizedlist>
  <title>Major New Features</title>

   <listitem>
    <para>New, more modern RESTful web services are available for
    authentication, identity management, profile management, session management,
    Integrated Windows Authentication, and more. New endpoints are available
    under the URI <literal>/json</literal> where OpenAM is deployed, and are
    demonstrated in the <citetitle>Developer Guide</citetitle> chapter on <link
    xlink:href="dev-guide#chap-rest" xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"
    xlink:show="new"><citetitle>Using RESTful Web Services</citetitle></link>
    in OpenAM.</para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>All of the web policy agents have been updated to include support for Internet
    Protocol version 6 (IPv6) support, in addition to support for IPv4. <!--include in the notes when 
    AME-1134 is closed, which includes removing unused libraries.--></para>
    <para>IPv6 replaces IPv4 to fix the problems of IPv4 address exhaustion. The new 
    protocol version increases the number of available internet addresses by using 
    128-bit addresses instead of the 32-bit addresses of IPv4.</para>
   </listitem>

  <listitem>
   <para>The policy tree index has been updated so that resources first check the root
   level of a realm first. The tree will be created from this level, and any subsequent
   referrals will create another tree specific to the realm where the referral was
   retrieved. This conserves memory and reduces the amount of time required to load
   the tree. An intelligent indexing model now assists with quickly identifying relevant
   policy rules for the resource being authorized.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
   <para>OpenAM now provides further support for OAuth 2.0. In addition
   to playing the role of client and resource server, OpenAM can now also
   play the role of OAuth 2.0 authorization server. See <link
   xlink:href="admin-guide#chap-oauth2"
   xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"><citetitle>Managing OAuth
   2.0 Authorization</citetitle></link> for explanations, instructions,
   and examples.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
   <para>Session failover has been modified to be simpler to deploy (<link
   xlink:href="https://bugster.forgerock.org/jira/browse/OPENAM-625"
   xlink:show="new">OPENAM-625</link>). OpenAM 10.0.1 and earlier required the
   use of Open Message Queue and Berkeley DB Java Edition, which increased the
   complexity and amount of time required to get session failover working.
   OpenAM now writes session data to the configuration data store instead.
   This implementation also can be used to make sessions persist across restart
   for single OpenAM servers. The current implementation requires that you use
   OpenDJ for the configuration data store.</para>

   <para>This new implementation is designed to operate on a local site network.
   Cross-site session failover and session failover across wide area networks
   (WANs) are not supported.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
   <para>IBM<superscript>®</superscript> WebSphere<superscript>®</superscript>
   8.0 is now a supported platform. See <link
   xlink:href="install-guide#prepare-ibm-websphere"
   xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"><citetitle>Preparing IBM
   WebSphere</citetitle></link> in the <citetitle>Installation Guide</citetitle>
   for details on how to setup WebSphere 8.0 and 8.5 before deploying 
   OpenAM.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
   <para>Legacy naming conventions have been changed to conform to the
   current product name, OpenAM. This includes the OpenAM bootstrap file
   (<link xlink:href="https://bugster.forgerock.org/jira/browse/OPENAM-1555"
   xlink:show="new">OPENAM-1555</link>). <filename>$HOME/.openamcfg/</filename>
   is the new name for <filename>$HOME/.openssocfg/</filename>. If you upgrade,
   OpenAM still supports use of <filename>$HOME/.openssocfg/</filename>, and
   does not rename the folder. For new OpenAM installs, OpenAM creates the
   directory with the new name, <filename>$HOME/.openamcfg/</filename>, at
   configuration time. Other files, such as the <filename>openam.war</filename>
   file, and paths have been modified to ensure consistency with the naming
   conventions.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
   <para>OpenAM now supports <link xlink:show="new"
   xlink:href="http://www.openauthentication.org/">Open Authentication</link>
   (<link xlink:href="https://bugster.forgerock.org/jira/browse/OPENAM-727"
   xlink:show="new">OPENAM-727</link>). The module provides the user with a
   one-time password based either on a HMAC one-time password or a time-based
   one-time password. OATH lets you determine which type of one-time password
   is best for your users when they need to login with a password generating
   device. Devices can range from a smartphone to a dedicated device, such as
   YubiKey or any other OATH compliant device.</para>

   <para>With OATH, OpenAM now supports YubiKey<superscript>®</superscript>
   authentication. The YubiKey simplifies the process of logging in with a One
   Time Password token as it does not require the user to re-type long pass
   codes from a display device into the login field of the computer. The
   YubiKey is inserted in the USB-port of any computer and the OTP is generated
   and automatically entered with a simple touch of a button on the YubiKey,
   and without the need of any client software or drivers.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para>OpenAM now supports (<link
                 xlink:href="https://bugster.forgerock.org/jira/browse/OPENAM-1375"
                 xlink:show="new">OPENAM-1375</link>)the Device Print adaptive authentication module.
             The module can use various characteristics of a system, including installed
             fonts, screen resolution, timezone, and geolocation to uniquely identify a
             system. The Device Print module includes all of the functionality associated
             with the HOTP authentication module.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para>OpenAM now supports the Core Token Service version 2 (CTSv2), with a more
    generalized token storage format. This covers all CTS areas including sessions,
    SAML Tokens, and OAuth Tokens. A new LDAP schema has been defined which is in
    addition to the existing schema.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
    <para>The C SDK for OpenAM has been simplified. The packages are all available as
    ZIP files, for Linux, Solaris x86, Solaris SPARC, and Windows operating systems, for
    both 32- and 64-bit varieties.</para>
  </listitem>

 </itemizedlist>

 <itemizedlist>
  <title>Additional New Features</title>

  <listitem>
    <para>OpenID now adds support for OpenID Connect 1.0.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
   <para>The zero page login has been modified so that administrators can disable the
   functionality. The zero page login process is the ability of the user to login
   using only GET parameters, which presents a possible security issue. Zero page 
   login is now disabled by default (<link
   xlink:href="https://bugster.forgerock.org/jira/browse/OPENAM-2354"
   xlink:show="new">OPENAM-2354</link>).</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
   <!-- AME-219 and CR-889 -->
   <para>OpenAM now provides an account expiration post authentication plugin to
   set an account expiration date on successful login.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
   <!-- AME-1652: Update DJ from 2.4.6 to 2.6 -->
   <para>OpenAM now bundles OpenDJ 2.6.</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
   <para>The AMLoginModule now lets authentication modules retrieve the list of
   current session tokens for a user (<link
   xlink:href="https://bugster.forgerock.org/jira/browse/OPENAM-1721"
   xlink:show="new">OPENAM-1721</link>).</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
   <para>OpenAM's IDPAdapter now provides additional hooks for customization.
   This improvement introduces changes to the API that affect custom IDPAdapters
   (<link xlink:href="https://bugster.forgerock.org/jira/browse/OPENAM-1623"
   xlink:show="new">OPENAM-1623</link>).</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
   <para>When running as a Service Provider, OpenAM no longer requires
   that you enable module-based authentication (<link
   xlink:href="https://bugster.forgerock.org/jira/browse/OPENAM-1470"
   xlink:show="new">OPENAM-1470</link>).</para>
  </listitem>

  <!-- Unresolved for Xpress
  <listitem>
   <para>The OATH authentication module now implements resynchronization
   for TOTP (<link
   xlink:href="https://bugster.forgerock.org/jira/browse/OPENAM-1462"
   xlink:show="new">OPENAM-1462</link>).</para>
  </listitem>
  -->

  <listitem>
   <para>OpenAM now has better support for using a reverse proxy for federation
   when DAS is also deployed (<link
   xlink:href="https://bugster.forgerock.org/jira/browse/OPENAM-1454"
   xlink:show="new">OPENAM-1454</link>).</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
   <para>OpenAM now allows use of a read-only data store with a non-transient
   NameID during SAML 2.0 federation (<link
   xlink:href="https://bugster.forgerock.org/jira/browse/OPENAM-1427"
   xlink:show="new">OPENAM-1427</link>).</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
   <para>The ssoadm command now includes a get-sub-cfg subcommand (<link
   xlink:href="https://bugster.forgerock.org/jira/browse/OPENAM-1348"
   xlink:show="new">OPENAM-1348</link>).</para>
  </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>The REST authenticate command now has a parameter to specify the
    client IP address (<link
    xlink:href="https://bugster.forgerock.org/jira/browse/OPENAM-1048"
    xlink:show="new">OPENAM-1048</link>).</para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
   <para>OpenAM is now built with Maven. Maven artifacts continue to be uploaded
   to the ForgeRock Maven repository (<link
   xlink:href="https://bugster.forgerock.org/jira/browse/OPENAM-739"
   xlink:show="new">OPENAM-739</link>).</para>
  </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>You can now prevent OpenAM from caching subject evaluations for
    policy decisions (part of the fix for <link xlink:show="new"
    xlink:href="https://bugster.forgerock.org/jira/browse/OPENAM-24"
    >OPENAM-24</link>).</para>
    <para>In most cases you do not need to turn off caching, as OpenAM now
    clears cache when group membership changes. Before turning off caching in
    production, first test the setting to ensure that the performance impact is
    acceptable for your deployment.</para>
    <para>To turn off caching, set Access Control &gt; <replaceable
    >Realm Name</replaceable> &gt; Services &gt; Policy Configuration &gt;
    Subjects Result Time to Live to 0. The equivalent
    <command>ssoadm</command> property for the
    <literal>iPlanetAMPolicyConfigService</literal> is
    <literal>iplanet-am-policy-config-subjects-result-ttl</literal>.</para>
   </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
</chapter>
