<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ! CCPL HEADER START
  !
  ! This work is licensed under the Creative Commons
  ! Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 3.0 Unported License.
  ! To view a copy of this license, visit
  ! http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/
  ! or send a letter to Creative Commons, 444 Castro Street,
  ! Suite 900, Mountain View, California, 94041, USA.
  !
  ! You can also obtain a copy of the license at
  ! src/main/resources/legal-notices/CC-BY-NC-ND.txt.
  ! See the License for the specific language governing permissions
  ! and limitations under the License.
  !
  ! If applicable, add the following below this CCPL HEADER, with the fields
  ! enclosed by brackets "[]" replaced with your own identifying information:
  !      Portions Copyright [yyyy] [name of copyright owner]
  !
  ! CCPL HEADER END
  !
  !      Copyright 2011-2012 ForgeRock AS
  !    
-->
<chapter xml:id='chap-issues'
 xmlns='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook' version='5.0' xml:lang='en'
 xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'
 xsi:schemaLocation='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd'
 xmlns:xlink='http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink'
 xmlns:xinclude='http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude'>
 <title>OpenAM Fixes, Limitations, &amp; Known Issues</title>

 <para>OpenAM issues are tracked at <link
 xlink:href='https://bugster.forgerock.org/jira/browse/OPENAM'
 >https://bugster.forgerock.org/jira/browse/OPENAM</link>. This chapter
 covers the status of key issues and limitations at release
 <?eval ${serverDocTargetVersion}?>.</para>

 <section xml:id="fixes">
  <title>Fixes</title>

  <para>The following issues were fixed in release
  <?eval ${serverDocTargetVersion}?>.</para>
  
  <itemizedlist>
  <!-- This list does not include some fixes for typos, doc issues, removed
  functionality, and issues raised on new features during testing. -->
<listitem><para>Identity web-services update call always removes group memberships (OPENAM-1043).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>isSessionQuotaReached in AMLoginModule does not work in single server mode (OPENAM-1042).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Wildcards in referrals can be ignored due to invalid search filter (OPENAM-1006).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>OpenAM should not be shipped with JDMK monitoring enabled by default (OPENAM-1004).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Deadlock during server startup (OPENAM-1003).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Special character used in membership search filter should be escaped (rfc2254) (OPENAM-987).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>RuntimeException in Sufficient module breaks the chain (OPENAM-975).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>OpenAM 10 does not get deployed in JBoss 7.02 (OPENAM-949).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Fedlet encounters error processing LogoutRequest as /saml2loginwithrelay.template is missing from the classpath (OPENAM-933).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>IdRepo log is spammed with agent attributes (OPENAM-923).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>SAML2Exception when fetching SP AuthnRequestInfo in multi server setup when IDP response is not sent to origin server (OPENAM-909).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>ServiceTypeManager can return invalid tokens (OPENAM-906).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Javascript and CSS bugs on userstore wizard screen (OPENAM-896).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Access to root realm after console deploy timeout occurs (OPENAM-895).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>REST logout does not perform actual logout on auth context (OPENAM-893).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Relative (goto) redirects don't work with proxied requests (OPENAM-891).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>SAML2 Authentication Authority entity bindings are verified as if they were in an SAML2 IDP entity, this causes an NPE (OPENAM-888).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>After restoring backup OpenAM fails to load configuration (OPENAM-885).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>PagePropertiesCallback ignores attribute and require lists (OPENAM-883).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>empty passwords cause backup to fail during upgrade (OPENAM-881).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>new_org.jsp doesn't work, when the second auth request contains extra parameters (OPENAM-878).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Configurator User Data Store selection not retrieving i18n values (OPENAM-871).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>OpenAM Console Session list throwing an exception (OPENAM-870).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Upgrade fails to connect to external configuration store (OPENAM-866).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>A second GUI Configurator Exists (OPENAM-863).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Exception handling in the REST interface (OPENAM-843).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>LDAP Auth Module doesn't remove terminated LDAP connection from pool and returns 401 error via REST interface (OPENAM-839).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Character encoding problem on the password reset page (OPENAM-832).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>L10NMessageImpl can lose initCause (OPENAM-828).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Creating a Identity Membership Condition in a sub-realm does not use the correct Datastore (OPENAM-827).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Multiprotocol federation sample application failure (OPENAM-825).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>LoginViewBean UI does not implement new_org.jsp functionality (OPENAM-824).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>SFO scripts don't work on Debian GNU/Linux, because of /bin/awk path (OPENAM-818).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>ShutdownManager gets stuck in waiting state causing the server to be unavailable (OPENAM-817).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Setup progress page is never closing the stream (OPENAM-814).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Session timeout branding is not working (OPENAM-813).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>LDAPFilterCondition will try to bind using LDAPv2 even with LDAPv3 only servers (OPENAM-812).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>AMIdentityMembershipCondition is missing information about who the user is which is required to make the decision (OPENAM-811).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>In case of session upgrade requesting the page again can cause Session Timeout errors (OPENAM-807).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Successful access to LoginViewBean still creates a new session (OPENAM-794).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>SAML2 Metadata for a remote service provider with Extensions breaks the console and Entity Providers no longer list under Federation (OPENAM-792).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>LDAPFilter conditions are not using the correct Policy config when used in a sub-realm policy definition (OPENAM-790).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Combination of referral policy, self evaluation and super resource match fails to follow referral (OPENAM-788).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>AMSetupServlet::getRemoteServerInfo fails if the first instance SSL certificate is invalid (OPENAM-784).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Config Wizard ignores server URL (OPENAM-778).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>When a SAML2 Request does not contain an Authentication Context, the Default Authentication Context mapper maps a level=0 (OPENAM-775).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Radius auth module typo (wrong server configuration check) (OPENAM-767).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Endless recursion in CachedRemoteServicesImpl (OPENAM-738).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>REST/SOAP API leaks information about users by returning an InvalidPassword exception when the users password is wrong. (OPENAM-735).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>AuthenticationFailureCount and AuthenticationFailureRate do not Update Correctly (OPENAM-734).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>JDBC authentication module fails to initialize in JNDI mode (OPENAM-733).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>LDAPConnectionPool has risk of dead lock (OPENAM-730).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Multi-threaded entitlement evaluation gives wrong result (OPENAM-726).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>amsfo start results in repeat /t Wait for the broker to start properly messages (OPENAM-723).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Shutting down DS when "sun-idrepo-ldapv3-config-idletimeout" is other than 0 (zero) can result in loop (OPENAM-716).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>REOPEN -LDAP Error 80 can result in build up of LDAPv3EventService::RetryTask objects (OPENAM-688).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>LDAPv3EventServicePolling can enter RetryTask loop if LDAP encounters a problem at the same time as the persistent searches are restarted (OPENAM-684).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>updateSiteNameToIDMappings will leave siteNameToIdTable null if sites are not configured (OPENAM-675).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>CachedSubEntries::getSubEntries returns the actual reference to the cache entry (OPENAM-673).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>AuthClientUtils::sendAuthRequestToOrigServer does not handle server errors (OPENAM-668).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Persistent Cookie should only be set on success and not on AMAuthCookie (OPENAM-667).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>OpenAM complains about invalid character when the FedCOTMemberName has '=' in it (OPENAM-664).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>jaxrpc xml parser can introduce corruption in the output when parsing (OPENAM-656).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>amsessiondb should run with tx no sync in bdb (OPENAM-652).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>amsessiondb error messages are going to System.err and are getting lost (OPENAM-644).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>amsessiondb does not shutdown properly if the DB/MQ is broken (OPENAM-643).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>amsessiondb does not recover from db errors and can break the MQ (OPENAM-642).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>DAUI shutdown is not releasing resources correctly (OPENAM-639).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Infinite loop in LoginViewBean during login using Membership login module (OPENAM-633).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>changing the debug level from message to error is ignored by the entitlements engine (OPENAM-622).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Error while trying to import service configuration into OpenDJ (OPENAM-616).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Session upgrade does not work if the second login is on a different server (OPENAM-615).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>LoginState looks up LDAP profile attributes for the session service when it doesn't need to. (OPENAM-612).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>javax.servlet.ServletException: missing jspFile on start up (OPENAM-608).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Certificate module has a problem with OCSP validation if JCE is used (OPENAM-586).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>REST authentication interface does not differentiate between inactive and locked accounts (OPENAM-584).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>maximum session limit during rest authentication results in 200 and null return (OPENAM-583).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Debug error log gets "unable to locate message ID object for FSAssertionManager" when using CDSSO (OPENAM-581).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>GOT_ALL_HOSTED_ENTITIES audit log is erroneusly logged (OPENAM-580).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>SecurID Authentication in New PIN mode and Change PIN mode fails in English locale (OPENAM-529).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>HOTP authentication module: If sms and/or email could not be sent no error is shown for the user (OPENAM-523).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>HOTP authentication module: Missing properties in resource bundle leads to internal authentication error (OPENAM-521).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>When a SAML2 Authentication Request is sent to an IdP with the IsPassive flag set to true and no valid session is present, the RelayState is dropped by the IdP (OPENAM-520).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>SecurID authentication exception: Logindisplay:Null (OPENAM-519).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>DAS configurator does not store OpenAM deployment URI (OPENAM-518).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>AuthUtils.isLocalServer method gets confused with the server URI when used on the DAS (OPENAM-509).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>lb cookie set on the DAS is used incorrectly in the PLLClient (OPENAM-508).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Not every admin tool ignores version check by default (OPENAM-506).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>NotificationSender does not analyse the response from the client correctly. (OPENAM-498).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Running in non c66encode mode can lead to dual URL decoding issue in the CDCClientServlet to CDCServlet communications (OPENAM-491).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Multiple windows during SAML2 sign-on can lead to NPE (OPENAM-489).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Multiple browser access can cause invalid redirects during SAML2 sign-on (OPENAM-488).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>In case of zero page session upgrade DAS does not set session cookie expiration (OPENAM-487).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>amMasterSessionTableStats can be negative in some cases (OPENAM-486).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>SAML validator.jsp breaks with NPE if it was unable to create ValidateSAML2 (OPENAM-485).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>create-server command returns success state when invalid properties were supplied (OPENAM-482).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>AuthClientUtils should forward requests with the same method in case of failover (OPENAM-478).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>SAML2 HTTPPOST Profil: Assertion not signed when response is signed (OPENAM-475).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Build can't handle spaces in directory names (OPENAM-473).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>DAS LogoutViewBean should not accept invalid gotoURL's (OPENAM-470).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>HttpURLConnectionManager should set a connect timeout for the provided connections (OPENAM-468).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Log file "amAuthentication.error" is not created (OPENAM-459).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>When changing the DNS alias in a realm, the Realm Alias Referrals are not updated until restart when using external configuration store (OPENAM-446).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Agent inheriting Location of Agent Configuration Repository from Agent Group causes error (OPENAM-440).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Missing files while creating console/noconsole wars (OPENAM-407).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>OpenAM's servlet API version does not officially support the included JSTL 1.1 (OPENAM-398).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>If the Session DB is offline, AMLoginModule::isSessionQuotaReached malfunctions (OPENAM-393).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>LoginViewBean NPE (OPENAM-370).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Custom Response Providers are ignored by the Entitlements Framework (OPENAM-333).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>It is not possible to assign a Post Authentication Class plugin to a service chain with the ssoadm (OPENAM-318).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>OpenAM LDAP schema should conform to the expected structural objectclass usage (OPENAM-312).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Distributed authentication UI not able to do resource based authentication (OPENAM-298).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Blank in form can break fedlet creation (OPENAM-269).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>SAML2.0 isPassive attribute in the AuthnRequest is ignored by the IdP (OPENAM-261).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Distributed Authentication UI Login URL not accepted (OPENAM-247).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Remote SessionRequest.setProperty causes HTTP 500 for null property/value (OPENAM-191).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>SetupDistAuthWAR does not support the ability to set the lb value (OPENAM-188).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>"Authentication by Module Chain" fails when used in a sub-realm (OPENAM-171).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>updating service to include new PluginSchems, ssoadm command is counterintuitive (OPENAM-109).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Default top-level realm privileges block SMS access to policy agents (OPENAM-90).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>SessionCount.getDeploymentMode uses site rather than server count to determine multi server mode (OPENAM-87).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>SAML2 service provider initiated SSO does not check that the realm of the authenticated user matches the realm of the COT (OPENAM-77).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>RuntimeException does not updates the failureModuleSet in LoginState (OPENAM-74).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>No way of configuring CDC and federated authentication without writing custom code (OPENAM-28).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Some classes of Policy Changes are not propagating to the agent (OPENAM-25).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>ssoadm versioncheck fails with encoded contents (OPENAM-20).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Deadlock when making Entitlements REST requests (OPENAM-16).</para></listitem>
<listitem><para>Wrong resource bundle in com.sun.identity.rest.RestException (OPENAM-15).</para></listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </section>

 <section xml:id="limitations">
  <title>Limitations</title>
  
  <para>ForgeRock supports the stable software releases that you can download
  from ForgeRock, not nightly builds or pre-release software. ForgeRock
  OpenAM downloads do not include OpenAM extensions. Therefore, ForgeRock does
  not support OpenAM extensions. If you have a special request for capabilities
  not currently in a software release, contact ForgeRock at <link
  xlink:href="mailto:info@forgerock.com">info@forgerock.com</link>.</para>
  
  <para>Do not run different versions of OpenAM together in the same OpenAM
  site.</para>

  <para>Not all features of OpenAM work with IPv6.</para>

  <para>The Database Repository type of data store is experimental and not
  supported for production use.</para>

  <!-- Fix for OPENAM-737: Add details to the release notes of OpenAM (for 735) -->
  <para>By default, the REST and SOAP APIs return different responses depending
  on whether the user name provided is valid or invalid. This behavior could
  allow an attacker to build list of valid user names, after which only
  passwords would be required to gain access to user account details. To
  prevent this risk, set the server configuration property
  <literal>openam.auth.soap.rest.generic.authentication.exception=true</literal>.
  You can set this property in OpenAM console under Configuration &gt; Servers
  and Sites &gt; Servers &gt; Server Name &gt; Advanced.</para>

  <!-- Fix for OPENAM-1032: Add details to the release notes and documentation of OpenAM (for 875) -->
  <para>By default OpenAM does not enforce session quotas when running in Site
  mode without session failover. To work around this behavior, set the server
  configuration property
  <literal>openam.session.useLocalSessionsInMultiServerMode=true</literal>.
  You can set this property in OpenAM console under Configuration &gt; Servers
  and Sites &gt; Servers &gt; Server Name &gt; Advanced.</para>
 </section>
 
 <section xml:id="known-issues">
  <title>Known Issues</title>

  <para>The following known issues remained open at the time
  release <?eval ${serverDocTargetVersion}?> became available.</para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>Web service library conflicts when deploying Oracle 11g Application
    Server (OPENAM-1073).</para>
    <para>OpenAM console and most features continue to function correctly,
    but the conflicts can pose problems for STS.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>When AM SDK cache is disabled, <literal>amadmin</literal> cannot
    login (OPENAM-1071).</para>
    <para>Avoid disabling AM SDK caching for this early access release.</para>
    <para>If you do lock yourself out, edit the entry with DN
    <literal>ou=server-default,ou=com-sun-identity-servers,ou=default,
    ou=GlobalConfig,ou=1.0,ou=iPlanetAMPlatformService,ou=services,
    %ROOT_SUFFIX%</literal> in an LDAP browser, manually changing the
    AM SDK cache configuration value. Then restart OpenAM, or the web
    application container.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>The <filename>fam-noconsole.list</filename> file for building
    a custom, no-console .war includes the wrong versions of OpenDJ LDAP SDK
    and Grizzly Framework .jar files (OPENAM-1070).</para>
    <para>To work around this issue, edit the file to include these versions
    instead:</para>
    <literallayout class="monospaced">./WEB-INF/lib/opendj-ldap-sdk-3.0.0-M1.jar
./WEB-INF/lib/grizzly-framework-2.1.7.jar</literallayout>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>Clicking the Version button in the console for OpenAM installed in
    JBoss 7.0.2 results in an uncaught exception page (OPENAM-1062).</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>The check whether session quota is reached does not work correctly
    for users with multiple sessions (OPENAM-1047).</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>Remaining issues with upgrade (OPENAM-1044).</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>Agent users have permissions beyond what is strictly necessary
    (OPENAM-1027).</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>The HTTP-Basic Auth Module returns an HTTP 200 OK on failure
    (OPENAM-1024).</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>On startup OpenAM writes <literal>JCEEncryption:: Unsupported
    version: -98</literal> in the Id Repo debug log (OPENAM-1001).</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>OpenAM console front page includes incorrect and outdated references
    (OPENAM-997).</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>OpenAM distributed authentication user interface allows users to
    send multiple requests, causing issues with modules that do not expect
    multiple requests (OPENAM-990).</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>OpenAM LDAP authentication module sometimes fails to fail over when
    an LDAP server stops (OPENAM-986).</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>When creating a hosted identity provider, OpenAM creates provider
    URLs based on host header name rather than the name you provide
    (OPENAM-830).</para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </section>
</chapter>
