<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ! CCPL HEADER START
  !
  ! This work is licensed under the Creative Commons
  ! Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 3.0 Unported License.
  ! To view a copy of this license, visit
  ! http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/
  ! or send a letter to Creative Commons, 444 Castro Street,
  ! Suite 900, Mountain View, California, 94041, USA.
  !
  ! You can also obtain a copy of the license at
  ! src/main/resources/legal-notices/CC-BY-NC-ND.txt.
  ! See the License for the specific language governing permissions
  ! and limitations under the License.
  !
  ! If applicable, add the following below this CCPL HEADER, with the fields
  ! enclosed by brackets "[]" replaced with your own identifying information:
  !      Portions Copyright [yyyy] [name of copyright owner]
  !
  ! CCPL HEADER END
  !
  !      Copyright 2011-2012 ForgeRock AS
  !    
-->
<chapter xml:id='chap-whats-new'
 xmlns='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook' version='5.0' xml:lang='en'
 xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'
 xsi:schemaLocation='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd'
 xmlns:xlink='http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink'
 xmlns:xinclude='http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude'>
 <title>What's New in OpenAM <?eval ${serverDocTargetVersion}?></title>

 <para>OpenAM <?eval ${serverDocTargetVersion}?> fixes a number of issues, and
 provides the following additional features.</para>

 <itemizedlist>
  <title>Major New Features</title>
  <listitem>
   <para>OpenIG, the ForgeRock <link xlink:href="http://openig.forgerock.org/"
   >Identity Gateway</link>, is a high-performance reverse proxy server with
   specialized session management and credential replay functionality. OpenIG
   integrates well with OpenAM, and there is no need to modify the target
   application or the container in which it runs.</para>
   <para>OpenIG also includes the Federation Gateway, which enables federation
   capabilities for applications that cannot be modified to use the Fedlet and
   SAML 2.0.</para>
  </listitem>
<!--   <listitem>
   <para>OpenAM now supports YubiKey authentication. The YubiKey simplifies
   the process of logging in with a One Time Password token as it does not
   require the user to re-type long pass codes from a display device into the
   login field of the computer. The YubiKey is inserted in the USB-port of any
   computer and the OTP is generated and automatically entered with a simple
   touch of a button on the YubiKey, and without the need of any client
   software or drivers.</para>
  </listitem> -->
  <listitem>
   <!-- OPENAM-??? -->
   <para>OpenAM now uses OpenDJ 2.4.5 as the embedded data store
   (OPENAM-960).</para>
   <para>OpenAM now also uses the OpenDJ LDAP SDK.<footnote><para>The Java EE
   deployment container in which OpenAM runs can potentially expose leaks in
   OpenDJ LDAP SDK (OPENDJ-388).</para></footnote></para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>OpenAM now provides JSON output through the identity services REST
   interface (OPENAM-940).</para>
  </listitem>
  <!-- TODO: reword this when the extension is integrated. -->
<!--   <listitem>
   <para>A new session failover mechanism introduces a replacement for
   the existing implementation that relies on Message Queue and Berkeley DB
   with a highly scalable, pure Java implementation.</para>
  </listitem> -->
  <listitem>
   <para>OpenAM now supports adaptive risk authentication (OPENAM-846). You
   configure the adaptive risk authentication module to assess risks, and then
   you add the module into an authentication chain. The module determines
   whether to require further authentication processing based on assessment of
   the risk involved during authentication. Adaptive risk authentication lets
   you require more from users when they login from an unfamiliar location,
   from a new device, after a long period during which the account remained
   idle, and so forth.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>OpenAM supports a new SAML 2.0 IdP Adapter plug-in for additional
   flexibility. The adapter lets the system handle situations that arise when
   the identity provider needs to perform additional processing before
   releasing the assertion, or when interaction with the user is needed before
   releasing it. The IdP Adapter class implementing the plugin can be
   configured through the console (OPENAM-700).</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>OpenAM now provides an OAuth 2.0 Client authentication module
   (OPENAM-679).</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>Multiple improvements in the OpenAM upgrade process streamline the
   move to the new version (OPENAM-626).</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>OpenAM now supports interoperability with LDAP servers that implement
   the (Behera) Internet-Draft, <link
   xlink:href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-behera-ldap-password-policy-09"
   >Password Policy for LDAP Directories</link> (OPENAM-613).</para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>

 <itemizedlist>
  <title>Additional New Features</title>
  <listitem>
   <para>Setup wizards make it easier to use OpenDJ as the identity
   repository.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>OpenAM now allows you to differentiate Login UI buttons using CSS
   (OPENAM-977).</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>OpenAM now allows authentication modules to be installed as a single
   .jar file (OPENAM-916).</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>OpenAM has improved console configuration for handling services such
   as Authentication Core Settings and Identity Repositories (OPENAM-887).</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>The <command>ssoadm</command> command now provides subcommands to
   manage entitlement application types: <command>create-appl-type</command>,
   <command>delete-appl-types</command>, <command>list-appl-types</command>
   (OPENAM-872).</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>OpenAM console now includes many more helpful hints and built-in
   documentation (OPENAM-805).</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>OpenAM now lets you fetch maximum session time, time remaining, and
   idle time when querying attributes over the REST interface
   (OPENAM-801).</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>OpenAM now supports a <literal>refresh</literal> parameter to reset
   session idle time to 0 when querying attributes over the REST interface
   (OPENAM-800).</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>OpenAM now supports time zone policy settings using the RFC 822
   format, +/-0000 (OPENAM-791).</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>OpenAM session service now lets you set the maximum session time,
   maximum idle time, and maximum caching time when assigning service to
   the user through the console (OPENAM-785).</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>OpenAM now returns a load balancer cookie, if configured, to an
   authentication request over the REST interface (OPENAM-766).</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>OpenAM ClusterStateService now works with HTTPS endpoints
   (OPENAM-759). When using HTTPS endpoints, set
   <literal>com.sun.identity.urlchecker.dorequest=false</literal>.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>OpenAM now bundles <filename>click-nodeps.jar</filename>
   (OPENAM-646).</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>OpenAM now provides additional statistics related to session failover
   (OPENAM-641).</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>The OpenAM <command>amsfo</command> script now starts the session
   database only after the message queue is up and running (OPENAM-624).</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>OpenAM .NET fedlets now support encrypted assertions
   (OPENAM-604).</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>The Administration Tools setup script now has better default
   settings (OPENAM-577).</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>The OpenAM console configuration wizard now suggests better values
   for cookie domains (OPENAM-576).</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>OpenAM .jar files now contain standard MANIFEST entries
   (OPENAM-570).</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>The <command>ssoadm</command> can now decode an encrypted password
   stored in the password file (OPENAM-569).</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>You can now configure the HOTP authentication module email from
   address using OpenAM console (OPENAM-513).</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>The OpenAM console page <filename>Debug.jsp</filename> (such as
   <literal>http://openam.example.com:8080/openam/Debug.jsp</literal>) now
   can set the log level for any debug instance (OPENAM-511). See the
   Debug instances drop-down list at the top of the page.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>OpenAM now provides a property,
   <literal>openam.authentication.ignore_goto_during_logout</literal>, to
   set whether to ignore logout <literal>goto</literal> URLs, and instead
   display the Logout page (OPENAM-494).</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>OpenAM now provides support for multiple failover servers in the 
   RADIUS authentication module (OPENAM-477).</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>OpenAM now provides a mechanism to control which session properties
   are copied during session upgrade (OPENAM-462).</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>OpenAM now provides session timeout notification (OPENAM-457).
   The improvement implements a hook for timeout into the session service on
   the server side. It listens for timeouts on all sessions.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>The OpenAM authentication service now can map HTTP headers
   when forwarding requests (OPENAM-453). This applies both to the distributed
   and centralized authentication services. See configuration properties
   <literal>openam.retained.http.headers</literal> and
   <literal>openam.forbidden.to.copy.headers</literal>.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>The OpenAM session service now lets you extend quota exhaustion
   actions with a plugin (OPENAM-433).</para>
   <para>To add a new plugin, update the
   <filename>amSession.properties</filename> files with the appropriate
   internationalization keys, and place your plugin class either in
   <filename>WEB-INF/classes</filename> or <filename>WEB-INF/lib</filename>
   where you deployed OpenAM. Next, add your implementation using the
   <command>ssoadm</command> command.</para>
   <screen>$ ssoadm
 set-attr-choicevals
 --servicename iPlanetAMSessionService
 --schematype Global
 --attributename iplanet-am-session-constraint-handler
 --adminid amadmin
 --password-file .pass
 --add
 --choicevalues mykey=demo.Clazz</screen>
   <para>Here, <replaceable>mykey</replaceable> is the internationalization
   key you added to <filename>amSession.properties</filename> files, and
   <replaceable>demo.Clazz</replaceable> is the fully qualified class name
   for your plugin class.</para>
   <para>You can remove the plugin using the <command>ssoadm
   remove-attr-choicevals</command> command, and list quota exhaustion
   actions using the <command>ssoadm get-attr-choicevals</command>
   command.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <!-- Fix for OPENAM-795: Document the new monitorable values -->
   <para>OpenAM now tracks monitoring information for LDAP connection pools
   (OPENAM-410). OpenAM monitoring exposes the minimum size of the pool, the
   maximum size of the pool, the high water mark of the pool, the current size
   of the pool, the number of connections retrieved, the number of connections
   created, and the number of connections destroyed.</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>OpenAM Windows Desktop SSO now provides a mechanism to fail attempted
   authentication when Kerberos-authenticated user has no profile in the OpenAM
   data store (OPENAM-403).</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>OpenAM now handles Active Directory password expiration responses
   properly (OPENAM-258).</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>OpenAM password reset now uses realm aliases to find realms for
   end users, eliminating the need to add a realm parameter to the URL
   (OPENAM-192).</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <para>OpenAM now allows time-based rotation, and also file name prefixes and
   suffixes for regular and debug logs. (OPENAM-41, OPENAM-42)</para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
   <!-- Fix for OpenAM-796: Document the login progressbar template functionality -->
   <para>For cross domain single sign on and SAML 2.0 authentication, users
   were presented with a blank login page during authentication, in fact a
   page containing forms with hidden fields used to process authentication.
   OpenAM now provides templates so you can show users something besides
   than blank pages, such as for example a page with an animated .gif progress
   bar (OPENAM-9).</para>
   <para>For cross domain single sign on, edit a copy of the file
   <filename>config/federation/default/cdclogin.jsp</filename> where you
   unpacked the OpenAM web application (for example
   <filename>/path/to/tomcat/webapps/openam/config/federation/default/cdclogin.jsp</filename>).
   You can change the presentation as appropriate for your deployment. Make
   sure you retain the form and JavaScript to ensure requests are processed
   properly. Then replace
   <filename>config/federation/default/cdclogin.jsp</filename> with your
   version.</para>
   <para>For SAML 2.0, modify the templates
   <link xlink:href="http://sources.forgerock.org/browse/openam/trunk/opensso/products/federation/library/resources/saml2login.template?r=HEAD"><filename>saml2login.template</filename></link>
   and
   <link xlink:href="http://sources.forgerock.org/browse/openam/trunk/opensso/products/federation/library/resources/saml2loginwithrelay.template?r=HEAD"><filename>saml2loginwithrelay.template</filename></link>
   to change the presentation, retaining the form and JavaScript. Then copy
   your templates under the <filename>WEB-INF/classes/</filename> directory
   where you unpacked the OpenAM web application (for example
   <filename>/path/to/tomcat/webapps/openam/WEB-INF/classes/</filename>).</para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>
</chapter>
