<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ! CCPL HEADER START
  !
  ! This work is licensed under the Creative Commons
  ! Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 3.0 Unported License.
  ! To view a copy of this license, visit
  ! http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/
  ! or send a letter to Creative Commons, 444 Castro Street,
  ! Suite 900, Mountain View, California, 94041, USA.
  !
  ! You can also obtain a copy of the license at
  ! src/main/resources/legal-notices/CC-BY-NC-ND.txt.
  ! See the License for the specific language governing permissions
  ! and limitations under the License.
  !
  ! If applicable, add the following below this CCPL HEADER, with the fields
  ! enclosed by brackets "[]" replaced with your own identifying information:
  !      Portions Copyright [yyyy] [name of copyright owner]
  !
  ! CCPL HEADER END
  !
  !      Copyright 2014 ForgeRock AS
  !
-->
<chapter xml:id='chap-saml-1'
         xmlns='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook' version='5.0' xml:lang='en'
         xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'
         xsi:schemaLocation='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook
                             http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd'
         xmlns:xlink='http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink'>
 <title>Managing SAML 1.x Single Sign-On</title>
 <indexterm>
  <primary>Federation</primary>
  <secondary>SAML 1.x</secondary>
 </indexterm>
 <indexterm>
  <primary>SAML 1.x</primary>
 </indexterm>

 <para>
  SAML 1.x describes an XML and SOAP based framework that allows
  online trusted partners to exchange security information.
  In particular, SAML 1.x defines mechanisms for
  browser based web single sign-on (SSO) across independent organizations
  that work together to permit SSO for access to resources.
 </para>

 <important>
  <para>
   Although not strictly compatible with SAML 1.x,
   SAML 2.0 extends SAML 1.x to several additional use cases
   and also clarifies how partners share metadata with each other.
   Unless you are integrating with an existing SAML 1.x deployment
   consider using SAML 2.0,
   or an alternative such as OAuth 2.0 or OpenID Connect 1.0, instead.
  </para>

  <para>
   See the following chapters for more information:
   <link xlink:href="admin-guide#chap-federation" xlink:show="new"
         xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"><citetitle
   >Managing SAML 2.0 Federation</citetitle></link>,
   <link xlink:href="admin-guide#chap-oauth2" xlink:show="new"
         xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"><citetitle
   >Managing OAuth 2.0 Authorization</citetitle></link>, and
   <link xlink:href="admin-guide#chap-openid-connect" xlink:show="new"
         xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"><citetitle
   >Managing OpenID Connect 1.0 Authorization</citetitle></link>.
  </para>
 </important>

 <section xml:id="saml-1-about">
  <title>About SAML 1.x</title>

  <para>
   SAML 1.x was defined in response to several technical problems.
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Web SSO solutions often use SSO session cookies.
     Browsers do not return cookies across domains.
     For instance, browsers do not return cookies
     set by servers in the example.com domain
     to servers in the example.net domain.
     SAML 1.x works around this limitation of HTTP cookies.
    </para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>
     Before SAML 1.x was defined, there were already proprietary SSO solutions,
     but the solutions did not interoperate well across domains.
    </para>

    <para>
     SAML 1.x specifies a standard, cross-domain, interoperable SSO mechanism
     that works together with proprietary SSO services in a particular domain.
    </para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>
     Before SAML 1.x was defined, there was not an easy way to communicate
     security attributes across organization boundaries.
    </para>

    <para>
     SAML 1.x simplifies the communication of security attributes
     between different organizations.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>
   In SAML 1.x, business partners can play two roles.
   The <firstterm>asserting party</firstterm>,
   also known as the SAML authority
   and whose domain is the Source site,
   authenticates users and asserts information about them.
   The <firstterm>relying party</firstterm>,
   whose domain is known as the Destination site,
   consumes assertions and uses information from the assertion
   to decide whether to allows access to resources.
  </para>

  <para>
   In the Web Browser SSO Profiles for SAML 1.x, the user generally starts
   by authenticating with the asserting party
   and then selecting a relying party link to browse.
   Alternatively, the "Destination-Site-First" scenario can start
   with the user browsing to the relying party's site
   and being redirected to the asserting party's site to authenticate.
  </para>

  <para>
   The SAML 1.x <firstterm>Inter-site Transfer Service</firstterm>
   is a service that redirects the authenticated user
   from the asserting party's site to the appropriate service
   on the relying party's site.
   The Inter-site Transfer Service also handles artifact and redirect generation.
   How this service transfers the user to the relying party's site depends on
   how the asserting party and the relying party exchange messages.
  </para>

  <para>
   The asserting party and relying party can exchange messages either
   by reference, where the asserting party sends
   an <firstterm>artifact</firstterm>
   (a base64 encoded reference to the assertion)
   as a query string parameter value,
   or by value, where the asserting party directs the user's browser
   to HTTP POST the assertion to the relying party.
  </para>

  <para>
   When the asserting party and relying party use artifacts,
   the Inter-site Transfer Service redirects
   the user's browser to the relying party's Artifact Receiver Service
   with the artifact as the value of a query string parameter.
   The relying party retrieves the artifact from the query string,
   and then sends a SAML Request
   to the Responder Service at the asserting party.
   The asserting party replies
   with a SAML Response containing one or more assertions.
  </para>

  <figure xml:id="figure-saml-1-browser-artifact-profile">
   <title>SAML 1.x Web SSO Browser Artifact Profile</title>

   <mediaobject>
    <alt>Sequence diagram of the web SSO browser artifact profile</alt>
    <imageobject>
     <imagedata fileref="images/saml-1-browser-artifact-profile.png" format="PNG" />
    </imageobject>
    <textobject>
     <para>
      Web SSO starts at the asserting party's site.
      Authorization on the relying party's site is not shown.
     </para>
    </textobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>
   See section 4.1.1 of the <link xlink:show="new"
   xlink:href="https://www.oasis-open.org/committees/download.php/6837/sstc-saml-tech-overview-1.1-cd.pdf"
   >SAML 1.1 technical overview</link> for more detail.
  </para>

  <para>
   When the assertion is sent using the Browser/POST Profile,
   the Inter-site Transfer Service responds to the user's browser
   with an auto-submitting form containing the SAML response.
   The browser then submits the SAML response as form data by HTTP POST
   to the relying party's Assertion Consumer Service.
   The relying party's Assertion Consumer Service then processes the assertion.
  </para>

  <figure xml:id="figure-saml-1-browser-post-profile">
   <title>SAML 1.x Web SSO Browser POST Profile</title>

   <mediaobject>
    <alt>Sequence diagram of the web SSO browser POST profile</alt>
    <imageobject>
     <imagedata fileref="images/saml-1-browser-post-profile.png" format="PNG" />
    </imageobject>
    <textobject>
     <para>
      Web SSO starts at the asserting party's site.
      Authorization on the relying party's site is not shown.
     </para>
    </textobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para>
   See section 4.2.1 of the <link xlink:show="new"
   xlink:href="https://www.oasis-open.org/committees/download.php/6837/sstc-saml-tech-overview-1.1-cd.pdf"
   >SAML 1.1 technical overview</link> for more detail.
  </para>

  <para>
   The Assertion Consumer Service at the relying party
   validates the digital signature on the SAML response,
   and redirects the browser to the target URL of the resource
   that the user is attempting to access.
   The server providing that resource uses
   the relying party's authorization decision capabilities to
   establish whether the user can access the resource.
   If so, the resource is returned to the user's browser.
   If the relying party is using OpenAM for example,
   then the relying party sets an OpenAM SSO token based on the SAML response,
   and this token is used to track the user's session for authorization.
  </para>

  <para>
   Organizations working together to achieve SAML 1.x web SSO
   are called <firstterm>trusted partners</firstterm> in this context.
   Trusted partners agree on which services they provide,
   which web SSO profiles they implement,
   and how information is exchanged in the assertions,
   including profile attribute values.
   Once the trusted partners have reached agreement on how they interact,
   you can collect information about your partners' configurations
   and configure OpenAM to match your organization's part of the agreement.
  </para>
 </section>

 <section xml:id="saml-1-gather-info">
  <title>Gathering Configuration Information</title>

  <para>
   Before you can configure OpenAM to allow web SSO with trusted partners,
   you must first gather information about the agreement itself,
   as well as information for your site and for your partners sites.
  </para>

  <para>
   This section lists the data that you must collect.
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     SAML protocol version to use (1.1 or 1.0; default: 1.1)
    </para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>
     Assertion version to use (1.1 or 1.0; default: 1.1)
    </para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>
     Which trusted partners play which roles (asserting party, relying party)
    </para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>
     Domain names of partner sites
     (such as <literal>example.com</literal>, <literal>example.net</literal>)
    </para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>
     Whether assertions are exchanged by SAML artifact or by HTTP POST
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
     <para>
      If assertions are exchanged by artifact, also gather this information:
     </para>

     <listitem>
      <para>
       SAML artifact parameter name (default: <literal>SAMLart</literal>)
      </para>
     </listitem>

     <listitem>
      <para>
       Artifact timeout
      </para>
     </listitem>

     <listitem>
      <para>
       URL to the relying party endpoint that receives the artifact
       (such as <literal>https://rp.example.com/openam/SAMLAwareServlet</literal>)
      </para>
     </listitem>

     <listitem>
      <para>
       Relying party hosts that consume artifacts
       (by IP addresses, DNS names, or certificate aliases)
      </para>
     </listitem>

     <listitem>
      <para>
       URL to the asserting party endpoint that responds to SAML requests
       (such as <literal>https://ap.example.net/openam/SAMLSOAPReceiver</literal>)
      </para>
     </listitem>

     <listitem>
      <para>
       Authentication credentials to connect to the asserting party endpoint,
       if any (such as the username and password for HTTP Basic authentication)
      </para>
     </listitem>

     <listitem>
      <para>
       Asserting party signing certificate alias
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <itemizedlist>
     <para>
      If assertions are exchanged by HTTP POST, also gather this information:
     </para>

     <listitem>
      <para>
       URL to the relying party endpoint
       that consumes the form data in the POST assertion
       (such as <literal>https://rp.example.com/openam/SAMLPOSTProfileServlet</literal>)
      </para>
     </listitem>

     <listitem>
      <para>
       Asserting party host:port issuing assertions
      </para>
     </listitem>

     <listitem>
      <para>
       Asserting party signing certificate alias
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>
     Whether the relying party sends SOAP query requests to the asserting party,
     for example to get authorization decisions
    </para>

    <itemizedlist>
     <para>
      If the relying party queries the asserting party,
      also gather this information:
     </para>

     <listitem>
      <para>
       Relying party hosts that consume artifacts
       (by IP addresses, DNS names, or certificate aliases)
      </para>
     </listitem>

     <listitem>
      <para>
       How to get SSO information,
       and to map partner actions to authorization decisions
      </para>
     </listitem>

     <listitem>
      <para>
       Asserting party host:port issuing assertions
      </para>
     </listitem>

     <listitem>
      <para>
       Asserting party signing certificate alias
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>
     Target specifier parameter name (default: <literal>TARGET</literal>)
    </para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>
     Assertion timeout
    </para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>
     Whether to digitally sign assertions, requests, responses
    </para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>
     Partners' public key certificates used for HTTPS
    </para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>
     Partners' public key certificates used for message signing
     (unless included on the <literal>KeyInfo</literal> element of signed messages)
    </para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>
     Partners' Site IDs
     (base64-encoded ID, such as <literal>XARFfsIAXeLX8BEWNIJg9Q8r0PE=</literal>)
    </para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>
     What NameID formats are used to exchange names
     (such as <literal>urn:oasis:names:tc:SAML:1.1:nameid-format:emailAddress</literal>)
    </para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>
     How attributes map from an assertion to an OpenAM profile
     (for example,
     <literal>urn:oasis:names:tc:SAML:1.1:nameid-format:emailAddress|EmailAddress=mail</literal>)
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>
   For more information about your own public key certificates,
   see <xref linkend="saml-1-security" />.
  </para>

  <para>
   For your own Site ID, see the following procedure.
  </para>

  <procedure xml:id="saml-1-own-site-id">
   <title>To Generate a Site Identifier For an OpenAM Site</title>

   <para>
    Trusted partners should ask you for a Site ID.
    OpenAM generates a SAML 1.x Site ID value at configuration time.
    This Site ID value corresponds to the server.
    To find this in OpenAM Console, see Federation
    > SAML 1.x Configuration > Local Site Properties > Site Identifiers,
    and then click your server URL.
   </para>

   <para>
    If you have multiple servers in an OpenAM Site set up behind a load balancer,
    you can generate a Site ID, and then use it for all the servers in your site.
   </para>

   <step>
    <para>
     Generate a Site ID for your site, using the primary site URL.
    </para>

    <para>
     This example is for an asserting party
     where the site load balancer host is <literal>ap.example.net</literal>.
     The command is bundled with OpenAM server,
     shown with lines folded to fit on the printed page.
    </para>

    <screen>
$ <userinput>cd /path/to/tomcat/webapps/openam/WEB-INF/lib/</userinput>
$ <userinput>java \
 -cp ${forgerockUtilLibrary}:${sharedLibrary}:\
    ${federationLibrary} com.sun.identity.saml.common.SAMLSiteID \
    https://ap.example.net/openam</userinput>
<computeroutput>9BAg4UmVS6IbjccsSj9gAFYGO9Y=</computeroutput>
    </screen>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </section>

 <section xml:id="saml-1-security">
  <title>Preparing To Secure SAML 1.x Communications</title>

  <para>
   SAML communications are secured using Public Key Infrastructure (PKI).
   Communications should be protected over the network by HTTPS,
   and relying parties requesting assertions should use
   SSL or TLS mutual authentication to identify each other,
   meaning they should be able to trust each others' certificates.
   Furthermore, when an asserting party works through the user's browser
   to post an assertion to the relying party,
   then the asserting party must digitally sign the SAML response.
  </para>

  <para>
   A certificate can be trusted when the signer's certificate is trusted,
   or when the certificate itself is trusted.
   Trusted partners must either use public key certificates
   signed by a well-known Certificate Authority (CA),
   or share their self-signed or private CA signing certificates.
  </para>

  <procedure xml:id="saml-1-configure-keys">
   <title>To Configure Keys For Protecting SAML 1.x Communications</title>

   <step>
    <para>
     See the chapter
     <link xlink:href="admin-guide#chap-certs-keystores" xlink:show="new"
           xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"><citetitle
     >Managing Certificates</citetitle></link>
     for instructions on handling your own key pairs.
    </para>

    <para>
     For specific instructions on changing signing keys, see the procedure
     <link xlink:href="admin-guide#change-signing-key" xlink:show="new"
           xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"><citetitle
     >To Change the Signing Key for Federation</citetitle></link>.
    </para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>
     If necessary, share signing certificates with trusted partners.
    </para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>
     Import public key certificates shared by trusted partners
     into your OpenAM key store.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </section>

 <section xml:id="saml-1-configure-local-site">
  <title>Configuring SAML 1.x For Your Site</title>

  <para>
   After you have gathered configuration information
   and prepared to secure SAML 1.x communications
   you can configure SAML 1.x for your site.
  </para>

  <tip>
   <para>
    When you enter SAML 1.x configuration data,
    OpenAM Console escapes these special characters by default:
    <literal>&amp; &lt; &gt; " ' /</literal>.
    If instead you have already escaped these characters
    in the data that you plan to enter in OpenAM Console,
    then set the advanced configuration property
    <literal>com.sun.identity.saml.escapeattributevalue</literal>
    to <literal>false</literal>
    under Configuration > Servers and Sites > Default Server Settings > Advanced,
    and then restart OpenAM or the container in which it runs
    to prevent OpenAM Console from escaping the characters for you.
   </para>
  </tip>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para><xref linkend="saml-1-configure-local-ap" /></para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para><xref linkend="saml-1-configure-local-rp" /></para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <procedure xml:id="saml-1-configure-local-ap">
   <title>To Configure Asserting Party Local Site Properties</title>

   <para>
    Using the configuration information you have gathered
    complete the following steps.
   </para>

   <step>
    <para>
     Login to OpenAM Console as administrator, amadmin,
     browse to Federation > SAML 1.x Configuration,
     and then click Local Site Properties.
    </para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>
     If the target specifier query string parameter
     is something other than the standard default TARGET,
     set it in the Target Specifier field.
    </para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>
     If instead of the default server Site Identifier,
     you use a Site Identifier for the OpenAM Site,
     click New in the Site Identifiers table,
     and then add the information for the OpenAM Site,
     including the Site ID that you generated.
    </para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>
     Target URLs let you configure URLs for which HTTP POST is always used.
    </para>

    <para>
     When the TARGET specified matches a URL in the Target URLs list,
     then the asserting party sends the response to the relying party
     by HTTP POST of an auto-submitting form returned to the browser.
    </para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>
     If necessary, set the Default Protocol Version.
    </para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>
     In the Assertion section, change the values if necessary.
    </para>

    <para>
     Remove Assertion: Yes means that assertions are deleted from memory
     after they are used, rather than deleted only when they expire.
    </para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>
     In the Artifact section, change the values if necessary.
    </para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>
     In the Signing section,
     for an asserting party using the HTTP POST profile,
     check at least Sign SAML Assertion.
    </para>

    <para>
     By default OpenAM signs messages using the certificate with alias test.
    </para>

    <para>
     Check other options as required by your trusted partners.
    </para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>
     In the Attribute Query section, if relying parties issue attribute queries,
     then set the default list of profile attributes to return.
    </para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>
     In the NameID Format section,
     map SAML NameID formats to local OpenAM user profile attributes.
    </para>

    <para>
     This allows OpenAM to map a remote user to a local user profile.
    </para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>
     In the Attribute Map section, if the parties exchange attributes,
     then map the SAML attributes requested by relying parties
     to local OpenAM user profile attributes.
    </para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>
     Save your work.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <procedure xml:id="saml-1-configure-local-rp">
   <title>To Configure Relying Party Local Site Properties</title>

   <para>
    Using the configuration information you have gathered
    complete the following steps.
   </para>

   <step>
    <para>
     Login to OpenAM Console as administrator, amadmin,
     browse to Federation > SAML 1.x Configuration,
     and then click Local Site Properties.
    </para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>
     If the target specifier query string parameter
     is something other than the standard default TARGET,
     set it in the Target Specifier field.
    </para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>
     If instead of the default server Site Identifier,
     you use a Site Identifier for the OpenAM Site,
     click New in the Site Identifiers table,
     and then add the information for the OpenAM Site,
     including the Site ID that you generated.
    </para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>
     Ignore the Target URLs table for a relying party.
    </para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>
     If necessary, set the Default Protocol Version.
    </para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>
     In the Assertion section, change the values if necessary.
    </para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>
     In the Artifact section, change the values if necessary.
    </para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>
     Ignore the Signing section for relying parties,
     unless trusted partners require that your site signs SAML requests.
    </para>

    <para>
     By default OpenAM signs messages using the certificate
     with alias <literal>test</literal>.
    </para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>
     Ignore the Attribute Query section for relying parties.
    </para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>
     In the NameID Format section,
     map SAML NameID formats to local OpenAM user profile attributes.
    </para>

    <para>
     This allows OpenAM to map a remote user to a local user profile
     when not all the partners are using OpenAM user IDs.
    </para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>
     In the Attribute Map section, if the parties exchange attributes,
     then map the SAML attributes requested by relying parties
     to local OpenAM user profile attributes.
    </para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>
     Save your work.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </section>

 <section xml:id="saml-1-configure-trusted-partners">
  <title>Configuring SAML 1.x Trusted Partners</title>

  <para>
   After you have gathered configuration information
   and if necessary imported public key certificates from trusted partners
   you can configure SAML 1.x information for the partners.
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para><xref linkend="saml-1-configure-trusted-rp" /></para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para><xref linkend="saml-1-configure-trusted-ap" /></para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <procedure xml:id="saml-1-configure-trusted-rp">
   <title>To Configure a Trusted Relying Party</title>

   <para>
    OpenAM Console refers to the relying party as the Destination,
    because the relying party's site is the destination site.
   </para>

   <step>
    <para>
     Login to OpenAM Console as administrator, amadmin,
     browse to Federation > SAML 1.x Configuration,
     and then click New in the Trusted Partners table.
    </para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>
     Under Destination, select the SAML profiles used with the relying party.
    </para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>
     In the Common Settings section,
     set at least a name for the partner configuration,
     enter the partner's Site ID as the Source ID,
     and specify the fully qualified domain, optionally with the port number,
     of the relying party in the Target field.
     The value in the target field is matched to TARGET parameter values,
     so it should correspond to the real domain (and optionally port number)
     in the URLs of resources to access at the relying party's site.
    </para>

    <para>
     Optionally set a custom site attribute mapper,
     a custom name identifier mapper,
     and the SAML Version to use with the partner.
    </para>

    <para>
     You must also set one or more values in the host list for the partner
     to identify all hosts from the partner site that can send requests.
     OpenAM rejects SAML requests from hosts not specified in this list.
    </para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>
     In the Destination section,
     if the SAML Artifact profile is used with the relying party,
     set the SAML URL to the relying party's endpoint
     that receives the artifact and contacts your asserting party.
    </para>

    <para>
     If the SAML POST profile is used with the relying party,
     set the Post URL to the relying party's endpoint
     that consumes the assertion in the HTTP POST form data
     and redirects the user's browser to the target
     at the relying party's site.
    </para>

    <para>
     If the relying party makes SAML SOAP query requests,
     optionally set custom attribute or action mappers.
    </para>

    <para>
     If the relying party signs requests,
     then either requests include the certificate for the signing key
     in the KeyInfo element,
     or OpenAM must find the signing certificate elsewhere.
     If the relying party provides the signing certificate separately,
     import the signing certificate
     into OpenAM's <filename>keystore.jks</filename> file,
     and set the alias for the signing certificate here in the configuration.
    </para>

    <para>
     Set the issuer to a host:port combination
     corresponding to the relying party server issuing the requests.
    </para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>
     Save your work.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <procedure xml:id="saml-1-configure-trusted-ap">
   <title>To Configure a Trusted Asserting Party</title>

   <para>
    OpenAM Console refers to the asserting party as the Source,
    because the asserting party's site is the source site.
   </para>

   <step>
    <para>
     Login to OpenAM Console as administrator, amadmin,
     browse to Federation > SAML 1.x Configuration,
     and then click New in the Trusted Partners table.
    </para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>
     Under Source, select the SAML profiles used with the asserting party.
    </para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>
     In the Common Settings section,
     set at least a name for the partner configuration
     and enter the partner's Site ID as the Source ID.
    </para>

    <para>
     Optionally set a custom account mapper.
     By default OpenAM maps accounts
     based on the NameID format configuration for your site.
    </para>

    <para>
     If the asserting party signs assertions (or other messages)
     and you have imported the signing certificate
     into OpenAM's key store (also used as a trust store),
     then enter the signing certificate alias.
     If instead the asserting party includes the signing certificate
     in the KeyInfo element of signed messages,
     then you can leave the alias blank.
    </para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>
     In the Source section,
     if the SAML Artifact profile is used with the asserting party,
     set the SOAP URL to the asserting party endpoint that responds to requests
     such as <literal>https://ap.example.net/openam/SAMLSOAPReceiver</literal>.
    </para>

    <para>
     If the asserting party requires authentication to the SOAP URL,
     then configure the settings appropriately.
    </para>

    <para>
     If the SOAP URL is accessed over HTTP, choose None or Basic.
     If the SOAP URL is accessed over HTTPS, choose SSL/TLS or SSL/TLS with Basic.
    </para>

    <para>
     Basic means HTTP Basic authentication (with username and password).
     For HTTP Basic authentication,
     the authentication at this level is performed
     by the application server container, not OpenAM.
     Therefore if the asserting party runs OpenAM
     and wants to enforce HTTP Basic authentication,
     the asserting party administrator must set up the container
     to handle HTTP Basic authentication for the SOAP URL.
    </para>

    <para>
     Set the SAML Version as necessary.
    </para>

    <para>
     If the SAML POST profile is used with the asserting party,
     set the Issuer to the issuer name, such as a host:port combination.
    </para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>
     Save your work.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </section>

 <section xml:id="saml-1-test-web-sso">
  <title>Testing SAML 1.x Web SSO</title>

  <para>
   You can try SAML 1.x Web SSO using OpenAM
   by following the procedures in this section.
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para><xref linkend="saml-1-test-prepare-servers" /></para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para><xref linkend="saml-1-test-ap" /></para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para><xref linkend="saml-1-test-rp" /></para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para><xref linkend="saml-1-try-it-out" /></para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <procedure xml:id="saml-1-test-prepare-servers">
   <title>To Prepare the OpenAM Servers</title>

   <step>
    <para>
     Install two separate OpenAM servers,
     one to act as asserting party,
     the other to act as relying party.
    </para>

    <para>
     How you do this in practice is up to you.
    </para>

    <para>
     You can for example set up two separate OpenAM servers on a single host
     by adding aliases for the hosts in your hosts file,
     and by using separate containers that listen on different ports.
    </para>

    <para>
     For example if your host is a laptop,
     you can add the aliases to the loopback address
     as in the following example line
     from an <filename>/etc/hosts</filename> file.
    </para>

    <literallayout class="monospaced"
    >127.0.0.1    localhost ap.example.net rp.example.com</literallayout>

    <para>
     Then run one application server to listen on port 8080,
     and another to listen on port 9080.
    </para>

    <para>
     Deploy and configure OpenAM server with the default configuration
     at <literal>http://ap.example.net:8080/ap</literal> for the asserting party
     and at <literal>http://rp.example.com:9080/rp</literal> for the relying party.
     This allows you to use the default configuration for both servers.
    </para>

    <para>
     See the
     <link xlink:href="install-guide#install-guide" xlink:show="new"
           xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"><citetitle
     >Installation Guide</citetitle></link> for instructions.
    </para>

    <para>
     The procedures in this section use those example URLs
     to represent the OpenAM servers acting as asserting and relying parties.
    </para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>
     On the asserting party server,
     login to OpenAM Console as administrator,
     browse to Federation > SAML 1.x Configuration,
     and then click Local Site Properties.
    </para>

    <para>
     Click the server's instance ID in the Site Identifiers table.
    </para>

    <para>
     Record the asserting party Site ID for later use.
    </para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>
     On the relying party server,
     login to OpenAM Console as administrator,
     browse to Federation > SAML 1.x Configuration,
     and then click Local Site Properties.
    </para>

    <para>
     Click the server's instance ID in the Site Identifiers table.
    </para>

    <para>
     Record the asserting party Site ID for later use.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <procedure xml:id="saml-1-test-ap">
   <title>To Prepare to Test the Asserting Party</title>

   <para>
    Follow these steps to configure the asserting party OpenAM server.
   </para>

   <step>
    <para>
     Login to OpenAM Console as administrator,
     browse to Federation > SAML 1.x Configuration,
     and then click Local Site Properties.
    </para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>
     On the Local Site Properties page
     for the asserting party server,
     select Sign SAML Response.
    </para>

    <para>
     The asserting party thus signs SAML responses
     with the private key for the default test certificate.
    </para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>
     Save your work,
     and then click Back to Federation.
    </para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>
     Click New in the Trusted Partners table
     to add the relying party as a trusted partner.
    </para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>
     In the Destination area of the Select trusted partner type and profile page,
     select Artifact and Post (not SOAP Query), and then click Next.
    </para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>
     Apply the following settings, adjusted for the host names you use.
    </para>

    <para>
     If a field is not mentioned, accept the defaults.
    </para>

    <para>
     Under Common Settings, use these settings:
    </para>

    <simplelist>
     <member>Name: rp.example.com:9080</member>
     <member>Source ID: relying party Site ID that you recorded</member>
     <member>Target: rp.example.com:9080</member>
    </simplelist>

    <para>
     Under Destination > Artifact, use these settings:
    </para>

    <simplelist>
     <member>SOAP URL: http://rp.example.com:9080/rp/SAMLAwareServlet</member>
     <member>Host List: rp.example.com</member>
    </simplelist>

    <para>
     Under Source > Post,
     set Post URL: http://rp.example.com:9080/rp/SAMLPOSTProfileServlet
    </para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>
     Click Finish to save your work.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <procedure xml:id="saml-1-test-rp">
   <title>To Prepare to Test the Relying Party</title>

   <para>
    Follow these steps to configure the relying party OpenAM server.
   </para>

   <step>
    <para>
     Login to OpenAM Console as administrator,
     browse to Federation > SAML 1.x Configuration,
     and then click New in the Trusted Partners table
     to add the asserting party as a trusted partner.
    </para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>
     In the Source area of the Select trusted partner type and profile page,
     select Artifact and Post, and then click Next.
    </para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>
     Apply the following settings, adjusted for the host names you use.
    </para>

    <para>
     If a field is not mentioned, accept the defaults.
    </para>

    <para>
     Under Common Settings, use these settings:
    </para>

    <simplelist>
     <member>Name: ap.example.net:8080</member>
     <member>Source ID: asserting party Site ID that you recorded</member>
     <member>Signing Certificate Alias: test</member>
    </simplelist>

    <para>
     Under Source > Artifact,
     set SOAP URL: http://ap.example.net:8080/ap/SAMLSOAPReceiver
    </para>

    <para>
     Under Source > Post, set Issuer: ap.example.net:8080
    </para>

    <para>
     Click Finish to save your work.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <procedure xml:id="saml-1-try-it-out">
   <title>To Try SAML 1.x Web SSO</title>

   <para>
    Once you have successfully configured both parties, try SAML 1.x Web SSO.
   </para>

   <step>
    <para>
     Log out of OpenAM Console on both servers.
    </para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>
     Try Web SSO using the SAML Artifact profile.
    </para>

    <substeps>
     <step>
      <para>
       Simulate the OpenAM administrator browsing the asserting party's site,
       and selecting a link to the OpenAM Console on the relying party's site.
      </para>

      <para>
       The URL to simulate this action is something like
       <literal>http://ap.example.net:8080/ap/SAMLAwareServlet?TARGET=http://rp.example.com:9080/rp</literal>.
      </para>

      <para>
       OpenAM requires that you authenticate.
      </para>
     </step>

     <step>
      <para>
       Login as OpenAM demo user,
       <literal>demo</literal> with default password <literal>changeit</literal>,
       on the asserting party server.
      </para>
     </step>

     <step>
      <para>
       Notice that you are redirected to OpenAM Console on the relying party server,
       and that you are successfully logged in as the demo user.
      </para>
     </step>

     <step>
      <para>
       Log out of OpenAM Console on both servers.
      </para>
     </step>
    </substeps>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>
     Try Web SSO using the SAML HTTP POST profile.
    </para>

    <substeps>
     <step>
      <para>
       Simulate the OpenAM administrator browsing the asserting party's site,
       and selecting a link to the OpenAM Console on the relying party's site.
      </para>

      <para>
       The URL to simulate this action is something like
       <literal>http://ap.example.net:8080/ap/SAMLPOSTProfileServlet?TARGET=http://rp.example.com:9080/rp</literal>.
      </para>

      <para>
       OpenAM requires that you authenticate.
      </para>
     </step>

     <step>
      <para>
       Login as OpenAM administrator, <literal>amadmin</literal>,
       on the asserting party server.
      </para>
     </step>

     <step>
      <para>
       Notice that you are redirected to OpenAM Console on the relying party server,
       and that you are successfully logged in as <literal>amadmin</literal>.
      </para>
     </step>
    </substeps>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </section>
</chapter>
