<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ! CCPL HEADER START
  !
  ! This work is licensed under the Creative Commons
  ! Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 3.0 Unported License.
  ! To view a copy of this license, visit
  ! http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/
  ! or send a letter to Creative Commons, 444 Castro Street,
  ! Suite 900, Mountain View, California, 94041, USA.
  !
  ! You can also obtain a copy of the license at
  ! src/main/resources/legal-notices/CC-BY-NC-ND.txt.
  ! See the License for the specific language governing permissions
  ! and limitations under the License.
  !
  ! If applicable, add the following below this CCPL HEADER, with the fields
  ! enclosed by brackets "[]" replaced with your own identifying information:
  !      Portions Copyright [yyyy] [name of copyright owner]
  !
  ! CCPL HEADER END
  !
  !      Copyright 2014 ForgeRock AS
  !
-->
<chapter xml:id='chap-install-multiple'
         xmlns='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook'
         version='5.0' xml:lang='en'
         xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'
         xsi:schemaLocation='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook
                     http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd'
         xmlns:xlink='http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink'>
 <title>Installing Multiple Servers</title>

 <indexterm>
  <primary>Installing</primary>
  <secondary>multiple servers</secondary>
 </indexterm>

 <indexterm>
  <primary>Installing</primary>
  <secondary>load balancer</secondary>
 </indexterm>

 <indexterm>
  <primary>Installing</primary>
  <secondary>proxy settings</secondary>
 </indexterm>

 <para>
  This chapter covers what to do when installing multiple OpenAM servers.
 </para>

 <section xml:id="considerations-multiple-servers">
  <title>Things to Consider When Installing Multiple Servers</title>

  <para>
   When installing multiple servers, consider the following points.
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>
     You generally install multiple servers to provide service availability.
     If one server is down for any reason, another server can respond instead.
     This means that you need something between incoming traffic and OpenAM
     to route around servers that are down.
    </para>

    <para>
     OpenAM has the concept of OpenAM <firstterm>site</firstterm> for this purpose.
     In an OpenAM site, multiple OpenAM servers are configured in the same way,
     and accessed through a load balancer layer.<footnote>
      <para>
       Technically it is possible to configure a site with only one OpenAM server.
      </para>
     </footnote>
     The load balancer can be implemented in hardware or software,
     but it is separate and independent from OpenAM software.
     When installed properly, a site configuration improves service availability,
     as the load balancer routes around OpenAM servers that are down,
     sending traffic to other servers in the site.
    </para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>
     You can use a load balancer layer to protect OpenAM services as well.
     The load balancer can restrict access to OpenAM services,
     throttle traffic, offload HTTPS encryption, and so forth.
    </para>

    <para>
     As an alternative, or in addition,
     you can use a separate reverse proxy service,
     or the OpenAM distributed authentication UI.
     The distributed authentication UI exposes a subset of OpenAM functionality.
     For instructions on setting up the distributed authentication UI, see
     <link
      xlink:show="new"
      xlink:href="install-guide#chap-install-das"
      xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"
     ><citetitle>Installing OpenAM Distributed Authentication</citetitle></link>.
    </para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>
     When you are protecting OpenAM with a load balancer or proxy service,
     configure your container so that OpenAM can trust
     the load balancer or proxy service.
     OpenAM trusts the distributed authentication UI
     as the distributed authentication UI uses
     credentials registered with OpenAM.
    </para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
     <para>
      OpenAM authentication can depend on information
      about the user to authenticate,
      such as the IP address where the request originated.
      When OpenAM is accessed through a load balancer or proxy layer,
      pass this information along using request headers.
      Also configure OpenAM to consume and to forward the headers as necessary.
      See <xref linkend="handle-request-headers" /> for details.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </section>

 <section xml:id="configure-sites">
  <title>Configuring OpenAM Sites</title>

  <indexterm>
   <primary>sites</primary>
   <secondary>configuring</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
   The most expedient way to configure a server in a site
   is to set the site up during the initial OpenAM configuration.
   In the GUI configurator, this is done in the Site Configuration screen.
   It is also possible to configure a site separately.
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <para>
    This section includes the following procedures.
   </para>

   <listitem>
    <para>
     <xref linkend="configure-site-after-installation" />
    </para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>
     <xref linkend="configure-site-load-balancing" />
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <procedure xml:id="configure-site-after-installation">
   <title>To Configure a Site with a First OpenAM Server</title>

   <para>
    You might already have configured an OpenAM server before realizing
    that a site is what you want.
   </para>

   <para>
    The following steps show how to set up the site for the first OpenAM server.
   </para>

   <step>
    <para>
     Login to OpenAM Console as administrator,
     by default <literal>amadmin</literal>,
     and then browse to Configuration > Servers and Sites > Sites.
    </para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>
     Click New to start configuring the new site.
    </para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>
     On the New Site page enter the site name,
     and set the Primary URL to the load balancer URL
     that is the entry point for the site,
     such as <literal>https://lb.example.com/openam</literal>.
    </para>

    <para>
     The site URL is the URL to the load balancer in front of
     the OpenAM servers in the site.
     For example, if your load balancer listens for
     HTTPS on host <literal>lb.example.com</literal>
     and port <literal>443</literal>,
     with OpenAM under <literal>/openam</literal>,
     then your site URL is <literal>https://lb.example.com/openam</literal>.
    </para>

    <para>
     Client applications and policy agents access the servers in the site
     through the site URL.
    </para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>
     Click Save to keep the site configuration.
    </para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>
     Under Configuration > Servers and Sites > Server,
     click the link to the server configuration.
    </para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>
     On the server configuration General tab page,
     set the Parent Site to the name of the site you just created,
     and then click Save to keep your changes.
    </para>

    <para>
     At this point the server is part of the new site you have configured.
    </para>

    <para>
     For all additional servers in the OpenAM site,
     add them to the site at configuration time as described in
     <link
      xlink:show="new"
      xlink:href="install-guide#add-servers-to-site"
      xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"
     ><citetitle>To Add a Server to a Site</citetitle></link>.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <procedure xml:id="configure-site-load-balancing">
   <title>To Configure Site Load Balancing</title>

   <para>
    If you did not set up the site during initial configuration,
    first follow the instructions in
    <xref linkend="configure-site-after-installation" />,
    and then follow all the steps below.
   </para>

   <step>
    <para>
     For each OpenAM server in the site, select
     Configuration > Servers and Sites > Servers > <replaceable>Server Name</replaceable>,
     set Parent Site to the site you created,
     and then Save your work.
    </para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>
     Make the <literal>amlbcookie</literal> value unique for each OpenAM server.
    </para>

    <para>
     In an OpenAM site, the server that authenticated a user
     is the server that continues to manage that user's session,
     unless the server is no longer available.
     The load balancer should send subsequent requests to that server
     to avoid overhead resulting from the server that gets the
     request being different from the server that authenticated the user.
    </para>

    <para>
     When traffic is protected with HTTPS, this approach requires
     that you terminate the connection on the load balancer.
     You then either re-encrypt the traffic from the load balancer to OpenAM,
     or make connections from the load balancer to OpenAM over HTTP.
    </para>

    <substeps>
     <step>
      <para>
       For each OpenAM server console in the site, browse to
       Configuration > Servers and Sites > Servers
       > <replaceable>Server Name</replaceable> > Advanced,
       and set <literal>com.iplanet.am.lbcookie.value</literal>
       to a unique value.
      </para>

      <para>
       By default, the cookie value is set to the OpenAM server ID.
      </para>

      <para>
       Changes take effect only after you restart the OpenAM server.
      </para>
     </step>

     <step>
      <para>
       Restart each OpenAM server where you changed the cookie value.
      </para>

      <para>
       You can then check the cookie value by logging in to OpenAM console,
       and examining the <literal>amlbcookie</literal> cookie in your browser.
      </para>
     </step>
    </substeps>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>
     Configure your load balancer to perform sticky load balancing
     based on the <literal>amlbcookie</literal> value.
    </para>

    <para>
     In other words, the load balancer layer must keep track of
     which <literal>amlbcookie</literal> cookie value
     corresponds to which OpenAM server.
    </para>

    <para>
     When the load balancer receives a request,
     it inspects the value of the <literal>amlbcookie</literal> cookie,
     and then forwards the request to the corresponding OpenAM server.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
  <note>
   <para>Sticky load balancing based on the value of the
    <literal>amlbcookie</literal> cookie does not guarantee request forwarding
    to the corresponding OpenAM server in all cases. For example,
    ForgeRock Common REST API calls do not typically use cookies. Therefore,
    load balancers are not able to route these calls to the OpenAM server
    on which a user's session resides.
   </para>
   <para>
    When an OpenAM request to read a session arrives at a server that does not
    hold the user's session, the OpenAM server attempts to locate the session
    from the Core Token Service session store by default.
   </para>
   <para>
    OpenAM servers can also use crosstalk to locate
    remote sessions. With crosstalk, OpenAM servers
    communicate with each other through a back channel to locate remote sessions.
    Because crosstalk generates network traffic, locating sessions from the
    Core Token Service session store is preferred for performance reasons.
   </para>
   <para>
    Requests to log out or set a session attribute always use crosstalk to
    ensure the integrity of the update requests.
   </para>
   <para>
   See
   <link
    xlink:show="new"
    xlink:href="install-guide#chap-session-failover"
    xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"
    ><citetitle>Setting Up OpenAM Session Failover</citetitle></link>
   for information about configuring remote session location options.
  </para>
  </note>
 </section>

 <section xml:id="handle-request-headers">
  <title>Handling HTTP Request Headers</title>

  <indexterm>
   <primary>HTTP request headers</primary>
   <secondary>handling</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
   HTTP requests can include information needed for access management,
   such as the client IP address used for adaptive risk-based authentication.
  </para>

  <para>
   Configure your load balancer or proxy to
   pass the information to OpenAM by using request headers.
   For example, the load balancer or proxy can send the client IP address
   by using the <literal>X-Forwarded-For</literal> HTTP request header.
  </para>

  <para>
   If you use the distributed authentication UI, you can retain headers
   by using the <literal>openam.retained.http.request.headers</literal> setting
   as described in
   <link
    xlink:show="new"
    xlink:href="install-guide#chap-install-das"
    xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"
   ><citetitle>Installing OpenAM Distributed Authentication</citetitle></link>.
  </para>

  <para>
   Also configure OpenAM to consume and to forward the headers as necessary.
   When configuring OpenAM through the console, you set the following properties
   under Configuration > Servers and Sites > Servers
   > <replaceable>Server Name</replaceable> > Advanced.
  </para>

  <para>
   For example, to configure OpenAM to look for the client IP address
   in the <literal>X-Forwarded-For</literal> request header,
   set the advanced configuration property
   <literal>com.sun.identity.authentication.client.ipAddressHeader</literal>
   to <literal>X-Forwarded-For</literal>.
  </para>

  <para>
   In a site configuration where one OpenAM server
   can forward requests to another OpenAM server,
   you can retain the header by adding it to the advanced configuration property
   <literal>openam.retained.http.request.headers</literal>.
   If <literal>X-Forwarded-For</literal> is the only additional header to retain,
   set <literal>openam.retained.http.request.headers</literal> to
   <literal>X-DSAMEVersion,X-Forwarded-For</literal>, for example.
  </para>
 </section>
</chapter>
