<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ! CCPL HEADER START
  !
  ! This work is licensed under the Creative Commons
  ! Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 3.0 Unported License.
  ! To view a copy of this license, visit
  ! http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/
  ! or send a letter to Creative Commons, 444 Castro Street,
  ! Suite 900, Mountain View, California, 94041, USA.
  !
  ! You can also obtain a copy of the license at
  ! src/main/resources/legal-notices/CC-BY-NC-ND.txt.
  ! See the License for the specific language governing permissions
  ! and limitations under the License.
  !
  ! If applicable, add the following below this CCPL HEADER, with the fields
  ! enclosed by brackets "[]" replaced with your own identifying information:
  !      Portions Copyright [yyyy] [name of copyright owner]
  !
  ! CCPL HEADER END
  !
  !      Copyright 2011-2014 ForgeRock AS
  !    
-->
<chapter xml:id='chap-session-failover'
 xmlns='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook'
 version='5.0' xml:lang='en'
 xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'
 xsi:schemaLocation='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook
                     http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd'
 xmlns:xlink='http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink'>
 <title>Setting Up OpenAM Session Failover</title>

 <indexterm>
  <primary>Installing</primary>
  <secondary>Session failover</secondary>
 </indexterm>
 <indexterm>
  <primary>session failover</primary>
 </indexterm>

 <para>
  This chapter covers setting up session failover (SFO).
  Session failover allows another OpenAM server to manage a session
  when the server that initially authenticated the user is down.
  This means the user does not need to log in again,
  even though the server that authenticated them is down.
 </para>

 <para>
  Session failover (high availability for sessions) builds
  on OpenAM service availability.
  Before configuring session failover,
  you must therefore first make the overall OpenAM service highly available.
  This is done by setting up OpenAM in a site configuration.
  You can find instructions for setting up a site configuration in the chapter,
  <link
   xlink:show="new"
   xlink:href="install-guide#chap-install-multiple"
   xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"
  ><citetitle>Installing Multiple Servers</citetitle></link>.
 </para>
 
 <para>
  Session failover also relies on a shared Core Token Service (CTS)
  to store user session data.
  The service is shared with other OpenAM servers in the same OpenAM Site.
  When an OpenAM server goes down, other servers in the Site
  can read user session information from the CTS,
  so the user with a valid session does not have to log in again.
  When the original OpenAM server becomes available again,
  it can also read session information from the CTS,
  and can carry on serving users with active sessions.
  By default the Core Token Service uses the embedded OpenDJ directory server.
  For more information on configuring the Core Token Service, see the chapter,
  <link
   xlink:show="new"
   xlink:href="install-guide#chap-cts"
   xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"
  ><citetitle>Configuring the Core Token Service (CTS)</citetitle></link>.
 </para>

 <para>
  In deployments with multiple OpenAM Sites,
  session failover can function across Sites.
  In order for this to work, all Sites must use
  the same, global, underlying Core Token Service,
  which is replicated across all Sites.
  Then when an entire Site fails or becomes unavailable,
  OpenAM servers in another Site detect the failure of the Site's load balancer
  and attempt to recover the user session from the global Core Token Service.
 </para>

 <para>
  In the event of a failure,
  client applications can connect to an OpenAM server in an active data center
  as shown in <xref linkend="figure-global-cts" />.
 </para>

 <figure xml:id="figure-global-cts">
  <title>Core Token Service For Global Session Failover</title>

  <mediaobject>
   <alt>Global CTS</alt>
   <imageobject>
       <imagedata fileref="images/global-cts.png" format="PNG" />
   </imageobject>
   <textobject>
       <para>
        Shows a globally replicated Core Token Service with two data centers
       </para>
   </textobject>
  </mediaobject>
 </figure>

 <para>
  For more information on how this is done with OpenDJ directory server,
  see the OpenDJ documentation on
  <link
   xlink:show="new"
   xlink:href="${opendjDocBase}/admin-guide/#chap-replication"
  ><citetitle>Managing Data Replication</citetitle></link>.
 </para>

 <procedure xml:id="enable-session-failover">
  <title>To Configure Session Failover After Installation</title>

  <indexterm>
   <primary>session failover</primary>
   <secondary>configuring</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
   Session failover requires an OpenAM Site configuration
   with a Core Token Service.
  </para>

  <para>
   If you did not configure session persistence and availability during
   initial configuration,
   first complete the steps in the procedure,
   <link
    xlink:show="new"
    xlink:href="install-guide#configure-site-load-balancing"
    xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"
   ><citetitle>To Configure Site Load Balancing</citetitle></link>,
   and then follow these steps.
  </para>

  <step>
   <para>
    In the OpenAM console for one of the servers in the Site,
    under Configuration > Global, click Session.
   </para>
  </step>

  <step>
   <para>
    Under Secondary Configuration Instance, click New.
   </para>

   <para>
    If the server is not part of a Site,
    or if the configuration server does not support the Core Token Service,
    the New button is grayed out.
   </para>
  </step>

  <step>
   <para>
    In the Add Sub Configuration page,
    check that the Name is set to the name of the site.
   </para>
  </step>

  <step>
   <para>
    To activate the Session Persistence and High Availability Failover option,
    check the Enabled box.
   </para>
  </step>

  <step>
   <para>To ensure that local OpenAM instances resolve sessions from the Core
    Token Service session store rather than by using crosstalk, check the Reduce
    Crosstalk Enabled box. For more information about crosstalk, see the section,
    <link
     xlink:show="new"
     xlink:href="install-guide#chap-install-multiple"
     xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"
     ><citetitle>To Configure Site Load Balancing</citetitle></link>.
   </para>

   <para>Do not disable reduced crosstalk unless advised to do so by ForgeRock
    Technical Support.
   </para>
  </step>

  <step>
   <para>
    Set reduced crosstalk options.
   </para>
   <para>
    Session logout/destroy broadcasting enables
    notification to all servers in an OpenAM site when a user logs out or
    her session is destroyed by the OpenAM server. The broadcast notifications
    are in addition to normal session logout/destroy notifications sent to
    interested clients and servers.
   </para>
   <para>
    Without session logout/destroy broadcasting,
    it is possible for a user to log out
    from one OpenAM server and then access her session on another server during
    the brief window between the logout and session store replication.
    Enabling session
    logout/destroy broadcasting ensures that logged out and destroyed sessions
    have the correct state on all OpenAM servers.
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Select Disabled if you do not want the OpenAM server to broadcast session
      logout/destroy messages. Session logout/destroy broadcasting is disabled
      by default. Disabling broadcasting is suitable when you do not need the
      highest level of security. Disable broadcasting when you do not expect
      users to maliciously attempt to access logged out or destroyed sessions.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      Specify one of the two broadcast options to achieve a higher level of
      security, at a cost of incurring additional network I/O. Select
      "Broadcast only to local site servers" if your session store
      supports a single OpenAM site. Select
      "Broadcast to servers in all sites" if your session store
      supports multiple OpenAM sites.
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>

   <para>
    The Reduced Crosstalk Purge
    Delay option specifies the amount of time (in minutes) before
    sessions are purged from OpenAM servers after the server receives
    session logout/destroy broadcast notification. The delay ensures that
    sessions are in memory during the time between
    session logout/destruction and session store replication.
   </para>
   <para>
    The default purge delay is 1 minute, which should be adequate unless
    session store replication is abnormally slow on your network.
   </para>
  </step>

  <step>
   <para>
    Click Add to save your work.
   </para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>
    Restart all the OpenAM servers in the site.
   </para>
  </step>
 </procedure>
</chapter>
