<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ! CCPL HEADER START
  !
  ! This work is licensed under the Creative Commons
  ! Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 3.0 Unported License.
  ! To view a copy of this license, visit
  ! http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/
  ! or send a letter to Creative Commons, 444 Castro Street,
  ! Suite 900, Mountain View, California, 94041, USA.
  !
  ! You can also obtain a copy of the license at
  ! src/main/resources/legal-notices/CC-BY-NC-ND.txt.
  ! See the License for the specific language governing permissions
  ! and limitations under the License.
  !
  ! If applicable, add the following below this CCPL HEADER, with the fields
  ! enclosed by brackets "[]" replaced with your own identifying information:
  !      Portions Copyright [yyyy] [name of copyright owner]
  !
  ! CCPL HEADER END
  !
  !      Copyright 2011-2013 ForgeRock AS
  !    
-->
<chapter xml:id='chap-session-failover'
 xmlns='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook'
 version='5.0' xml:lang='en'
 xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'
 xsi:schemaLocation='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd'
 xmlns:xlink='http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink'>
 <title>Setting Up OpenAM Session Failover</title>
 <indexterm>
  <primary>Installing</primary>
  <secondary>Session failover</secondary>
 </indexterm>
 <indexterm>
  <primary>Installing</primary>
  <secondary>Load Balancer</secondary>
 </indexterm>
 <para>This chapter covers setting up SFO when using multiple
 instances of OpenAM in a site configuration for high availability. The basic
 idea followed here is that you configure load balancing to be sticky, based
 on the value of an OpenAM cookie, <literal>amlbcookie</literal>, different
 for each OpenAM server. Should that server become unavailable, the load
 balancer fails client requests over to another OpenAM server. The other OpenAM
 server must then fail over the user session associated with the client.</para>
 
 <para>SFO relies on a shared, highly available Core Token Service (CTS) to
 store user session data. The service is shared with other OpenAM servers in the
 same OpenAM site. When the OpenAM server where a user authenticated goes down,
 other servers in the site read user session information from the CTS, so the
 user with a valid session does not have to login again. When the original
 OpenAM server becomes available again, it can also read session information
 from the CTS, and can carry on serving users with active sessions.</para>

 <itemizedlist>
  <para>This chapter includes these procedures.</para>

  <listitem><para><xref linkend="configure-site-after-installation" /></para></listitem>
  <listitem><para><xref linkend="configure-site-load-balancing" /></para></listitem>
  <listitem><para><xref linkend="enable-session-failover" /></para></listitem>
 </itemizedlist>

 <procedure xml:id="configure-site-after-installation">
  <title>To Configure a Site with a First OpenAM Server</title>
  
  <para>Before you set up SFO, first configure OpenAM in a site configuration
  with a load balancer as the entry point to the site. The most expedient way
  to configure the site is to set it up during the initial OpenAM configuration.
  However, you may already have a working instance before realizing that
  multiple instances are necessary. The following steps walk you through setting
  up the site configuration for the first OpenAM server.</para>

  <para>Once you have set up a site for the first OpenAM server, see <link
  xlink:href="install-guide#add-servers-to-site" xlink:show="new"
  xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"><citetitle>To Add a Server
  to a Site</citetitle></link> for instructions on configuring subsequent
  servers in the site.</para>
  
  <step>
   <para>Login to OpenAM Console as <literal>amadmin</literal>, and then browse
   to Configuration > Servers and Sites > Sites.</para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>Click New, and on the New Site page enter the site name, and set the
   Primary URL to the load balancer URL that is the entry point for the site,
   such as <literal>https://lb.example.com/openam</literal>.</para>

   <para>The site URL is the URL to the load balancer in front of your OpenAM
   servers in the site. For example, if your load balancer listens for HTTPS on
   host <literal>lb.example.com</literal> and port <literal>443</literal>,
   with OpenAM under <literal>/openam</literal>, then your site URL is
   <literal>https://lb.example.com/openam</literal>.</para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>Click Save to keep the site configuration.</para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>Under Configuration > Servers and Sites > Server, click the link
   to the server configuration.</para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>On the server configuration General tab page, set the Parent Site to
   the name of the site you just created, and then click Save to keep your
   changes.</para>

   <para>At this point the server is part of the site you have configured.</para>
  </step>
 </procedure>

 <procedure xml:id="configure-site-load-balancing">
  <title>To Configure Site Load Balancing</title>
  
  <para>If you did not set up the site during initial configuration,
  first follow the instructions in <xref
  linkend="configure-site-after-installation" />, and then follow all the
  steps below.</para>
  
  <step>
   <para>For each OpenAM server in the site, select Configuration &gt;
   Servers and Sites &gt; Servers &gt; <replaceable>Server Name</replaceable>,
   and then set Parent Site to the site you created before saving your
   work.</para>
  </step>

  <step>
   <para>In an OpenAM site, the server that authenticated a user is the server
   that continues to manage that user's session, unless the server is no longer
   available. Therefore, you should use sticky load balancing. To do so,
   configure your load balancer to inspect the value of the
   <literal>amlbcookie</literal> so that it can determine which
   OpenAM server should receive the client request.</para>

   <para>As your load balancer depends on the <literal>amlbcookie</literal>
   value, on each OpenAM server console in the site, select Configuration &gt;
   Servers and Sites &gt; Servers &gt; <replaceable>Server Name</replaceable>
   &gt; Advanced, makes sure that
   <literal>com.iplanet.am.lbcookie.value</literal> is unique. By default
   the value of the <literal>amlbcookie</literal> is set to the server ID
   for the OpenAM instance.</para>

   <note>
    <para>When using SSL, the approach requires that you either terminate SSL
    on the load balancer and re-encrypt traffic from the load balancer
    to the OpenAM servers.</para>
   </note>

   <para>If you must change <literal>amlbcookie</literal> values to make them
   unique, then your changes take effect after you restart the OpenAM server.
   (To check, login to the console and check the cookie value in your
   browser.)</para>
  </step>

  <step>
   <para>Restart each OpenAM server or the web containers where the OpenAM
   servers run so that all configuration changes take effect.</para>
  </step>
 </procedure>
 
 <procedure xml:id="enable-session-failover">
  <title>To Configure Session Failover After Installation</title>
  
  <para>Session failover requires a site configuration with one or more servers
  and OpenDJ as a configuration store (embedded or external).</para>

  <para>If you did not configure session persistence and availability during
  initial configuration, first complete the steps in <xref
  linkend="configure-site-load-balancing" />, and then follow these steps.</para>

  <step>
   <para>In the OpenAM console for one of the servers in the site, under
   Configuration > Global, click Session.</para>
  </step>

  <step>
   <para>Under Secondary Configuration Instance, click New.</para>

   <para>If the server is not part of a site, or if you are not using OpenDJ
   server, the New button is grayed out.</para>
  </step>

  <step>
   <para>In the Add Sub Configuration page, check that the Name is set to the
   name of the site.</para>
  </step>

  <step>
   <para>Activate the Session Persistence and High Availability Failover Enabled option.</para>
  </step>

  <step>
   <para>Click Add to save your work.</para>
  </step>
 </procedure>
</chapter>
