<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ! CCPL HEADER START
  !
  ! This work is licensed under the Creative Commons
  ! Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 3.0 Unported License.
  ! To view a copy of this license, visit
  ! http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/
  ! or send a letter to Creative Commons, 444 Castro Street,
  ! Suite 900, Mountain View, California, 94041, USA.
  !
  ! You can also obtain a copy of the license at
  ! src/main/resources/legal-notices/CC-BY-NC-ND.txt.
  ! See the License for the specific language governing permissions
  ! and limitations under the License.
  !
  ! If applicable, add the following below this CCPL HEADER, with the fields
  ! enclosed by brackets "[]" replaced with your own identifying information:
  !      Portions Copyright [yyyy] [name of copyright owner]
  !
  ! CCPL HEADER END
  !
  !      Copyright 2012-2013 ForgeRock AS
  !    
-->
<chapter xml:id='chap-securing'
 xmlns='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook'
 version='5.0' xml:lang='en'
 xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'
 xsi:schemaLocation='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd'
 xmlns:xlink='http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink'
 xmlns:xinclude='http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude'>
 <title>Securing OpenAM</title>
 <indexterm>
  <primary>Securing OpenAM</primary>
 </indexterm>

 <para>This chapter identifies best practices for securing your OpenAM
 deployment.</para>

 <section xml:id="avoid-obvious-defaults">
  <title>Avoiding Obvious Defaults</title>

  <itemizedlist>
   <para>OpenAM includes default settings to make it easier for you to
   evaluate the software. Avoid these default settings in production
   deployments.</para>

   <listitem>
    <para>When connecting to LDAP, bind with a specific administrative account
    rather than a root DN account if possible.</para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>Change the default <literal>iPlanetDirectoryPro</literal> cookie name
    both in OpenAM (<literal>com.iplanet.am.cookie.name</literal>) and in your
    policy agent profiles (<literal
    >com.sun.identity.agents.config.cookie.name</literal>).</para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>When installing OpenAM, do not use <literal>/openam</literal> or
    <literal>/opensso</literal> as the deployment URI.</para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>Set valid goto URL domains for OpenAM in the core authentication
    module configuration. The parameter is described in the section providing
    <link xlink:show="new" xlink:href="admin-guide#core-module-conf-hints"
    xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"><citetitle>Hints For the
    Core Authentication Module</citetitle></link> (<literal
    >iplanet-am-auth-valid-goto-domains</literal>).</para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>Create an administrator in the top-level realm with a different ID
    than the default <literal>amadmin</literal>.</para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>Create specific administrator users to track better who makes
    configuration changes.</para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>Set the OpenAM advanced property
    <literal>openam.auth.soap.rest.generic.authentication.exception</literal>
    to <literal>true</literal>. This causes OpenAM to return the same exception
    both when the user does not exist, and also when the password is not
    valid.</para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </section>

 <section xml:id="protect-network-access">
  <title>Protecting Network Access</title>

   <para>Anytime users interact with a web service, there are risks. With OpenAM, you can
   reduce those risks by deploying different parts of OpenAM in appropriate parts of an
   enterprise network.</para>

    <para>To minimize risks, deploy only the core OpenAM server on systems directly connected
        through a firewall. As a start, deploy only the core server (and the protected web application)
        on Internet-facing servers. For instructions, see the following section from the
        OpenAM Installation Guide, <link xlink:href="install-guide#which-war-to-deploy"
        xlink:show="new" xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"><citetitle>Determine Which
        War File to Deploy</citetitle></link>.</para>

    <para>You can further limit what is exposed through the firewall by using one of two strategies:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>Set up a distributed authentication user interface (UI) in a DMZ between firewalls.</para>
            <para>The distributed authentication UI is essentially a small subset of the OpenAM server with
            just enough login logic to receive user authentication requests. Those requests are forwarded
            to the core OpenAM servers.</para>
            <para>See <link xlink:href="install-guide#chap-install-das"
                  xlink:show="new" xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"><citetitle>Installing
                    OpenAM Distributed Authentication</citetitle></link> for installation
                instructions. The following figure shows the recommended architecture.</para>
            <mediaobject xml:id="figure-securing-openam-daui">
                <alt>Exposing only the Distributed Authentication UI to the Internet</alt>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/securing-openam-daui.png" format="PNG" />
                </imageobject>
                <textobject><para>The OpenAM Distributed Authentication UI can hide many
                    OpenAM administrative capabilities from the Internet. Notice that OpenAM
                    installed with the console is inside your infrastructure as well.</para></textobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
            <para>Alternatively, use a reverse proxy in front of OpenAM to allow access only to
            the necessary URLs. The following figure shows the recommended architecture with a
            reverse proxy.</para>

            <mediaobject xml:id="figure-securing-openam-rp">
                <alt>Exposing only a reverse proxy to the Internet</alt>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/securing-openam-rp.png" format="PNG" />
                </imageobject>
                <textobject><para>By placing a reverse proxy between OpenAM and the
                    Internet, you expose only the necessary endpoints outside your
                    infrastructure. Notice that OpenAM installed with the console is inside
                    your infrastructure as well.</para></textobject>
            </mediaobject>
            <para>For access to the console, deploy the full OpenAM application<footnote
                    ><para>Console only deployment is no longer supported.</para></footnote> on
                a separate system that is reachable only from internal systems. Do not
                include the full OpenAM server in the load-balanced pool of OpenAM servers
                serving applications.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Leave <literal>ssoadm.jsp</literal> disabled in production. (Advanced
                property: <literal>ssoadm.disabled=true</literal>)</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>If possible in your deployment, control access to OpenAM console by
                network address, such that administrators can only connect from well-known
                systems and networks.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>Restrict access to URIs that you do not use, and prevent internal
                endpoints such as <literal>/sessionservice</literal> from being reachable
                over the Internet.</para>
            <para>For a full list of endpoints, see the OpenAM Reference Guide
            Chapter on <link xlink:show="new" xlink:href="reference#chap-endpoints"
            xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink">
            <citetitle>Service Endpoints</citetitle></link>.</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
 </section>

 <section xml:id="secure-openam-administration">
  <title>Securing OpenAM Administration</title>

  <itemizedlist>
   <para>Keep administration of access management services separate from
   management of the services themselves.</para>

   <listitem>
    <para>Create realms for your organization(s) and separate administrative
    users from end users. For instructions, see <link
    xlink:href="admin-guide#chap-realms" xlink:show="new"
    xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"><citetitle>Configuring
    Realms</citetitle></link>. You must then either:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>Use the <literal>realm=<replaceable>realm-name</replaceable></literal>
      query string parameter when redirecting users to OpenAM, which gives you
      a way to isolate the URLs used by an application.</para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>Create fully qualified domain name realm/DNS aliases, and use
      them to control access to the realms.</para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>When customizing <filename>config/auth/default*/Login.jsp</filename>,
    make sure that you do not introduce any security vulnerabilities such as
    cross-site scripting due to unvalidated input.</para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>Create a policy agent profile for each policy agent. See <link
    xlink:href="admin-guide#chap-agents" xlink:show="new"
    xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"><citetitle>Configuring
    Policy Agent Profiles</citetitle></link> for instructions.</para>
   </listitem>

  </itemizedlist>
 </section>

 <section xml:id="secure-communications">
  <title>Securing Communications</title>

  <itemizedlist>
   <para>Keep communications secure by using encryption, properly configured
   cookies, and request and response signatures.</para>

   <listitem>
    <para>Protect network traffic by using HTTPS and LDAPS where
    possible.</para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>When using HTTPS, use <link xlink:show="new"
    xlink:href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/HTTP_cookie#Secure_and_HttpOnly"
    >secure cookies</link>.</para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>Where possible, use subdomain cookies, and control subdomains in
    a specific DNS master.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>Use cookie hijacking protection with restricted tokens, where each
    policy agent uses different SSO tokens for the same user. See <link
    xlink:show="new" xlink:href="admin-guide#enable-cdsso-cookie-hijacking-protection"
    xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"><citetitle>To Protect
    Against CDSSO Cookie Hijacking</citetitle></link> for instructions.</para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>When using SAML 2.0:</para>
    <itemizedlist>
     <listitem>
      <para>Sign authentication requests, authentication responses, and single
      logout requests.</para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>If the other entities in your circle of trust can handle encryption,
      then use encryption as well.</para>
     </listitem>
     <listitem>
      <para>Use your own key, not the <literal>test</literal> key provided with
      OpenAM.</para>
     </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
 </section>


    <section xml:id="amadmin-changes">
        <title>Administering the amadmin Account</title>

        <para>You can make changes to the password and user name for the main OpenAM administrative account.</para>
        <para>You can change the user name of the <literal>amadmin</literal> administrative account
            to something more obscure, such as superroot. However, the capabilities of that alternative administrative
            account would not be complete, due to some hard-coding of <literal>amadmin</literal> in the source files.
            When changing the password for the main OpenAM administrative account, you must make a corresponding change
            to the authentication datastore. That datastore could be OpenDJ. The steps you would take to change
            the OpenAM top-level administrative password and account name are shown in the following sections.</para>

        <procedure xml:id="change-amadmin-password">
            <title>To Change the Password for the Top-Level Administrator (normally <literal>amadmin</literal>)</title>

            <step>
                <para>Login to the OpenAM console as the administrator, normally
                    <literal>amadmin</literal>.</para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>Under Access Control &gt; / (Top Level Realm) &gt; Subjects &gt; User, select the name of the
                    current top-level administrative user.</para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>In the page that appears, navigate to the Password row and click Edit.</para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>In the window that appears, enter the desired new password in the New Password and
                    Re-Enter Password text boxes.</para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>Click OK to implement the change. If you want to cancel, click Close or just close the window.</para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>You'll also need to change the password for the administrator on the directory server. If you are
                    using OpenDJ, refer to the <link xlink:show="new"
                    xlink:href="admin-guide#troubleshoot-reset-admin-passwords"
                    xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"><citetitle>OpenDJ Administration Guide</citetitle> section on Resetting Administrator
                    Passwords</link>. If you are using a different directory server, you will have to refer to the
                documentation for that server.</para>
            </step>
        </procedure>

        <para>In the following steps, you will identify the new administrative user by assigning it to the <literal>
            com.sun.identity.authentication.super.user</literal> directive. You may also need to create an
            OpenAM account for the new administrative user. Don't forget to make sure that new administrative
            account is configured in the corresponding directory server such as OpenDJ.
        </para>

        <procedure xml:id="change-amadmin-uid">
            <title>To Change the Account Name for the Top-Level Administrator (normally <literal>amadmin</literal>)</title>

            <step>
                <para>Login to the OpenAM console as the administrator, normally
                    <literal>amadmin</literal>.</para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>Navigate to the page where you can set the properties for different classes. Select
                    Configuration &gt; Servers and Sites &gt; <replaceable>Server Name</replaceable> &gt; Advanced.</para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>In the Advanced Properties window that appears, click Add.</para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>You'll see blank entries in the end of the list of Property Names and Property Values. In the
                    empty Property Name text box, enter <literal>com.sun.identity.authentication.super.user</literal>.</para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>In the corresponding Property Values test box, enter appropriate values for the new administrative
                    user in LDAP Data Interchange Format (LDIF). For example, the following entry would set up an
                    administrative user named <literal>superroot</literal>, in the organizational unit named <literal>
                        people</literal>people, associated with the example.com domain:
                    <literal>uid=superroot,ou=people,dc=example,dc=com</literal>.</para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>Click Save to save the changes that you've made. </para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>If the account doesn't already exist in OpenAM or on a connected directory server, you'll need to
               create it. To do so, select Access Control &gt; / (Top Level Realm) &gt; Subject &gt; User &gt; New.
               In the New User window that appears, create the new user. Make sure to enter an appropriate password
               and make that user Active. The ID for that new user is the user name.</para>
            </step>
            <step>
                <para>As noted earlier, you'll also need to make sure that the corresponding account on the directory server
                has at least CN=Directory Manager  privileges. If you're using OpenDJ, refer to the chapter on
                    <citetitle>Configuring Privileges &amp; Access Control</citetitle> in the
                    <link xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"
                    xlink:href="admin-guide#chap-privileges-acls" xlink:show="new">
                    <citetitle>OpenDJ Administration Guide</citetitle></link>.</para>
            </step>
        </procedure>

        <para>If you do change the account name of the top-level administrative account, you should be aware that the
        original <literal>amadmin</literal> account is "hard-coded" in the source code of several files.
            The code in these files may affect the functionality of a top-level administrative user
            with a name other than <literal>amadmin</literal>.</para>

        <para>One of the improvements that we plan to make to OpenAM is to eliminate these instances of hard-coding.
        Until we make such improvements, the amadmin user would retain privileges related to the LoginState and some
        IDM-related classes.</para>

    </section>

</chapter>
