<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ! CCPL HEADER START
  !
  ! This work is licensed under the Creative Commons
  ! Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 3.0 Unported License.
  ! To view a copy of this license, visit
  ! http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/
  ! or send a letter to Creative Commons, 444 Castro Street,
  ! Suite 900, Mountain View, California, 94041, USA.
  !
  ! You can also obtain a copy of the license at
  ! src/main/resources/legal-notices/CC-BY-NC-ND.txt.
  ! See the License for the specific language governing permissions
  ! and limitations under the License.
  !
  ! If applicable, add the following below this CCPL HEADER, with the fields
  ! enclosed by brackets "[]" replaced with your own identifying information:
  !      Portions Copyright [yyyy] [name of copyright owner]
  !
  ! CCPL HEADER END
  !
  !      Copyright 2013 ForgeRock AS
  !
-->
<chapter xml:id='chap-mobile'
         xmlns='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook'
         version='5.0' xml:lang='en'
         xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'
         xsi:schemaLocation='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd'
         xmlns:xlink='http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink'>
 <title>Working with Mobile Devices &amp; Applications</title>

 <para>When building applications that run on mobile devices, you can use
 the same OpenAM service that you also use for access management in your
 web, cloud, and other applications. OpenAM has features that make it
 particularly well suited for the mobile world, too.</para>

 <section xml:id="mobile-oauth">
  <title>Simplifying Access on Mobile Devices</title>

  <para>On many mobile devices, users want to avoid repeatedly entering
  credentials such as an email address or user name and a password. They
  do not want new credentials to manage for every application they try.
  They do not want to share their credentials across applications. Instead
  users want single sign-on with few identity providers. They want to
  authorize access for applications rather than share their
  credentials.</para>

  <para>OpenAM supports emerging standards including <link xlink:show="new"
  xlink:href="admin-guide#chap-oauth2"
  xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink">OAuth 2.0</link> and <link
  xlink:show="new" xlink:href="admin-guide#chap-openid"
  xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink">OpenID Connect 1.0</link>.
  After you register your application as an OAuth or OpenID Connect client
  with OpenAM, your application can then redirect a user to OpenAM to
  authenticate and to authorize access to resources that the user owns,
  such as profile data. Your application gets an access token that can be
  used later to gain authorized access without requiring the user to
  authenticate again. OpenID Connect extends OAuth, standardizing how client
  applications discover and register with identity providers, and also
  defining how applications can manage user sessions and handle logout when
  they no longer want to authorize access.</para>

  <mediaobject xml:id="figure-mobile-oauth">
   <alt>OAuth 2.0 with a mobile application</alt>
   <imageobject>
    <imagedata fileref="images/mobile-oauth.png" format="PNG" />
   </imageobject>
   <textobject>
    <para>The mobile application is an OAuth 2.0 client.</para>
   </textobject>
  </mediaobject>

  <para>An OAuth 2.0 client application can thus make simplify the user
  experience on the phone to authorizing access.</para>

  <mediaobject xml:id="figure-oauth2-phone">
   <alt>OAuth 2.0 mobile application demonstration</alt>
   <imageobject>
    <imagedata fileref="images/oauth2-phone.png" format="PNG" />
   </imageobject>
   <textobject>
    <para>This mobile application shows an OAuth 2.0 client reducing user
    interaction to an authorization decision.</para>
   </textobject>
  </mediaobject>

  <para>In addition to serving as an identity provider, OpenAM can also
  function as an OAuth 2.0 client, protecting access to resources within
  your control based on authorization granted by an identity provider who
  users already know and use, such as Facebook, Google, MSN and others.
  OpenAM's built in authorization policy management makes it
  straightforward to integrate this capability into your
  applications.</para>

  <para>The OAuth and OpenID Connect standards specify REST interfaces,
  making them essentially programming language-independent and accessible
  for web applications and mobile applications alike.</para>

  <para>OpenAM also supports <link xlink:href="http://www.openauthentication.org/"
  xlink:show="new">Open Authentication</link> architecture with the OATH module
  mentioned in the next section.</para>
 </section>

 <section xml:id="mobile-oath">
  <title>Protecting Access for Mobile Users</title>

  <para>You must give users access to your organization's resources while
  they are on the go. At the same time you must manage risk. OpenAM
  supports risk-based adaptive authentication, device fingerprints,
  one-time passwords and other multi-factor authentication capabilities
  that help you do both. As OpenAM handles authentication through
  plugin modules that you can chain, your OpenAM service can meet a
  variety of requirements.</para>

  <para>OpenAM's <link xlink:show="new"
  xlink:href="admin-guide#adaptive-auth-module-conf-hints"
  xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink">Adaptive Risk authentication
  module</link> lets you add risk assessment to any authentication module
  chain, dynamically requiring stronger authentication when circumstances
  require it (new location, ancient last login time, new device, new IP address,
  specific application, and so forth). You can add the <link xlink:show="new"
  xlink:href="admin-guide#device-print-auth-module-conf-hints"
  xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink">Device Print module</link>
  to an authentication chain to fingerprint users' devices for additional risk
  assessment, making it easier to handle sign-on when users bring their
  own devices.</para>

  <mediaobject xml:id="figure-adaptive-auth-module-again">
   <alt>Including the Adaptive Risk module in an authentication chain</alt>
   <imageobject>
    <imagedata fileref="images/adaptive-auth-module.png" format="PNG" />
   </imageobject>
   <textobject>
    <para>With the Adaptive Risk module set as sufficient for authentication,
    OpenAM continues to the next module in the chain should the Adaptive Risk
    module return failure.</para>
   </textobject>
  </mediaobject>

  <para>OpenAM also lets you decide exactly what stronger authentication
  means in your situation. You can for example add multi-factor
  authentication involving mobile devices using OpenAM's <link xlink:show="new"
  xlink:href="admin-guide#OATH-module-conf-hints"
  xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink">OATH</link> and <link
  xlink:show="new" xlink:href="admin-guide#hotp-module-conf-hints"
  xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink">HOTP</link>
  modules either to use a one-time password soft token generated on a
  device, or to send a one-time password in a text message to a mobile
  phone.</para>

  <para>In addition to capabilities supporting new applications, OpenAM
  integrates well with existing systems needed by users on the move.
  Whether users are authenticating from a mobile device through a gateway
  using an MSISDN, starting single sign-on by logging on to a laptop, or
  connecting to a VPN with certificate based authentication, OpenAM has an
  authentication module for that.</para>

  <mediaobject xml:id="figure-openam-modules">
   <alt>OpenAM authentication modules</alt>
   <imageobject>
    <imagedata fileref="images/openam-modules.png" format="PNG" />
   </imageobject>
   <textobject>
    <para>OpenAM offers many authentication modules out of the box.</para>
   </textobject>
  </mediaobject>

  <para>All of these capabilities are available with OpenAM out of the
  box.</para>
 </section>

 <section xml:id="mobile-rest">
  <title>Simplifying Access with REST APIs</title>

  <para>Representational State Transfer (REST) is a architectural style
  designed in parallel with HTTP. REST simplifies integration and
  deployment while enabling layered, web-scale services. REST APIs in OpenAM
  implement REST in a way that reuses common HTTP verbs and decouples APIs
  from the programming languages that developers use to interact with them.
  OpenAM exposes REST APIs for many capabilities such as those in the following
  list.</para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>Authentication (including a callback mechanism so applications can
    work with all OpenAM authentication modules)</para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>Logout</para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>Managing groups</para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>Managing policy agent profiles</para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>Managing realms</para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>Managing user profiles</para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>OAuth 2.0 authorization</para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>OpenAM native authorization</para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>OpenID Connect 1.0 authorization</para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>Resetting forgotten passwords</para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>Token validation</para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>User self-registration</para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <mediaobject xml:id="figure-openam-single">
   <alt>OpenAM capabilities in a single image</alt>
   <imageobject>
    <imagedata fileref="images/openam-single.png" format="PNG" />
   </imageobject>
   <textobject>
    <para>REST APIs are a core feature of OpenAM.</para>
   </textobject>
  </mediaobject>

  <para>As <link xlink:show="new" xlink:href="dev-guide#chap-rest"
  xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink">OpenAM REST APIs</link>
  provide language-independent access, they make it easier to build cross-device
  applications. Developers can use the same APIs to access OpenAM both from
  web applications and also from native mobile applications.</para>

  <para>Furthermore OpenAM REST APIs are built on an underlying common
  REST framework, designed to provide common access to resource providers.
  The common REST framework standardizes both how resource providers serve
  standard requests (create, read, update, delete, query, patch), and also
  how resource providers offer extended operations in a managed way (using
  actions). Applications built to interact with OpenAM REST APIs
  increasingly can interoperate with other products in the ForgeRock stack
  such as <link xlink:show="new"
  xlink:href="http://forgerock.com/what-we-offer/open-identity-stack/openidm/"
  >OpenIDM for identity management</link> and <link xlink:show="new"
  xlink:href="http://forgerock.com/what-we-offer/open-identity-stack/opendj/"
  >OpenDJ for highly available data</link>.</para>
 </section>

 <section xml:id="get-mobile-sample-apps">
  <title>Getting Source Code for Sample Mobile Applications</title>

  <para>
   You can get source code for sample mobile applications
   from ForgeRock's public source code repository under
   <literal>https://svn.forgerock.org/commons/samples/mobile</literal>.
  </para>

  <para>
   For example, if you have a Mac running OS X 10.8 or later
   with Xcode installed, try the <link xlink:show="new"
   xlink:href="http://commons.forgerock.org/samples/mobile/ios/openam-ios-oauth2-sample-app/"
   >OpenAM OAuth 2.0 iOS Sample App</link>.
  </para>

  <mediaobject xml:id="figure-ios-auth2-sample-app">
   <alt>OpenAM OAuth 2.0 iOS Sample App</alt>
   <imageobject>
    <imagedata fileref="images/ios-auth2-sample-app.png" format="PNG" />
   </imageobject>
   <textobject>
    <para>
     The OAuth 2.0 iOS Sample App demonstrates use of OpenAM server's standard
     OAuth 2.0 REST API to authorize OAuth 2.0 client access.
    </para>
   </textobject>
  </mediaobject>
 </section>
</chapter>
