<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ! CCPL HEADER START
  !
  ! This work is licensed under the Creative Commons
  ! Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 3.0 Unported License.
  ! To view a copy of this license, visit
  ! http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/
  ! or send a letter to Creative Commons, 444 Castro Street,
  ! Suite 900, Mountain View, California, 94041, USA.
  !
  ! You can also obtain a copy of the license at
  ! src/main/resources/legal-notices/CC-BY-NC-ND.txt.
  ! See the License for the specific language governing permissions
  ! and limitations under the License.
  !
  ! If applicable, add the following below this CCPL HEADER, with the fields
  ! enclosed by brackets "[]" replaced with your own identifying information:
  !      Portions Copyright [yyyy] [name of copyright owner]
  !
  ! CCPL HEADER END
  !
  !      Copyright 2011-2013 ForgeRock AS
  !    
-->
<chapter xml:id='chap-pwd-reset'
 xmlns='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook'
 version='5.0' xml:lang='en'
 xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'
 xsi:schemaLocation='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd'
 xmlns:xlink='http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink'
 xmlns:xinclude='http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude'>
 <title>Configuring Password Reset</title>
 <indexterm><primary>Password reset</primary></indexterm>
 <para>This chapter focuses on how to enable users to reset their own
 passwords in secure fashion.</para>
 
 <section xml:id="about-pwd-reset">
  <title>About Password Reset</title>
  <para>Users who know their passwords, but must reset them because for example
  the password is going to expire, can reset their passwords by successfully
  authenticating to OpenAM, visiting their end user pages, such as
  <literal>http://openam.example.com:8080/openam/idm/EndUser</literal>, and
  clicking Edit next to the Password field to display the change password
  page.</para>
  
  <mediaobject xml:id="figure-console-change-pwd">
   <alt>The OpenAM Change Password page</alt>
   <imageobject>
    <imagedata fileref="images/console-change-pwd.png" format="PNG" />
   </imageobject>
   <textobject><para>Authenticated users can change their passwords
   through the OpenAM console.</para></textobject>
  </mediaobject>
  
  <para>You therefore do not need to configure password reset for users
  who can remember their current password. Instead, you point them to the
  <literal>idm/EndUser</literal> page to let them do it themselves.</para>
 </section>
 
 <section xml:id="forgotten-pwd-reset">
  <title>Resetting Forgotten Passwords</title>
  
  <para>OpenAM can provide self-service password reset for forgotten passwords.
  To enable self-service password reset, you must configure the password
  reset service itself, which consists mainly of setting up secret questions,
  and configuring an SMTP mail server to send reset passwords to the users
  of the service.</para>
  
  <tip>
   <para>Users must be able to access their mail after the service resets
   their passwords, or they will not be able to receive the new password.
   Do not therefore set up the service to reset the password used to access
   the email account specified in the user's profile.</para>
  </tip>
  
  <procedure xml:id="set-up-pwd-reset-service">
   <title>To Set Up the Password Reset Service</title>

   <para>You can configure the password reset service for OpenAM, letting
   each realm inherit the global settings.</para>

   <step performance="optional">
    <para>When OpenAM is configured with default settings, it uses the
    <literal>ldapService</literal> authentication chain, which relies on the
    <literal>DataStore</literal> authentication module. The
    <literal>DataStore</literal> authentication module provides a generic
    authentication mechanism for OpenAM data stores, and therefore cannot
    handle specific data store settings, such as the directory server password
    policy setting to force password changes on reset. When you use settings
    the module cannot handle, then authentication can fail.</para>

    <para>If you must configure the directory server to force password changes
    on reset, then also configure a separate authentication chain for users.
    The separate authentication chain must require the <literal>LDAP</literal>
    authentication module rather than the <literal>DataStore</literal>
    authentication module.</para>

    <para>You can create and configure authentication chains, and assign them
    in the OpenAM console under Access Control &gt; <replaceable>Realm
    Name</replaceable> &gt; Authentication.</para>

    <para>The OpenAM administrator, <literal>amadmin</literal>, uses the
    <literal>DataStore</literal> authentication module. If you set Access
    Control &gt; /(Top Level Realm) &gt; Authentication &gt;
    Core &gt; Organization Authentication Configuration to use your
    <literal>LDAP</literal> based authentication chain for users, let the
    Administrator Authentication Configuration continue to use the
    <literal>DataStore</literal> based authentication chain. To login to the
    OpenAM console as <literal>amadmin</literal>, access the administrator
    console service instead of the UI login service endpoint. For example:
    <literal>http://openam.example.com:8080/openam/console</literal>.</para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>In the OpenAM console, browse to Configuration &gt; Global &gt;
    Password Reset in the Global Properties list.</para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>In the Password Reset page, use the following hints to adjust
    settings, and then save your work.</para>
    <para>In addition to the User Validation and Secret Question values
    provided, you must configure at least the Bind DN and Bind Password
    of the user who can reset passwords in the LDAP data store.</para>
    <variablelist>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>User Validation</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>OpenAM uses this LDAP attribute and the value entered by the
       user to look up the user profile in the data store.</para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Secret Question</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>This list corresponds to property values held in the file
       <filename>WEB-INF/classes/amPasswordReset.properties</filename> under
       the directory where OpenAM is deployed.</para>
       <para>For localized versions of this file, copy
       <filename>WEB-INF/classes/amPasswordReset.properties</filename> to
       <filename>WEB-INF/classes/amPasswordReset_<replaceable>locale</replaceable>.properties</filename>,
       and localize only the values of the questions. For example if the
       default properties file contains:</para>
       <literallayout class="monospaced">favourite-restaurant=What is your favorite restaurant?</literallayout>
       <para>Then <filename>WEB-INF/classes/amPasswordReset_fr.properties</filename>
       ought to contain:</para>
       <literallayout class="monospaced">favourite-restaurant=Quel est votre restaurant préféré ?</literallayout>
       <para>If you change these files, you must restart OpenAM.</para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Search Filter</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>An additional LDAP search filter you specify here is &amp;-ed
       with the filter constructed for user validation to find the user
       entry in the data store.</para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Base DN</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>If you specify no base DN for the search, the search for the user
       entry starts from the base DN for the realm.</para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Bind DN</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>The DN of the user with access to change passwords in the
       LDAP data store.</para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Bind Password</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>The password of the user with access to change passwords in the
       LDAP data store.</para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Password Reset Option</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>Classname of a plugin that implements the
       <literal>PasswordGenerator</literal> interface.</para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Password Change Notification Option</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>Classname of a plugin that implements the
       <literal>NotifyPassword</literal> interface.</para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Password Reset</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>Enables the service.</para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Personal Question</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>When enabled, allows the user to create custom secret
       questions.</para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Maximum Number of Questions</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>Maximum number of questions to ask during password reset.</para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Force Change Password on Next Login</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>When enabled, the user must change her password next time she
       logs in after OpenAM resets her password.</para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Password Reset Failure Lockout</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>When enabled, the user only gets the specified number of tries
       before her account is locked.</para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Password Reset Failure Lockout Count</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>If Password Reset Failure Lockout is enabled, this specifies the
       maximum number of tries to reset a password within the specified
       interval before the user's account is locked.</para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Password Reset Failure Lockout Interval</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>This interval applies when Password Reset Failure Lockout is
       enabled, and when Password Reset Failure Lockout Count is set. During
       this interval, a user can try to reset her password the specified
       number of times before being locked out. For example, if this interval
       is 5 minutes and the count is set to 3, a user gets 3 tries during
       a given 5 minute interval to reset her password.</para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Email Address to Send Lockout Notification</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>This specifies the administrator address(es) which receive(s)
       notification on user account lockout. Each address must be a full
       email address such as <literal>admin@example.com</literal>, or
       <literal>admin@host.domain</literal>.</para>
       <para>OpenAM must be able to send mail through an SMTP-capable service
       for this to work. See <xref linkend="set-up-mail-notification" />.</para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Warn User After N Failures</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>If you configure Password Reset Failure Lockout, set this to
       warn users who are about to use up their count of tries.</para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Password Reset Failure Lockout Duration</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>If you configure Password Reset Failure Lockout, set this to a
       number of minutes other than <literal>0</literal> so that lockout is
       temporary, requiring only that the locked-out user wait to try again
       to reset her password, rather than necessarily require help from
       an administrator.</para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Password Reset Lockout Attribute Name</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>If you configure Password Reset Failure Lockout, then OpenAM sets
       sets data store attribute to <literal>inactive</literal> upon
       lockout.</para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Password Reset Lockout Attribute Value</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>If set to <literal>inactive</literal>, then a user who is locked
       out cannot attempt to reset her password if the Password Reset
       Failure Lockout Duration is <literal>0</literal>.</para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>If you changed Secret Questions in the
    <filename>WEB-INF/classes/amPasswordReset.properties</filename> file or in
    any localized versions, restart OpenAM for the changes to take
    effect.</para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
  
  <procedure xml:id="set-up-mail-notification">
   <title>To Set Up SMTP Mail Notification</title>
   
   <para>By default, OpenAM expects the SMTP service to listen on
   <literal>localhost:25</literal>. You can change these settings.</para>
   
   <step>
    <para>In the OpenAM console, click the Configuration &gt; Servers and
    Sites &gt; Default Server Settings.</para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>In the Edit server-default page, scroll down to Mail Server to
    change the Mail Server Host Name or Mail Server Port Number.</para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>Save your work.</para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
  
  <procedure xml:id="prepare-users-for-pwd-reset">
   <title>To Prepare Users to Reset Passwords</title>
   
   <para>Before a user can reset her password, she must choose answers for
   secret questions.</para>
   
   <step>
    <para>When her account is first created, direct the user to her
    <literal>idm/EndUser</literal> page, such as
    <literal>http://openam.example.com:8080/openam/idm/EndUser</literal>,
    where she can provide a valid email address to recover the reset password
    and can edit Password Reset Options.</para>
    <mediaobject xml:id="figure-console-end-user">
     <alt>The OpenAM end user page</alt>
     <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="images/console-end-user.png" format="PNG" />
     </imageobject>
     <textobject><para>Authenticated users can change their email and
     password reset secret questions through the OpenAM console.</para></textobject>
    </mediaobject>
    <para>By default OpenAM console redirects end users to this page when
    they login.</para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>After the user updates her secret questions, she can use the
    password reset service when necessary.</para>

    <mediaobject xml:id="figure-console-secret-questions">
     <alt>The OpenAM secret question page</alt>
     <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="images/console-secret-questions.png" format="PNG" />
     </imageobject>
     <textobject><para>Authenticated users can change the answers to secret
     questions through the OpenAM console.</para></textobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <note><para>Answers to secret questions are case sensitive.</para></note>
   </step>
  </procedure>
  
  <procedure xml:id="redirect-to-reset-pwd">
   <title>To Direct Users to Reset Passwords</title>
   
   <para>Having setup her email and answers to secret questions, the user
   can use the reset password service.</para>
   <para>Create a test subject and use these steps to validate your
   configuration.</para>
   
   <step>
    <para>Send the user with a forgotten password to enter her user ID at
    the password reset URL.</para>
    <para>If the user is in the default realm use <literal>password</literal>
    at the end of the URL to OpenAM, as in
    <literal>http://openam.example.com:8080/openam/password</literal>.</para>
    <para>If the password reset service is enabled only for the user's realm
    and not the parent realm, or the realm to reset the password is different
    from the user's default realm, use <literal>ui/PWResetUserValidation?realm=<replaceable>realm
    name</replaceable>, as in</literal>
    <literal>http://openam.example.com:8080/openam/ui/PWResetUserValidation?realm=<replaceable>realm
    name</replaceable></literal>.</para>
    <mediaobject xml:id="figure-console-user-validation">
     <alt>The OpenAM user validation page</alt>
     <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="images/console-user-validation.png" format="PNG" />
     </imageobject>
     <textobject><para>OpenAM validates that the user exists, has an active
     account, and has set answers to her secret questions.</para></textobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>The user answers the specified questions, and clicks OK.</para>
    <para>OpenAM resets the password, sending mail to the SMTP service
    you configured.</para>
    <mediaobject xml:id="figure-console-answer-questions">
     <alt>The OpenAM user validation page</alt>
     <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="images/console-answer-questions.png" format="PNG" />
     </imageobject>
     <textobject><para>OpenAM prompts with secret questions.</para></textobject>
    </mediaobject>
    <mediaobject xml:id="figure-console-reset-confirmation">
     <alt>The page confirming password reset</alt>
     <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="images/console-reset-confirmation.png" format="PNG" />
     </imageobject>
     <textobject><para>OpenAM confirms password reset.</para></textobject>
    </mediaobject>
    <para>The user receives the email with a line such as the following.</para>
    <literallayout class="monospaced">Your OpenAM password was changed to:  647bWluw</literallayout>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>The user logs in using the new password.</para>
    <para>If you configured the system to force a change on password reset,
    then OpenAM requires the user to change her password.</para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </section>
</chapter>
