<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ! CCPL HEADER START
  !
  ! This work is licensed under the Creative Commons
  ! Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 3.0 Unported License.
  ! To view a copy of this license, visit
  ! http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/
  ! or send a letter to Creative Commons, 444 Castro Street,
  ! Suite 900, Mountain View, California, 94041, USA.
  !
  ! You can also obtain a copy of the license at
  ! src/main/resources/legal-notices/CC-BY-NC-ND.txt.
  ! See the License for the specific language governing permissions
  ! and limitations under the License.
  !
  ! If applicable, add the following below this CCPL HEADER, with the fields
  ! enclosed by brackets "[]" replaced with your own identifying information:
  !      Portions Copyright [yyyy] [name of copyright owner]
  !
  ! CCPL HEADER END
  !
  !      Copyright 2012-2013 ForgeRock AS
  !    
-->
<chapter xml:id='chap-oauth2'
 xmlns='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook'
 version='5.0' xml:lang='en'
 xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'
 xsi:schemaLocation='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd'
 xmlns:xlink='http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink'
 xmlns:xinclude='http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude'>
 <title>Managing OAuth 2.0 Authorization</title>
 <indexterm>
  <primary>Authorization</primary>
  <secondary>Configuring</secondary>
 </indexterm>
 <indexterm>
  <primary>OAuth 2.0</primary>
 </indexterm>

 <para>This chapter covers OpenAM support for the OAuth 2.0 authorization
 framework. The chapter begins by showing where OpenAM fits into the OAuth 2.0
 authorization framework, and then shows how to configure the
 functionality.</para>
 
 <section xml:id="about-oauth2-support">
  <title>About OAuth 2.0 Support in OpenAM</title>

  <para>RFC 6749, <link xlink:href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc6749"
  xlink:show="new"><citetitle>The OAuth 2.0 Authorization Framework</citetitle></link>,
  provides a standard way for <firstterm>resource owners</firstterm> to grant
  <firstterm>client</firstterm> applications access to the owners' web-based
  resources. The canonical example involves a user (resource owner) granting
  access to a printing service (client) to print photos that the user has
  stored on a photo-sharing server.</para>

  <para>The section describes how OpenAM supports the OAuth 2.0 authorization
  framework in terms of the roles that OpenAM plays.<footnote><para>Read
  <link xlink:show="new" xlink:href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc6749"
  >RFC 6749</link> to understand the authorization framework itself.</para>
  </footnote> The following sequence diagram indicates the primary roles
  OpenAM can play in the OAuth 2.0 protocol flow.</para>

  <mediaobject xml:id="figure-oauth2-flow">
   <alt>OpenAM in OAuth 2.0 protocol flow</alt>
   <imageobject>
    <imagedata fileref="images/oauth2-flow.png" format="PNG"/>
   </imageobject>
   <textobject><para>OpenAM can function as the authorization server and also
   as the client.</para></textobject>
  </mediaobject>

  <section xml:id="openam-oauth2-authz-server">
   <title>OpenAM as OAuth 2.0 Authorization Server</title>

   <para>OpenAM can function as an OAuth 2.0 <firstterm>authorization
   server</firstterm>. In this role, OpenAM authenticates resource owners and
   obtains their authorization in order to return access tokens to
   clients.</para>

   <para>When using OpenAM as authorization server, you register clients with
   OpenAM by using OAuth 2.0 policy agent profiles. OpenAM supports both
   confidential and public clients.</para>

   <para>OpenAM supports the four main grants for obtaining authorization
   described in RFC 6749: the authorization code grant, the implicit grant,
   the resource owner password credentials grant, and the client credentials
   grant. See RFC 6749 for details on the authorization grant process, and
   for details on how clients should make authorization requests and handle
   authorization responses. OpenAM also supports the <link xlink:show="new"
   xlink:href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-ietf-oauth-saml2-bearer"
   ><citetitle>SAML 2.0 Bearer Assertion Profiles for OAuth 2.0</citetitle></link>,
   described in the Internet-Draft.</para>

   <section xml:id="oauth2-authz">
    <title>OAuth 2.0 Authorization Grant</title>
    <para>The authorization code grant starts with the client, such as a
    web-based service, redirecting the resource owner's user-agent to the OpenAM
    authorization service. After authenticating the resource owner and
    obtaining the resource owner's authorization, OpenAM redirects the resource
    owner's user-agent back to the client with an authorization code that the
    client uses to request the access token. The following sequence diagram
    outlines a successful process from initial client redirection through to the
    client accessing the protected resource.</para>

    <mediaobject xml:id="figure-oauth2-authz">
     <alt>OpenAM in OAuth 2.0 Authorization Code Grant process</alt>
     <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="images/oauth2-authz.png" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <textobject><para>OpenAM supports the authorization code
     grant.</para></textobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </section>

   <section xml:id="oauth2-implicit">
    <title>OAuth 2.0 Implicit Grant</title>
    <para>The implicit grant is designed for clients implemented to run inside
    the resource-owner user agent. Instead of providing an authorization code
    that the client must use to retrieve an access token, OpenAM returns the
    access token directly in the fragment portion of the redirect URI. The
    following sequence diagram outlines the successful process.</para>

    <mediaobject xml:id="figure-oauth2-implicit">
     <alt>OpenAM in OAuth 2.0 Implicit Grant process</alt>
     <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="images/oauth2-implicit.png" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <textobject><para>OpenAM supports the implicit grant.</para></textobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </section>

   <section xml:id="oauth2-ropc">
    <title>OAuth 2.0 Resource Owner Password Credentials Grant</title>
    <para>The resource owner password credentials grant lets the client use the
    resource owner's user name and password to get an access token directly.
    Although this grant might seem to conflict with an original OAuth goal of
    not having to share resource owner credentials with the client, it can
    makes sense in a secure context where other authorization grant types are
    not available, such as a client that is part of a device operating system
    using the resource owner credentials once and thereafter using refresh tokens
    to continue accessing resources. The following sequence diagram shows the
    successful process.</para>

    <mediaobject xml:id="figure-oauth2-ropc">
     <alt>OpenAM in OAuth 2.0 Resource Owner Password Credentials Grant process</alt>
     <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="images/oauth2-ropc.png" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <textobject><para>OpenAM supports the resource owner password credentials
     grant.</para></textobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </section>

   <section xml:id="oauth2-client-cred">
    <title>OAuth 2.0 Client Credentials Grant</title>
    <para>The client credentials grant uses client credentials as an
    authorization grant. This grant makes sense when the client is also the
    resource owner, for example. The following sequence diagram shows the
    successful process.</para>

    <mediaobject xml:id="figure-oauth2-client-cred">
     <alt>OpenAM in OAuth 2.0 Client Credentials Grant process</alt>
     <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="images/oauth2-client-cred.png" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <textobject><para>OpenAM supports the client credentials
     grant.</para></textobject>
    </mediaobject>
   </section>

   <section xml:id="oauth2-saml2-bearer">
    <title>SAML 2.0 Bearer Assertion Profiles</title>
    <indexterm>
     <primary>Federation</primary>
     <secondary>OAuth 2.0</secondary>
    </indexterm>

    <para>The Internet-Draft, <link xlink:show="new"
    xlink:href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-ietf-oauth-saml2-bearer"
    ><citetitle>SAML 2.0 Bearer Assertion Profiles for OAuth 2.0</citetitle></link>,
    describes a means to use SAML 2.0 assertions to request access tokens and
    to authenticate OAuth 2.0 clients.</para>

    <para>At present OpenAM implements the profile to request access
    tokens.</para><!-- Pending AME-710 -->

    <para>In both profiles, the issuer must sign the assertion. The client
    communicates the assertion over a channel protected with transport
    layer security, by performing an HTTP POST to the OpenAM's access token
    endpoint. OpenAM as OAuth 2.0 authorization server uses the issuer ID to
    validate the signature on the assertion.</para>

    <para>In the profile to request an access token, the OAuth 2.0 client
    bears a SAML 2.0 assertion that was issued to the resource owner on
    successful authentication. A valid assertion in this case is equivalent
    to an authorization grant by the resource owner to the client. OAuth 2.0
    clients must make it clear to the resource owner that by authenticating to
    the identity provider who issues the assertion, they are granting the client
    permission to access the protected resources.</para>

    <mediaobject xml:id="figure-oauth2-saml2-bearer">
     <alt>SAML 2.0 Bearer Assertion Authorization Grant</alt>
     <imageobject>
      <imagedata fileref="images/oauth2-saml2-bearer.png" format="PNG"/>
     </imageobject>
     <textobject><para>OpenAM supports SAML 2.0 Bearer Assertion Profiles, for
     example to use an assertion to request an access token.</para></textobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <para>The HTTP POST to OpenAM to request an access token looks something
    like this:</para>

    <programlisting language="http">POST /openam/oauth2/access_token HTTP/1.1
    Host: openam.example.com
    Content-Type: application/x-www-form-urlencoded

    grant_type=urn%3Aietf%3Aparams%3Aoauth%3Agrant-type%3Asaml2-bearer&amp;
    assertion=PHNhbWxwOl...[base64url encoded assertion]...ZT4&amp;
    client_id=[ID registered with OpenAM]</programlisting>

    <!-- Pending AME-710
    <para>In the profile to authenticate the client, the SAML 2.0 assertion
    replaces the client password.</para>

    <para>The HTTP POST to OpenAM to authenticate the client looks something
    like this during an access token request given an authorization code:</para>

    <programlisting language="http">POST /openam/oauth2/access_token HTTP/1.1
    Host: openam.example.com
    Content-Type: application/x-www-form-urlencoded

    grant_type=authorization_code&amp;
    code=[encoded authorization code]&amp;
    client_assertion_type=urn%3Aietf%3Aparams%3Aoauth
     %3Aclient-assertion-type%3Asaml2-bearer&amp;
    client_assertion=PHNhbWxwOl...[base64url encoded assertion]...ZT4&amp;
    client_id=[ID registered with OpenAM]</programlisting>
    -->

    <para>If OpenAM is already a SAML 2.0 service provider, you can configure
    OpenAM as OAuth 2.0 authorization server as well, and set an adapter class
    name in the service provider configuration that lets OpenAM POST the
    assertion from the service provider to the authorization server. See
    <xref linkend="oauth2-sp-and-authz" /> for details.</para>
   </section>

   <section xml:id="oauth2-endpoints">
    <title>OpenAM OAuth 2.0 Endpoints</title>
    <xinclude:include href="../shared/variablelist-oauth2-endpoints.xml" />

    <para>For examples, see the <citetitle>Developer's Guide</citetitle> section,
    <link xlink:href="dev-guide#rest-api-oauth2"
    xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"><citetitle>OAuth 2.0
    Authorization</citetitle></link>.</para>
   </section>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="openam-oauth2-client">
   <title>OpenAM as OAuth 2.0 Client &amp; Resource Server Solution</title>

   <para>OpenAM can function as an OAuth 2.0 client for installations where the
   web resources are protected by OpenAM. To configure OpenAM as an OAuth 2.0
   client, you set up an OpenAM OAuth 2.0 authentication module instance, and
   then integrate the authentication module into your authentication chains as
   necessary.</para>

   <para>When OpenAM functions as an OAuth 2.0 client, OpenAM provides an
   OpenAM SSO session after successfully authenticating the resource owner and
   obtaining authorization. This means the client can then access resources
   protected by policy agents. In this respect the OpenAM OAuth 2.0 client is
   just like any other authentication module, one that relies on an OAuth 2.0
   authorization server to authenticate the resource owner and obtain
   authorization. The following sequence diagram shows how the client gains
   access to protected resources in the scenario where OpenAM functions as both
   authorization server and client for example.</para>

   <mediaobject xml:id="figure-oauth2-openam-client">
    <alt>OpenAM as OAuth 2.0 client and authorization server</alt>
    <imageobject>
     <imagedata fileref="images/oauth2-openam-client.png" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <textobject><para>OpenAM as client works as an authentication module where
    authentication and authorization is handled by the authorization server,
    and on success an SSO session is created, so that OpenAM access management
    can happen as it normally does.</para></textobject>
   </mediaobject>

   <para>As the OAuth 2.0 client functionality is implemented as an OpenAM
   authentication module, you do not need to deploy your own resource server
   implementation when using OpenAM as an OAuth 2.0 client. Instead, use policy
   agents or OpenIG to protect resources.</para>

   <para>To configure OpenAM as an OAuth 2.0 client, see <link
   xlink:href="admin-guide#oauth2-module-conf-hints"
   xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"><citetitle>Hints For the
   OAuth 2.0 Authentication Module</citetitle></link>.</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="oauth2-byo-client">
   <title>Using Your Own Client &amp; Resource Server</title>

   <para>OpenAM returns bearer tokens as described in RFC 6750, <link
   xlink:show="new" xlink:href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc6750"
   ><citetitle>The OAuth 2.0 Authorization Framework: Bearer Token
   Usage</citetitle></link>. Notice in the following example JSON response to
   an access token request that OpenAM returns a refresh token with the access
   token. The client can use the refresh token to get a new access token as
   described in RFC 6749.</para>

   <programlisting language="javascript">{
    "expires_in": 599,
    "token_type": "Bearer",
    "refresh_token": "f6dcf133-f00b-4943-a8d4-ee939fc1bf29",
    "access_token": "f9063e26-3a29-41ec-86de-1d0d68aa85e9"
}</programlisting>

   <para>In addition to implementing your client, the resource server must also
   implement the logic for handling access tokens. The resource server can use
   the <literal>/oauth2/tokeninfo</literal> endpoint to determine whether the
   access token is still valid, and to retrieve the scopes associated with the
   access token.</para>

   <para>The default OpenAM implementation of OAuth 2.0 scopes assumes that the
   space-separated (%20 when URL encoded) list of scopes in an access token
   request correspond to names of attributes in the resource owner's
   profile.</para>

   <para>To take a concrete example, consider an access token request where
   <literal>scope=mail%20cn</literal> and where the resource owner is the
   default OpenAM demo user. (The demo user has no email address by default, but
   you can add one, such as <literal>demo@example.com</literal> to the demo
   user's profile.) When the resource server performs an HTTP GET on the token
   information endpoint, <literal>/oauth2/tokeninfo?access_token=<replaceable
   >token-id</replaceable></literal>, OpenAM populates the
   <literal>mail</literal> and <literal>cn</literal> scopes with the email
   address (<literal>demo@example.com</literal>) and common name
   (<literal>demo</literal>) from the demo user's profile. The result is a
   something like the following token information response.</para>

   <programlisting language="javascript">{
    "mail": "demo@example.com",
    "scope": [
        "mail",
        "cn"
    ],
    "cn": "demo",
    "realm": "/",
    "token_type": "Bearer",
    "expires_in": 577,
    "access_token": "f9063e26-3a29-41ec-86de-1d0d68aa85e9"
}</programlisting>

   <para>OpenAM is designed to allow you to plug in your own scopes
   implementation if the default implementation does not do what your
   deployment requires. See <link xlink:href="dev-guide#chap-oauth2-scopes"
   xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"><citetitle>Customizing
   OAuth 2.0 Scope Handling</citetitle></link> for an example.</para>
  </section>
 </section>

 <section xml:id="configure-oauth2-authz">
  <title>Configuring the OAuth 2.0 Authorization Service</title>

  <para>You configure the OAuth 2.0 authorization service for a particular
  realm, starting from the Common Tasks page of the OpenAM console. This
  process also protects the authorization endpoint using a standard
  policy.</para>

  <procedure xml:id="common-task-oauth2-authz">
   <title>To Set Up the OAuth 2.0 Authorization Service</title>

   <para>Follow these steps.</para>

   <step>
    <para>In the OpenAM console, select Common Tasks &gt; Configure
    OAuth2.</para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>On the Configure OAuth2 page, enter the Realm for the authorization
    service.</para>
   </step>
   <step performance="optional">
    <para>If necessary, adjust the lifetimes for authorization codes
    (10 minutes is the recommended setting in RFC 6749), access tokens, and
    refresh tokens.</para>
   </step>
   <step performance="optional">
    <para>Select Issue Refresh Tokens unless you do not want the authorization
    service to supply a refresh token when returning an access token.</para>
   </step>
   <step performance="optional">
    <para>If you want to use the default scope implementation, whereby
    scopes are taken to be resource owner profile attribute names, then
    keep the default setting.</para>
    <para>If you have a custom scope implementation, put it on the OpenAM
    classpath, and provide the class name as Scope Implementation Class.</para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>Click Create to complete the process.</para>

    <para>In addition to setting up an OAuth 2.0 authorization server for the
    realm, OpenAM sets up a policy to protect the authorization endpoint.
    The policy appears in the list of policies for the realm. Its name is
    <literal>OAuth2ProviderPolicy</literal>.</para>
   </step>

   <step performance="optional">
    <para>If your provider has plugins for custom response types, add the
    custom response types and the corresponding plugin class names to the
    list of Response Type Plugins.</para>
   </step>

   <step performance="optional">
    <para>If resource owners log in with a user name that is not their user ID,
    but instead their mail address or some other profile attribute, then add the
    profile attribute name to the list that can be used for authentication.</para>

    <para>To make the change, browse to Access Control &gt; <replaceable>Realm
    Name</replaceable> &gt; Services &gt; OAuth2 Provider, add the profile
    attributes to the list titled User Profile Attribute(s) the Resource Owner
    is Authenticated On.</para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>Set a multi-valued profile attribute where OpenAM can store a resource
    owner's decisions to authorize clients without further interaction in the
    Shared Consent Attribute Name field.</para>

    <para>If no profile attribute is available for this purpose, you can add
    an attribute as described in <link xlink:href="dev-guide#chap-custom-attr"
    xlink:show="new" xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"><citetitle
    >Customizing Profile Attributes</citetitle></link> in the <citetitle
    >Developer's Guide</citetitle>.</para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>Save your changes.</para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <para>You can further adjust the authorization server configuration after you
  create it in the OpenAM console under Access Control &gt; <replaceable>Realm
  Name</replaceable> &gt; Services &gt; OAuth2 Provider.</para>

  <para>You can adjust global defaults in the OpenAM console under Configuration
  &gt; Global &gt; OAuth2 Provider.</para>
 </section>

 <section xml:id="register-oauth2-client">
  <title>Registering OAuth 2.0 Clients With the Authorization Service</title>

  <para>You register an OAuth 2.0 client with the OpenAM OAuth 2.0 authorization
  service by creating and configuring an OAuth 2.0 Client agent profile.</para>

  <para>At minimum you must have the client identifier and client password
  in order to register your OAuth 2.0 client.</para>

  <procedure xml:id="create-oauth2-client-profile">
   <title>To Create an OAuth 2.0 Client Agent Profile</title>

   <step>
    <para>Use either of these two facilities.</para>
    <stepalternatives>
     <step>
      <para>In the OpenAM console, access the client registration endpoint
      at <literal>/oauth2/registerClient.jsp</literal>.</para>
      <para>The full URL depends on where you deployed OpenAM. For example,
      <literal>https://openam.example.com:8443/openam/oauth2/registerClient.jsp</literal>.</para>
      <para>The Register a Client page lets you quickly create and configure
      an OAuth 2.0 client in a simple web page without inline help.</para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>In the OpenAM console under Access Control &gt; <replaceable>Realm
      Name</replaceable> &gt; Agents &gt; OAuth 2.0 Client &gt; Agent, click
      New..., then provide the client identifier and client password, and
      finally click Create to create the profile.</para>
      <para>This page requires that you perform additional configuration
      separately.</para>
     </step>
    </stepalternatives>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <procedure xml:id="configure-oauth2-client-profile">
   <title>To Configure an OAuth 2.0 Client Agent Profile</title>

   <para>After initially registering or creating a client agent profile as
   necessary.</para>

   <step>
    <para>In the OpenAM console, browse to Access Control &gt;
    <replaceable>Realm Name</replaceable> &gt; Agents &gt; OAuth 2.0 Client
    &gt; Agent &gt; <replaceable>Client Name</replaceable> to open the Edit
    <replaceable>Client Name</replaceable> page.</para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>Adjust the configuration as needed using the inline help for hints,
    and also the documentation section <link xlink:show="new"
    xlink:href="admin-guide#configure-oauth2-client"
    xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"><citetitle>Configuring
    OAuth 2.0 &amp; OpenID Connect 1.0 Clients</citetitle></link>.</para>

    <para>An important decision to make at this point is whether your client
    is a confidential client or a public client. This depends on whether your
    client can keep its credentials confidential, or whether its credentials
    can be exposed to the resource owner or other parties. If your client is a
    web-based application running on a server, such as the OpenAM OAuth 2.0
    client, then you can keep its credentials confidential. If your client is
    a user-agent based client, such as a JavaScript client running in a browser,
    or a native application installed on a device used by the resource owner,
    then yours is a public client.</para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>When finished, Save your work.</para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </section>

 <section xml:id="oauth2-manage-tokens">
  <title>Managing OAuth 2.0 Tokens</title>

  <para>OpenAM exposes a RESTful API that lets administrators read, list, and
  delete OAuth 2.0 tokens. OAuth 2.0 clients can also manage their own tokens.
  See the <citetitle>Developer's Guide</citetitle> section on the <link
  xlink:href="dev-guide#rest-api-oauth2-token-admin-endpoint"
  xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"><citetitle>OAuth 2.0 Token
  Administration Endpoint</citetitle></link> for details.</para>

  <para>OpenAM also lets resource owners browse and delete OAuth 2.0 tokens
  that they authorized. Resource owners can do this from the OAuth 2 Token
  Manager page. The OAuth 2 Token Manager page is not visible by default,
  however, as the page is designed for advanced users.</para>

  <para>To make the OAuth 2 Token Manager page visible to users, edit
  <filename>XUI/config/AppConfiguration.js</filename> under the deployment
  directory for OpenAM, changing the following lines to uncomment the
  <literal>"oauth2"</literal> configuration. Changes these lines:</para>

  <programlisting language="none">}/*,
"oauth2": {
  "url": "#oauth2/tokens",
  "name": "config.AppConfiguration.Navigation.links.oauthtokens"
}*/</programlisting>

  <para>The resulting lines should appear as follows.</para>

  <programlisting language="none">},
"oauth2": {
  "url": "#oauth2/tokens",
  "name": "config.AppConfiguration.Navigation.links.oauthtokens"
}</programlisting>

  <para>To access the page, login to OpenAM at <literal>/XUI</literal>, such as
  <literal>https://openam.example.com:8443/openam/XUI/</literal>, as the
  resource owner. Then click the OAuth 2 Token Manager link at the top of the
  page.</para>

  <para>For example, the following screen shows the demo user (user name:
  <literal>demo</literal>, password: <literal>changeit</literal>) browsing
  access tokens on OAuth 2 Token Manager page, after the OAuth 2.0 client with
  identifier <literal>myClientID</literal> has been granted tokens by using the
  Resource Owner Password Credentials Grant as shown in the
  <citetitle>Developer's Guide</citetitle>.</para>

  <mediaobject xml:id="figure-oauth2-tokens-gui">
   <alt>Managing OAuth 2.0 tokens as a resource owner</alt>
   <imageobject>
    <imagedata fileref="images/oauth2-tokens-gui.png" format="PNG" />
   </imageobject>
   <textobject><para>The resource owner can browse and delete tokens issued to
   clients.</para></textobject>
  </mediaobject>
 </section>

 <section xml:id="oauth2-client-plus-authz">
  <title>Configuring OpenAM as Authorization Server &amp; Client</title>

  <para>This section takes a high-level look at how to set up OpenAM both as an
  OAuth 2.0 authorization server and also as a client in order to protect
  resources by using a policy agent. The high-level steps are as follows.</para>

  <orderedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>Set up a policy agent or OpenIG to protect your web resources,
    including the policy used to protect the resources.</para>
    <para>Make sure you can access the resources using an authentication module
    that you already know before working with OAuth 2.0.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>Configure OpenAM's OAuth 2.0 authorization service as described
    in <xref linkend="configure-oauth2-authz" />.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>Configure an OpenAM OAuth 2.0 authentication module instance using
    the <link xlink:href="admin-guide#oauth2-module-conf-hints"
    xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"><citetitle>Hints For the
    OAuth 2.0 Authentication Module</citetitle></link> with the OpenAM
    authorization service endpoints.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>Register the OAuth 2.0 authentication module as an OAuth 2.0
    confidential client as described in <xref
    linkend="register-oauth2-client" />.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>Logout and access the protected resources to see the process in
    action.</para>
   </listitem>
  </orderedlist>

  <example xml:id="protect-web-site-with-oauth2"><?dbfo keep-together="auto"?>
   <title>Web Site Protected With OAuth 2.0</title>

   <para>This example pulls everything together (except security
   considerations), using OpenAM as an OAuth 2.0 authorization server,
   OAuth 2.0 client, and "resource server" by protecting web resources with
   a policy agent.</para>

   <para>This example uses two hosts, <literal>oauth2.example.com</literal>
   where OpenAM is deployed at
   <literal>http://oauth2.example.com:8080/openam</literal>, and
   <literal>www.example.com</literal> where the resources to protect are
   deployed in Apache Tomcat at
   <literal>http://www.example.com:8080/examples</literal>.</para>

   <orderedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>Set up an OpenAM policy agent and policy in the top-level realm,
     <literal>/</literal>, to protect resources. So far this is standard
     OpenAM, unrelated to OAuth 2.0.</para>

     <para>See the <link xlink:href="web-install-guide#web-install-guide"
     xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"><citetitle>OpenAM Web Policy
     Agent <?eval ${agentsDocTargetVersion}?> Installation Guide</citetitle></link>
     or <link xlink:href="jee-install-guide#jee-install-guide"
     xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"><citetitle>OpenAM Java EE Policy
     Agent <?eval ${agentsDocTargetVersion}?> Installation Guide</citetitle></link>
     for instructions on installing a policy agent. This example relies on the
     Apache Tomcat Java EE policy agent, configured to protect resources in
     Apache Tomcat at <literal>http://www.example.com:8080/</literal>.</para>

     <para>The policies for this example protect the Apache Tomcat examples
     under <literal>http://www.example.com:8080/examples/</literal>, allowing
     GET and POST operations by all authenticated users. For more information
     on creating policies, see <link xlink:show="new"
     xlink:href="admin-guide#configure-authz-policy"
     xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"><citetitle>Configuring
     Policies</citetitle></link>.</para>

     <para>After setting up the policy agent and the policy, you can make sure
     everything is working by attempting to access a protected resource, in this
     case <literal>http://www.example.com:8080/examples/</literal>. The policy
     agent should redirect you to OpenAM to authenticate with the default
     authentication module, where you can login as user <literal>demo</literal>
     password <literal>changeit</literal>. After successful authentication,
     OpenAM redirects your browser back to the protected resource and the
     policy agent lets you get the protected resource, in this case the Tomcat
     examples top page.</para>

     <mediaobject xml:id="figure-oauth2-examples">
      <alt>Successfully accessing the Apache Tomcat examples</alt>
      <imageobject>
       <imagedata fileref="images/oauth2-examples.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <textobject><para>If your policy agent and policy are set up correctly,
      you should get HTTP 200 and the Apache Tomcat examples page.</para></textobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
     <para>Configure OpenAM's OAuth 2.0 authorization service as described
     in <xref linkend="configure-oauth2-authz" />.</para>

     <para>The authorization endpoint to protect in this example is at
     <literal>http://oauth2.example.com:8080/openam/oauth2/authorize</literal>.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
     <para>Configure an OpenAM OAuth 2.0 authentication module instance for
     the top-level realm.</para>

     <para>Under Access Control &gt; / (Top-Level Realm) &gt; Authentication
     &gt; Module Instances, click New. Name the module
     <literal>OAuth2</literal>, and select the OAuth 2.0 type, then click
     OK to save your work.</para>

     <para>Then click Authentication &gt; Module Instances &gt; OAuth2 to open
     the OAuth 2.0 client configuration page. This page offers numerous options.
     The key settings for this example are the following.</para>
     <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
       <term>Client Id</term>
       <listitem>
        <para>This is the client identifier used to register your client with
        OpenAM's authorization server, and then used when your client must
        authenticate to OpenAM.</para>
        <para>Set this to <literal>myClientID</literal> for this example.</para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term>Client Secret</term>
       <listitem>
        <para>This is the client password used to register your client with
        OpenAM's authorization server, and then used when your client must
        authenticate to OpenAM.</para>
        <para>Set this to <literal>password</literal> for this example. Make
        sure you use strong passwords when you actually deploy OAuth 2.0.</para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term>Authentication Endpoint URL</term>
       <listitem>
        <para>In this example,
        <literal>http://oauth2.example.com:8080/openam/oauth2/authorize</literal>.</para>

        <para>This OpenAM endpoint can take additional parameters. In
        particular you must specify the realm if the OpenAM OAuth 2.0
        provider is configured for a subrealm rather than / (Top-Level
        Realm).</para>

        <para>For example, if the OAuth 2.0 provider is configured for the
        realm <literal>/customers</literal>, then use the following URL:
        <literal>https://openam.example.com:8443/openam/oauth2/authorize?realm=/customers</literal></para>

        <para>The <literal>/oauth2/authorize</literal> endpoint can also take
        <literal>module</literal> and <literal>service</literal> parameters. Use
        either as described in <link xlink:href="admin-guide#authn-from-browser"
        xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"><citetitle
        >Authenticating To OpenAM</citetitle></link>, where
        <literal>module</literal> specifies the authentication module instance
        to use or <literal>service</literal> specifies the authentication chain
        to use when authenticating the resource owner.</para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term>Access Token Endpoint URL</term>
       <listitem>
        <para>In this example,
        <literal>http://oauth2.example.com:8080/openam/oauth2/access_token</literal>.</para>

        <para>This OpenAM endpoint can take additional parameters. In
        particular you must specify the realm if the OpenAM OAuth 2.0
        provider is configured for a subrealm rather than / (Top-Level
        Realm).</para>

        <para>For example, if the OAuth 2.0 provider is configured for the
        realm <literal>/customers</literal>, then use the following URL:
        <literal>https://openam.example.com:8443/openam/oauth2/access_token?realm=/customers</literal></para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term>User Profile Service URL</term>
       <listitem>
        <para>In this example,
        <literal>http://oauth2.example.com:8080/openam/oauth2/tokeninfo</literal>.</para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term>Scope</term>
       <listitem>
        <para>In this example, <literal>cn</literal>.</para>
        <para>The demo user has common name <literal>demo</literal> by default,
        so by setting this to <literal>cn</literal> (Common Name), OpenAM
        can get the value of the attribute without the need to create
        additional subjects, or to update existing subjects.</para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term>Proxy URL</term>
       <listitem>
        <para>The client redirect URL, which in this example is
        <literal>http://oauth2.example.com:8080/openam/oauth2c/OAuthProxy.jsp</literal>.</para>
       </listitem></varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term>Attribute Mapper</term>
       <listitem>
        <para>In this example, 
        <literal>org.forgerock.openam.authentication.modules.oauth2.DefaultAccountMapper</literal>.</para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term>Account Mapper Configuration</term>
       <listitem>
        <para>In this example, <literal>cn=cn</literal>.</para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term>Create account if it does not exist</term>
       <listitem>
        <para>In this example, disable this functionality.</para>
        <para>OpenAM can create local accounts based on the account information
        returned by the authorization server. For this example, map all users
        to the anonymous account to keep it simple.</para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
       <term>Map to anonymous user</term>
       <listitem>
        <para>In this example, enable this functionality.</para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
     </variablelist>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
     <para>Register the OAuth 2.0 authentication module as an OAuth 2.0
     confidential client as described in <xref
     linkend="register-oauth2-client" />.</para>

     <para>Under Access Control &gt; / (Top-Level Realm) &gt; Agents &gt;
     OAuth 2.0 Client &gt; Agents &gt; <literal>myClientID</literal>, adjust
     the following settings.</para>

     <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
       <term>Client type</term>
       <listitem>
        <para>In this example, <literal>confidential</literal>. OpenAM protects
        its credentials as an OAuth 2.0 client.</para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
       <term>Redirection URIs</term>
       <listitem>
        <para>In this example,
        <literal>http://oauth2.example.com:8080/openam/oauth2c/OAuthProxy.jsp</literal>.</para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
       <term>Scopes</term>
       <listitem>
        <para>In this example, <literal>cn</literal>.</para>
       </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
     </variablelist>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
     <para>Before you try it out, you must make the following additional
     change to the configuration.</para>

     <para>Your OpenAM OAuth 2.0 client authentication module is not part
     of the default chain, and therefore OpenAM does not call it unless
     you specifically request the OAuth 2.0 client authentication
     module.</para>

     <para>To cause the policy agent to request your OAuth 2.0 client
     authentication module explicitly, browse in OpenAM console to your
     <emphasis>policy agent profile configuration</emphasis>, in this case
     Access Control &gt; / (Top-Level Realm) &gt; Agents &gt; J2EE &gt;
     Agents &gt; <literal>Tomcat</literal> &gt; OpenAM Services &gt; OpenAM
     Login URL, and add
     <literal>http://oauth2.example.com:8080/openam/UI/Login?module=OAuth2</literal>,
     moving it to the top of the list.</para>

     <para>Save your work.</para>

     <para>This ensures that the policy agent directs the resource owner
     to OpenAM with the instruction to authenticate using the
     <literal>OAuth2</literal> authentication module.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
     <para>Try it out.</para>

     <para>First make sure you are logged out of OpenAM, for example by
     browsing to the logout URL, in this case
     <literal>http://oauth2.example.com:8080/openam/UI/Logout</literal>.</para>

     <para>Next attempt to access the protected resource, in this case
     <literal>http://www.example.com:8080/examples/</literal>.</para>

     <para>If everything is set up properly, the policy agent redirects your
     browser to the login page of OpenAM with <literal>module=OAuth2</literal>
     among other query string parameters. After you authenticate, for example
     as user <literal>demo</literal>, password <literal>changeit</literal>,
     OpenAM presents you with an authorization decision page.</para>

     <mediaobject xml:id="figure-oauth2-authz-page">
      <alt>OpenAM presenting authorization decision page to resource owner</alt>
      <imageobject>
       <imagedata fileref="images/oauth2-authz-page.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <textobject><para>Upon successful authentication, the resource owner must
      make a decision to authorize the client to access the protected
      resource.</para></textobject>
     </mediaobject>

     <para>When you click Allow, the authorization service creates an SSO
     session, and redirects the client back to the resource, thus allowing
     the client to access the protected resource. If you configured an attribute
     on which to store the saved consent decision, and you choose to save the
     consent decision for this authorization, then OpenAM can use that saved
     decision to avoid prompting you for authorization next time the client
     accesses the resource, but only ensure that you have authenticated and
     have a valid session.</para>

     <mediaobject xml:id="figure-oauth2-examples-again">
      <alt>Successfully accessing the Apache Tomcat examples</alt>
      <imageobject>
       <imagedata fileref="images/oauth2-examples.png" format="PNG"/>
      </imageobject>
      <textobject><para>If everything is set up correctly, you should end up
      with HTTP 200 and the Apache Tomcat examples page.</para></textobject>
     </mediaobject>
    </listitem>
   </orderedlist>
  </example>
 </section>

 <section xml:id="oauth2-sp-and-authz">
  <title>Configuring OpenAM as Both SAML 2.0 Service Provider &amp; OAuth 2.0
  Authorization Server</title>

  <para>As described in <xref linkend="oauth2-saml2-bearer" />, OpenAM as
  OAuth 2.0 authorization server can handle the profile where a SAML 2.0
  assertion borne by the client functions as an authorization grant to get
  an access token. This lets a client get an access token when a resource owner
  completes SAML 2.0 Web Single Sign-On.</para>

  <para>You can configure OpenAM as both SAML 2.0 service provider and OAuth
  2.0 authorization server, using an built-in adapter class to POST assertions
  returned to the service provider to the access token endpoint of the
  authorization server. This allows clients to send a resource owner to the
  identity provider for SAML 2.0 web SSO, get an assertion at the service
  provider, and retrieve an access token from the authorization server. In other
  words, once this scenario is configured, the client must only direct the
  resource owner to start web SSO as described in <link
  xlink:href="admin-guide#using-saml2-sso-slo"
  xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"><citetitle>Using SAML 2.0
  Single Sign-On &amp; Single Logout</citetitle></link>, and then retrieve the
  access token on success or handle the error condition on failure.</para>

  <procedure xml:id="configure-oauth2-sp-and-authz">
   <title>To Get an Access Token From SAML 2.0 Web SSO</title>

   <itemizedlist>
    <para>For this scenario to work, the following conditions must be met.</para>

    <listitem>
     <para>The client must make the resource owner understand that by
     authenticating to the SAML 2.0 identity provider the resource owner grants
     the client access to the protected resources. OpenAM does not present the
     resource owner with an authorization decision.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
     <para>The SAML 2.0 identity provider issuing the assertion must sign the
     assertion, and must correctly handle the name ID for the subject.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
     <para>OpenAM as relying party must request that assertions are signed, must
     verify the signatures on assertions, must correctly handle name IDs
     from the issuer, and must use the built-in
     <literal>org.forgerock.restlet.ext.oauth2.flow.OAuth2Saml2GrantSPAdapter</literal>
     adapter class in the service provider configuration to POST assertions
     to the OAuth 2.0 authorization service.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
     <para>The OAuth 2.0 authorization service and SAML 2.0 service provider
     must be configured together on the same OpenAM server.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
     <para>An OAuth 2.0 client configuration on OpenAM with the same name as
     the service provider entity ID must be set up on OpenAM.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
     <para>The OAuth 2.0 client initiating the process must be able to consume
     the access token and to handle errors if necessary.</para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>

   <para>Follow these steps. The test configuration hints in this procedure let
   you prepare configuration to test with the demo user created in OpenAM by
   default.</para>

   <step>
    <para>Make sure the SAML 2.0 identity provider signs assertions and that
    name IDs are correctly configured to map resource owner accounts.</para>

    <para>When configuring OpenAM as a hosted identity provider follow these
    steps.</para>

    <substeps>
     <step>
      <para>Make sure the Signing Key is properly configured on setup.</para>

      <para>For a test configuration, select the <literal>test</literal>
      certificate shown in the Common Tasks &gt; Create Hosted Service Provider
      wizard.</para>
     </step>

     <step>
      <para>Make sure name IDs are properly configured.</para>

      <para>For a test configuration, in the OpenAM console under Federation
      &gt; Entity Providers &gt; <replaceable>IDP name</replaceable> &gt;
      NameID Value Map, add
      <literal>urn:oasis:names:tc:SAML:1.1:nameid-format:unspecified=cn</literal>
      and then Save your work.</para>
     </step>
    </substeps>

    <para>For more detail on configuring OpenAM as a SAML 2.0 identity provider,
    see <link xlink:href="admin-guide#configure-idp"
    xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"><citetitle>Configuring
    Identity Providers</citetitle></link>.</para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>Configure OpenAM as service provider.</para>

    <substeps>
     <step>
      <para>Set up a hosted service provider in OpenAM console under
      Common Tasks &gt; Create Hosted Service Provider, keeping track of
      the name, such as <literal>https://www.sp.example:8443/openam</literal>,
      and selecting Use default attribute mapping from Identity Provider.</para>

      <para>For details on configuring OpenAM as a SAML 2.0 service provider,
      see <link xlink:href="admin-guide#configure-sp"
      xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"><citetitle>Configuring
      Service Providers</citetitle></link>.</para>
     </step>

     <step>
      <para>Under Federation &gt; Entity Providers &gt; <replaceable>SP
      name</replaceable> &gt; Assertion Content &gt; Request/Response Signing,
      check Assertions Signed.</para>
     </step>

     <step>
      <para>For a test configuration, in Federation &gt; Entity Providers &gt;
      <replaceable>SP name</replaceable> &gt; Assertion Content &gt; NameID
      Format List, remove all but
      <literal>urn:oasis:names:tc:SAML:1.1:nameid-format:unspecified</literal>,
      and then Save your work.</para>
     </step>

     <step>
      <para>In Federation &gt; Entity Providers &gt; <replaceable>SP
      name</replaceable> &gt; Assertion Processing &gt; Adapter, add
      <literal>org.forgerock.restlet.ext.oauth2.flow.OAuth2Saml2GrantSPAdapter</literal>,
      and then Save your work.</para>

      <para>This is the adapter class that POSTs the SAML 2.0 assertion to
      the OAuth 2.0 access token endpoint.</para>
     </step>

     <step>
      <para>Use the wizard under Common Tasks &gt; Register Remote Identity
      Provider to import the identity provider metadata.</para>
     </step>
    </substeps>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>Make sure the identity provider imports the metadata for your
    service provider.</para>

    <para>If your service provider is at
    <literal>https://www.sp.example:8443/openam</literal>, then the metadata
    can be accessed at
    <literal>https://www.sp.example:8443/openam/saml2/jsp/exportmetadata.jsp</literal>.</para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>On the service provider OpenAM server, set up the OAuth 2.0
    authorization server as described in
    <xref linkend="configure-oauth2-authz" />.</para>

    <para>For a test configuration, set the realm to <literal>/</literal>, and
    accept the defaults.</para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>On the service provider and authorization server OpenAM server, set
    up an OAuth 2.0 client profile with the same name as the service
    provider under Access Control &gt; <replaceable>realm</replaceable> &gt;
    Agents &gt; OAuth 2.0 Client &gt; New...</para>

    <para>For example, if the service provider name is
    <literal>https://www.sp.example:8443/openam</literal>, then that is also
    the name of the OAuth 2.0 client profile.</para>

    <para>You can make additional changes to the client profile if necessary.
    See <xref linkend="register-oauth2-client" /> for details.</para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>Test your configuration.</para>

    <substeps>
     <step>
      <para>Logout of all OpenAM servers.</para>
     </step>

     <step>
      <para>Initiate SAML 2.0 Web SSO.</para>

      <para>For example, if your identity provider is at
      <literal>https://www.idp.example:8443/openam</literal> with meta alias
      <literal>/idp</literal> and your service provider is at
      <literal>https://www.sp.example:8443/openam</literal>, then browse to the
      following URL (without line breaks or spaces).</para>

      <programlisting language="none"
      >http://www.idp.example:8443/openam/saml2/jsp/idpSSOInit.jsp
 ?metaAlias=/idp&amp;spEntityID=http://www.sp.example:8443/openam</programlisting>

      <para>For other configurations, see <link
      xlink:href="admin-guide#using-saml2-sso-slo"
      xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"><citetitle>Using SAML 2.0
      Single Sign-On &amp; Single Logout</citetitle></link>.</para>
     </step>

     <step>
      <para>Login to the identity provider.</para>

      <para>For OpenAM, login with user name <literal>demo</literal> and
      password <literal>changeit</literal>.</para>
     </step>

     <step>
      <para>Login to the service provider.</para>

      <para>For OpenAM, login with user name <literal>demo</literal> and
      password <literal>changeit</literal>.</para>
     </step>

     <step>
      <para>See the resulting access token on successful login.</para>

      <para>The result looks something like this, all on one line.</para>
      <programlisting language="javascript">{
    "expires_in": 59,
    "token_type": "Bearer",
    "access_token": "f0f731e0-6013-47e3-9c07-da598157a85f"
}</programlisting>
     </step>
    </substeps>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </section>

 <section xml:id="oauth2-security-considerations">
  <title>Security Considerations</title>

  <para>OAuth 2.0 messages involve credentials and access tokens that allow
  the bearer to retrieve protected resources. Therefore, do not let an attacker
  capture requests or responses. Protect the messages going across the
  network.</para>

  <para>RFC 6749 includes a number of <link xlink:show="new"
  xlink:href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc6749#section-10">Security
  Considerations</link>, and also requires Transport Layer Security (TLS)
  to protect sensitive messages. Make sure you read the section covering
  <citetitle>Security Considerations</citetitle>, and that you can implement
  them in your deployment.</para>

  <para>Also, especially when deploying a mix of other clients and resource
  servers, take into account the points covered in the Internet-Draft, <link
  xlink:href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-ietf-oauth-v2-threatmodel"
  xlink:show="new"><citetitle>OAuth 2.0 Threat Model and Security
  Considerations</citetitle></link>, before putting your service into
  production.</para>
 </section>
</chapter>
