<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ! CCPL HEADER START
  !
  ! This work is licensed under the Creative Commons
  ! Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 3.0 Unported License.
  ! To view a copy of this license, visit
  ! http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/
  ! or send a letter to Creative Commons, 444 Castro Street,
  ! Suite 900, Mountain View, California, 94041, USA.
  !
  ! You can also obtain a copy of the license at
  ! src/main/resources/legal-notices/CC-BY-NC-ND.txt.
  ! See the License for the specific language governing permissions
  ! and limitations under the License.
  !
  ! If applicable, add the following below this CCPL HEADER, with the fields
  ! enclosed by brackets "[]" replaced with your own identifying information:
  !      Portions Copyright [yyyy] [name of copyright owner]
  !
  ! CCPL HEADER END
  !
  !      Copyright 2013 ForgeRock AS
  !    
-->
<chapter xml:id='chap-dashboard'
 xmlns='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook'
 version='5.0' xml:lang='en'
 xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'
 xsi:schemaLocation='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd'
 xmlns:xlink='http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink'
 xmlns:xinclude='http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude'>
 <title>Configuring the Dashboard Service</title>
 
 <indexterm>
  <primary>Dashboard service</primary>
 </indexterm>
 
 <para>This chapter shows how to configure the OpenAM <firstterm>Dashboard</firstterm>.</para>

 <section xml:id="about-the-dashboard">
  <title>About the Dashboard Service</title>
  
   <para>The Dashboard service provides the end user with an interface to access
   applications secured by OpenAM, both cloud-based applications like SalesForce
   and internal applications protected by policy agents. The Dashboard service uses SSO to 
   login to the applications when the user clicks on the application icon. For some apps, 
   like SalesForce, you will want to limit access to only a few users. Other apps, 
   like Google Mail or Drive, you will probably want to make available to all users.</para>
   
   <mediaobject xml:id="figure-user-dashboard">
    <alt>User Dashboard screen</alt>
    <imageobject>
     <imagedata fileref="images/user-dashboard.png" format="PNG" />
    </imageobject>
    <textobject><para>The user Dashboard lets users quickly access
    their applications.</para></textobject>
   </mediaobject>   
   
   <para>The Dashboard service is meant to give users a single place to access their
   applications. Keep in mind that this does not limit user access, only what appears
   on the user Dashboard.</para>
 
   <itemizedlist>
    <para>There are three stages to setting up the Dashboard service.</para>
    <listitem>
     <para>Setup the Dashboard service and add applications.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>Add the service to the realms.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>Assign users applications so that they appear on the users' Dashboards. 
     This can be done manually or through a provisioning solution.</para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   
 </section>
 
 <section xml:id="dashboard-setup">
  <title>Setting Up the Dashboard Service</title>

   <para>Making some applications universally available ensures that all users have the same
   basic applications. However, some of your applications should be protected from the
   majority of your users. You will need to single out which users will include the 
   application on their Dashboard.</para>
   
   <para>There are three default applications in the Dashboard service: Google, SalesForce,
   and ZenDesk.</para>
 
   <procedure xml:id="dashboard-add">
    <title>To Add Applications from the Dashboard</title>
  
    <para>You can add applications to the Dashboard service with the following steps.
    All fields except the Dashboard Class name and ICF Identifier are required for 
    the application to work properly from the Dashboard.</para>
  
    <step>
     <para>Login to the OpenAM console as OpenAM Administrator,
     <literal>amadmin</literal>.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>On the Configuration tab &gt; Global &gt; Dashboard click New
     to add a new application to the Dashboard service and to provide the information
     needed to connect to the app. </para>

    </step>
    <step>
     <para>Provide a unique name for the application.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>Add a Dashboard Class Name that identifies how the end user
     will access the app, such as <literal>SAML2ApplicationClass</literal>
     for a SAML 2.0 application.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>Add a Dashboard Name for the application.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>Add a Dashboard Display Name. This name is what the end user
     will see, such as Google.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>Add the Dashboard Icon you would like the end user to see for the application. 
     Either use a fully-qualified URL or an appropriate relative URL so that the
     icon is rendered properly on the user Dashboard.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>Add the Dashboard Login URL to point to the location the end user
     will go to once they click on the icon.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>Leave the ICF Identifier blank.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>Click Add when you are done.</para>
    </step>
 
   </procedure>

 </section>

 <section xml:id="dashboard-realms">
  <title>Configuring Dashboard Service for a Realm</title>
 
   <procedure xml:id="dashboard-single-realm">
    <title>To Add the Application Dashboard Service to a Realm</title>

    <para>You must add the Dashboard service to a realm before it will be available. 
    The following instructions show you how to add an application to a single realm.
    Before you begin, make sure you have the name of the application as it appears
    on the Secondary Configuration Instance table under Configuration &gt; Global 
    &gt; Dashboard.</para>
 
    <step>
     <para>On the Access Control &gt; <replaceable>Realm Name</replaceable>
     &gt; Services, click Add....</para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>Select the Dashboard service, then click Next.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>Add or remove the applications you would like to appear on the Dashboard
     service for the realm.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>Click Finish when you are done.</para>
    </step>
  
   </procedure>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="dashboard-users">
   <title>Adding Applications to a User's Dashboard</title>

   <procedure xml:id="assign-app-to-user">
    <title>To Add an Application to a User's Dashboard</title>
    <indexterm><primary>Dashboard service</primary></indexterm>
    
     <para>Use the following steps to add an application to a user's Dashboard.</para>
   
     <step>
      <para>On the Access Control &gt; <replaceable>Realm Name</replaceable>
      &gt; Subjects, click the user identifier to edit the user's profile.</para>
     </step>

     <step>
      <para>Under Services, click Dashboard.</para>
     </step>
  
     <step>
      <para>Add the application beside the user name under the user's Assigned
      Dashboard list.</para>
     </step>

     <step>
      <para>Click Save.</para>
     </step>
    </procedure>
    
    <procedure xml:id="dashboard-remove-user-access">
     <title>Removing User Access to an Application</title>
     <indexterm><primary>Dashboard service</primary></indexterm>
     
     <para>You may need to remove an application from user's Dashboard, but
     you don't want to entirely delete the user. The following steps walk you through
     removing an application from a user's Dashboard.</para>

     <step>
      <para>On the Access Control &gt; <replaceable>Realm Name</replaceable>
      &gt; Subjects, click the user identifier to edit the user's profile.</para>
     </step>

     <step>
      <para>Under Services, click Dashboard.</para>
     </step>
  
     <step>
      <para>Delete the application beside the user name under the user's Assigned
      Dashboard list.</para>
     </step>

     <step>
      <para>Click Save.</para>
     </step>
     
    </procedure>

  </section>
  
</chapter>