<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ! CCPL HEADER START
  !
  ! This work is licensed under the Creative Commons
  ! Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 3.0 Unported License.
  ! To view a copy of this license, visit
  ! http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/
  ! or send a letter to Creative Commons, 444 Castro Street,
  ! Suite 900, Mountain View, California, 94041, USA.
  !
  ! You can also obtain a copy of the license at
  ! src/main/resources/legal-notices/CC-BY-NC-ND.txt.
  ! See the License for the specific language governing permissions
  ! and limitations under the License.
  !
  ! If applicable, add the following below this CCPL HEADER, with the fields
  ! enclosed by brackets "[]" replaced with your own identifying information:
  !      Portions Copyright [yyyy] [name of copyright owner]
  !
  ! CCPL HEADER END
  !
  !      Copyright 2013 ForgeRock AS
  !    
-->
<chapter xml:id='chap-openid-connect'
 xmlns='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook'
 version='5.0' xml:lang='en'
 xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'
 xsi:schemaLocation='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd'
 xmlns:xlink='http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink'
 xmlns:xinclude='http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude'>
 <title>Managing OpenID Connect 1.0 Authorization</title>
 <indexterm>
  <primary>Authorization</primary>
  <secondary>Configuring</secondary>
 </indexterm>
 <indexterm>
  <primary>OpenID Connect 1.0</primary>
 </indexterm>

 <para>This chapter covers OpenAM support for OpenID Connect 1.0. <link
 xlink:href="http://openid.net/connect/" xlink:show="new">OpenID Connect</link>
 1.0 extends OAuth 2.0 so the client can verify claims about the identity of
 the end user, get profile information about the end user, and log the user out
 at the end of the OpenAM session. OpenID Connect also makes it possible to
 discover the provider for an end user, and to register client applications
 dynamically. OpenID connect services are built on OAuth 2.0, JSON Web Token
 (JWT), WebFinger and Well-Known URIs.</para>

 <section xml:id="about-openid-connect-support">
  <title>About OpenID Connect 1.0 Support in OpenAM</title>

  <para>In its role as OpenID Provider, OpenAM lets OpenID Connect clients
  discover its capabilities, handles both dynamic and static registration of
  OpenID Connect clients, responds to client requests with authorization codes,
  access tokens, and user information according to the Basic and Implicit Client
  Profiles of OpenID Connect, and manages sessions.</para>

  <para>This section describes how OpenAM fits into the OpenID Connect picture
  in terms of the roles that it plays in basic and implicit client profiles,
  provider discovery, client registration, and session management.</para>

  <section xml:id="openam-openid-basic-client-profile">
   <title>OpenID Connect Basic Client Profile</title>

   <para>The OpenID Connect Basic Client Profile specifies how the client
   application interacts with the provider, in this case OpenAM, based on use
   of the OAuth 2.0 authorization grant. The following sequence diagram shows
   successful processing from the authorization request, through grant of the
   authorization code, access token, and ID token, and optional use of the
   access token to get information about the end user.</para>

   <mediaobject xml:id="figure-openid-connect-basic">
    <alt>OpenAM in OpenID Connect Basic Client Profile</alt>
    <imageobject>
     <imagedata fileref="images/openid-connect-basic.png" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <textobject>
     <para>OpenAM supports the OpenID Connect Basic Client Profile.</para>
    </textobject>
   </mediaobject>

   <para>In addition to what OAuth 2.0 specifies, OpenID Connect uses an ID
   token so the client can validate claims about the end user. It also defines
   how to get user information such as profile, email, address, and phone
   details from the UserInfo endpoint with a valid access token.</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="openam-openid-implicit-client-profile">
   <title>OpenID Connect Implicit Client Profile</title>

   <para>The OpenID Connect Implicit Client Profile specifies how the client
   application interacts with the provider, in this case OpenAM, based on
   use of the OAuth 2.0 implicit grant. The following sequence diagram shows
   successful processing from the authorization request, through grant of the
   access and ID tokens, and optional use of the access token to get information
   about the end user.</para>

   <mediaobject xml:id="figure-openid-connect-implicit">
    <alt>OpenAM in OpenID Connect Implicit Client Profile</alt>
    <imageobject>
     <imagedata fileref="images/openid-connect-implicit.png" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <textobject>
     <para>OpenAM supports the OpenID Connect Implicit Client Profile.</para>
    </textobject>
   </mediaobject>

   <para>As for the Basic Client Profile, the Implicit Client Profile specifies
   an ID token so the client can validate claims about the end user. It also
   defines how to get user information such as profile, email, address, and
   phone details from the UserInfo endpoint with a valid access token.</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="openam-openid-discovery">
   <title>OpenID Connect Discovery</title>

   <para>OpenID Connect defines how a client application can discover the
   OpenID connect provider and corresponding OpenID Connect configuration for
   an end user. The discovery mechanism relies on WebFinger to get the
   information based on the end user's identifier. The server returns the
   information in JSON Resource Descriptor (JRD) format.</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="openam-openid-client-registration">
   <title>OpenID Connect Client Registration</title>

   <para>OpenID Connect clients can register with OpenAM as a provider both
   statically, as for other OAuth 2.0 clients, and also dynamically as specified
   by OpenID Connect. To allow dynamic registration, you register an initial
   client that other clients can use to get access tokens for registration.</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="openam-openid-session-management">
   <title>OpenID Connect Session Management</title>

   <para>OpenID Connect lets the client track whether the end user is logged in
   at the provider, and also initiate end user logout at the provider. The
   specification has the client application monitor session state using an
   invisible iframe and communicate status using the HTML 5 postMessage
   API.</para>
  </section>

 </section>

 <section xml:id="configure-openid-connect-provider">
  <title>Configuring OpenAM As an OpenID Connect Provider</title>

  <para>You can configure OpenAM's OAuth 2.0 authorization service to double
  as an OpenID Connect 1.0 Provider. To do so, make sure that the Response Type
  Plugins list includes at least the default plugin classes.</para>

  <para>See <link xlink:href="admin-guide#configure-oauth2-authz"
  xlink:show="new" xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"
  ><citetitle>Configuring the OAuth 2.0 Authorization Service</citetitle></link>
  for detailed instructions on configuring the service.</para>
 </section>

 <section xml:id="configure-openid-connect-discovery">
  <title>Configuring OpenAM For OpenID Connect Discovery</title>

  <para>In order to allow clients to discover the provider for an end user,
  OpenAM supports OpenID Connect Discovery 1.0. In addition to discovering
  the provider for an end user, the client can also request the OpenID
  Connect Provider configuration.</para>
  
  <para>OpenAM as OpenID Connect Provider exposes two endpoints for
  discovery:</para>

  <simplelist type="vert" columns="1">
   <member><literal>/.well-known/webfinger</literal></member>
   <member><literal>/.well-known/openid-configuration</literal></member>
  </simplelist>
  
  <para>A client needs to be able to discover the provider for an end user. In
  this case you should consider redirecting requests to URIs at the server root,
  such as <literal>http://www.example.com/.well-known/webfinger</literal>
  and <literal>http://www.example.com/.well-known/openid-configuration</literal>,
  to these Well-Known URIs in OpenAM's space.</para>

  <para>Discovery relies on <link xlink:show="new"
  xlink:href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/draft-ietf-appsawg-webfinger"
  >WebFinger</link>, a protocol to discover information about people and other
  entities using standard HTTP methods. WebFinger uses <link xlink:show="new"
  xlink:href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc5785">Well-Known URIs</link>,
  which defines the path prefix <literal>/.well-known/</literal> for the
  URLs defined by OpenID Connect Discovery.</para>
  
  <para>Unless you deploy OpenAM in the root context of a container listening
  on port 80 on the primary host for your domain, clients need to find
  the right <replaceable>host:port/deployment-uri</replaceable> combination
  to locate the well-known endpoints. Therefore you must manage the redirection
  to OpenAM. If you are using WebFinger for something else than OpenID Connect
  Discovery, then you probably also need proxy logic to route the requests.</para>

  <para>To retrieve the provider for an end user, the client needs the
  following.</para>

  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>host</literal></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>The server where the client can access the WebFinger service.</para>

     <para>Notice that this is a host name rather than a URL to the endpoint,
     which is why you might need to redirect clients appropriately as described
     above.</para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>

   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>resource</literal></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>Identifies the end user that is the subject of the request.</para>

     <para>The client must percent-encode the resource value when using it in
     the query string of the request, so when using the "acct" URI scheme and
     the resource is <literal>acct:user@example.com</literal>, then the value
     to use is <literal>acct%3Auser%40example.com</literal>.</para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>

   <varlistentry>
    <term><literal>rel</literal></term>
    <listitem>
     <para>URI identifying the type of service whose location is requested.</para>

     <para>In this case <literal>http://openid.net/specs/connect/1.0/issuer</literal>,
     which is <literal>http%3A%2F%2Fopenid.net%2Fspecs%2Fconnect%2F1.0%2Fissuer</literal>.</para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

  <para>Ignoring the question of redirection, you can test the endpoint for the
  demo user account (output lines folded to make them easier to read).</para>

  <screen>$ curl "https://openam.example.com:8443/openam/.well-known/webfinger
 ?resource=acct%3Ademo%40example.com
 &amp;rel=http%3A%2F%2Fopenid.net%2Fspecs%2Fconnect%2F1.0%2Fissuer"
{
  "subject": "acct:demo@example.com",
  "links": [
    {
      "rel": "http://openid.net/specs/connect/1.0/issuer",
      "href": "https://openam.example.com:8443/openam"
    }
  ]
}</screen>

  <para>This shows that the OpenID Connect Provider for the OpenAM demo user is
  indeed the OpenAM server.</para>

  <para>The client can also discover the provider configuration. Ignoring the
  question of redirection, you can test this (output lines folded to make them
  easier to read).</para>

  <informalexample><?dbfo pgwide="1"?>
  <screen>{
    "response_types_supported": [
        "id_token|org.forgerock.restlet.ext.oauth2.flow.responseTypes.IDTokenResponseType",
        "token|org.forgerock.restlet.ext.oauth2.flow.responseTypes.TokenResponseType",
        "code|org.forgerock.restlet.ext.oauth2.flow.responseTypes.CodeResponseType"
    ],
    "registration_endpoint": "https://openam.example.com:8443/openam/oauth2/connect/register",
    "token_endpoint": "https://openam.example.com:8443/openam/oauth2/access_token",
    "end_session_endpoint": "https://openam.example.com:8443/openam/oauth2/connect/endSession",
    "version": "3.0",
    "userinfo_endpoint": "https://openam.example.com:8443/openam/oauth2/userinfo",
    "subject_types_supported": [
        "pairwise",
        "public"
    ],
    "issuer": "https://openam.example.com:8443/openam",
    "jwks_uri": "",
    "id_token_siging_alg_values_supported": [
        "HmacSHA256",
        "HmacSHA512",
        "HmacSHA384"
    ],
    "check_session_iframe": "https://openam.example.com:8443/openam/oauth2/connect/checkSession",
    "claims_supported": [
        "phone",
        "email",
        "address",
        "openid",
        "profile"
    ],
    "authorization_endpoint": "https://openam.example.com:8443/openam/oauth2/authorize"
}</screen>
  </informalexample>
 </section>

 <section xml:id="register-openid-connect-clients">
  <title>Registering OpenID Connect Clients</title>

  <para>OpenID Connect Clients can register with OpenAM both statically through
  OpenAM console for example, and also dynamically using OpenID Connect 1.0
  Dynamic Registration.</para>

  <procedure xml:id="register-openid-connect-client-static">
   <title>To Register a Client With OpenAM Console</title>

   <para>Registering a client by using the OpenAM console consists of first
   creating an OAuth 2.0 Client agent profile, and then editing the profile
   to indicate the client settings pertinent to OpenID Connect 1.0.</para>

   <step>
    <para>In the OpenAM console under Access Control &gt; <replaceable>Realm
    Name</replaceable> &gt; Agents &gt; OAuth 2.0 Client &gt; Agent, click
    New..., then provide the client identifier and client password, and
    finally click Create to create the profile.</para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>Follow the hints in the section, <link xlink:show="new"
    xlink:href="admin-guide#configure-oauth2-client"
    xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"><citetitle>Configuring
    OAuth 2.0 &amp; OpenID Connect 1.0 Clients</citetitle></link> to edit
    the profile to match the client configuration.</para>

    <para>In order to read and edit the client configuration dynamically later
    without using OpenAM console, be sure to set an access token in the field
    titled, "The access token used to update the client."</para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <procedure xml:id="register-openid-connect-client-dynamic">
   <title>To Register a Client Dynamically</title>

   <para>For dynamic registration you need the client configuration metadata,
   and an access token to write the configuration to OpenAM by HTTP POST. To
   obtain the access token, register an initial client statically after creating
   the provider, as described in
   <xref linkend="register-openid-connect-client-static" />. Other clients can
   then use that client to obtain the access token needed to perform dynamic
   registration.</para>

   <para>On successful registration, OpenAM responds with information including
   an access token to allow the client subsequently to read and edit its
   profile.</para>

   <step>
    <para>Register an initial OAuth 2.0 client statically with a client ID
    such as <literal>masterClient</literal> and client secret such as
    <literal>password</literal>.</para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>Obtain an access token using the client you registered.</para>

    <para>For example, if you created the client as described in the previous
    step, and OpenAM administrator <literal>amadmin</literal> has password
    <literal>password</literal>, you can use the OAuth 2.0 resource owner
    password grant as in the following example.</para>

    <screen>$ curl
 --request POST
 --user "masterClient:password"
 --data "grant_type=password&amp;username=amadmin&amp;password=password"
 https://openam.example.com:8443/openam/oauth2/access_token
{
    "expires_in": 59,
    "token_type": "Bearer",
    "refresh_token": "26938cd0-6870-4e31-ade9-df31afc37ee1",
    "access_token": "515d6551-4512-4279-98b6-c0ef3f03a722"
}</screen>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>HTTP POST the client registration profile to the
    <literal>/oauth2/connect/register</literal> endpoint, using bearer token
    authorization with the access token you obtained from OpenAM.</para>

    <para>For an example written in JavaScript, see the registration page in
    the examples <link xlink:show="new"
    xlink:href="https://github.com/markcraig/openid/">available online</link>.
    Successful registration shows a response that includes the client ID and
    client secret.</para>

    <programlisting language="javascript">{
  "issued_at": 1376916775,
  "expires_at": 0,
  "client_secret": "5a1f50db-ed93-4a9b-bf37-c1cb3c74ca16",
  "com.forgerock.openam.oauth2provider.redirectionURIs": [
    "https://openam.example.com:8443/openid/cb-basic.html",
    "https://openam.example.com:8443/openid/cb-implicit.html"
  ],
  "client_id": "c1e5c60a-9fd4-4780-a283-ec89580b6cc1",
  "registration_client_uri":
    "https://openam.example.com:8443/openam/oauth2/connect/register
     ?client_id=c1e5c60a-9fd4-4780-a283-ec89580b6cc1"
}</programlisting>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </section>

 <section xml:id="manage-sessions-openid-connect">
  <title>Managing User Sessions</title>

  <para>OpenID Connect Session Management 1.0 allows the client to manage
  OpenID Connect sessions, making it possible to know when the end user should
  be logged out.</para>

  <para>As described in the <link
  xlink:href="http://openid.net/specs/openid-connect-session-1_0.html"
  xlink:show="new">OpenID Connect Session Management 1.0</link> specification,
  OpenAM's OpenID Connect provider exposes both a "check_session_iframe" URL
  that allows the client to receive notifications when the end user's session
  state changes at the provider, and also an "end_session_endpoint" URL to
  which to redirect an end user for logout.</para>

  <para>When registering your client that uses session management, you set the
  OAuth 2.0 client agent profile properties Post Logout Redirect URI and
  Client Session URI, described in <link xlink:show="new"
  xlink:href="admin-guide#configure-oauth2-client"
  xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"><citetitle>Configuring
  OAuth 2.0 &amp; OpenID Connect 1.0 Clients</citetitle></link>. The Post
  Logout Redirect URI is used to redirect the end user user-agent after logout.
  The Client Session URI is the client URI where OpenAM sends notifications
  when the end user's session state changes.</para>
 </section>

 <section xml:id="openid-connect-examples">
  <title>Client Examples</title>

  <para>OpenID Connect Basic and Implicit Client Profiles define how clients
  interact with the provider to obtain end user authorization and profile
  information. Although you can run the simple example clients mentioned in
  this section without setting up Transport Layer Security, do not deploy
  clients in production without securing the transport.</para>

  <para>Code for the client examples shown here is <link xlink:show="new"
  xlink:href="https://github.com/markcraig/openid/">available online</link>.
  Clone the example project to deploy it in the same web container as
  OpenAM. Edit the configuration at the outset of the .js files in the project,
  register a corresponding profile for the example client as described in
  <xref linkend="register-openid-connect-clients"/>, and browse the deployment
  URL to see the initial page.</para>

  <mediaobject xml:id="figure-openid-connect-example-start-page">
   <alt>OpenID Connect Client Profiles Start Page</alt>
   <imageobject>
    <imagedata fileref="images/openid-connect-example-start-page.png" format="PNG" />
   </imageobject>
   <textobject>
    <para>The OpenID Connect Client Profiles Start Page lets you choose whether
    to try the Basic Client Profile or the Implicit Client Profile.</para>
   </textobject>
  </mediaobject>

  <example xml:id="openid-basic-profile-example"><?dbfo keep-together="auto"?>
   <title>Basic Client Profile Example</title>

   <para>OpenID Connect Basic Client Profile 1.0 is designed for web-based
   relying parties that use the OAuth 2.0 Authorization Code grant type.
   This grant type makes it possible for the client to get the access code
   by using the authorization code directly, without passing through the end
   user's browser. To protect its client secret (password), part of the
   client must run on the server.</para>

   <para>In the example, the Basic Client Profile Start Page describes the
   prerequisite configuration, which must be part of the client profile stored
   in the OpenAM realm where you set up the OpenID Provider. In OpenAM console,
   check that the OAuth 2.0 agent profile matches the settings described.</para>

   <mediaobject xml:id="figure-openid-connect-basic-start-page">
    <alt>OpenID Connect Basic Client Profile Start Page</alt>
    <imageobject>
     <imagedata fileref="images/openid-connect-basic-start-page.png" format="PNG" />
    </imageobject>
    <textobject>
     <para>The Basic Client Profile start page describes the configuration
     required.</para>
    </textobject>
   </mediaobject>

   <para>Logout of OpenAM, and click the link at the bottom of the page to
   request authorization. The link sends an HTTP GET request asking for
   <literal>openid profile</literal> scopes to the OpenID Connect provider
   authorization URI.</para>

   <para>If everything is configured correctly, OpenAM's OpenID Connect provider
   has you authenticate as an end user, such as the demo user with username
   <literal>demo</literal> and password <literal>changeit</literal>, and
   grant (Allow) the client access to your profile.</para>

   <para>If you successfully authenticate and allow the example client access
   to your profile, OpenAM returns an authorization code to the example client.
   The example client then uses the authorization code to request an access
   token and an ID token. It shows the response to that request, and also
   decodes the ID token to show the content and to perform some validation.
   Finally it uses the access token to request information about the end user
   who authenticated, and displays the result.</para>

   <mediaobject xml:id="figure-openid-connect-basic-response-page">
    <alt>OpenID Connect Basic Client Profile Response Page</alt>
    <imageobject>
     <imagedata fileref="images/openid-connect-basic-response-page.png" format="PNG" />
    </imageobject>
    <textobject>
     <para>The Basic Client Profile response page shows responses from OpenAM's
     OpenID Connect provider.</para>
    </textobject>
   </mediaobject>

   <para>Notice that in addition to the standard payload, the ID token indicates
   the end user's OpenAM realm, in this case <literal>"realm": "/"</literal>.</para>
  </example>

  <example xml:id="openid-implicit-profile-example"><?dbfo keep-together="auto"?>
   <title>Implicit Client Profile Example</title>

   <para>OpenID Connect Implicit Client Profile 1.0 is designed for relying
   parties that use the OAuth 2.0 Implicit grant type. This grant type is
   designed for clients implemented in a browser. Rather than protect a
   client secret, the client profile must register a protected redirect URI
   in advance with the OpenID Provider.</para>

   <para>In the example, the Implicit Client Profile Start Page describes the
   prerequisite configuration, which must be part of the client profile stored
   in the OpenAM realm where you set up the OpenID Provider. In OpenAM console,
   check that the OAuth 2.0 agent profile matches the settings described.
   If you have already configured the agent profile for the Basic Client Profile
   then you still need to add the redirect URI for the Implicit Client
   Profile.</para>

   <mediaobject xml:id="figure-openid-connect-implicit-start-page">
    <alt>OpenID Connect Implicit Client Profile Start Page</alt>
    <imageobject>
     <imagedata fileref="images/openid-connect-implicit-start-page.png" format="PNG" />
    </imageobject>
    <textobject>
     <para>The Implicit Client Profile start page describes the configuration
     required.</para>
    </textobject>
   </mediaobject>

   <para>Logout of OpenAM, and click the link at the bottom of the page to
   request authorization. The link sends an HTTP GET request asking for
   <literal>id_token token</literal> response types and <literal>openid
   profile</literal> scopes to the OpenID Connect provider authorization
   URI.</para>

   <para>If everything is configured correctly, OpenAM's OpenID Connect provider
   has you authenticate as an end user, such as the demo user with username
   <literal>demo</literal> and password <literal>changeit</literal>, and
   grant (Allow) the client access to your profile.</para>

   <para>If you successfully authenticate and allow the example client access
   to your profile, OpenAM returns the access token and ID token directly in
   the fragment (after <literal>#</literal>) of the redirect URI. The client
   does not get an authorization code. The client shows the response to the
   request, and also decodes the ID token to show the content and to perform
   some validation (though it does not check the ID token signature). Finally
   the client uses the access token to request information about the end user
   who authenticated, and displays the result.</para>

   <mediaobject xml:id="figure-openid-connect-implicit-response-page">
    <alt>OpenID Connect Implicit Client Profile Response Page</alt>
    <imageobject>
     <imagedata fileref="images/openid-connect-implicit-response-page.png" format="PNG" />
    </imageobject>
    <textobject>
     <para>The Implicit Client Profile response page shows responses from
     OpenAM's OpenID Connect provider.</para>
    </textobject>
   </mediaobject>

   <para>As for the Basic Client Profile, the ID Token indicates the end user's
   OpenAM realm in addition to the standard information.</para>
  </example>
 </section>

 <section xml:id="openid-connect-security-considerations">
  <title>Security Considerations</title>

  <para>As for other OAuth 2.0 applications, you must protect messages going
  across the network. OpenID Connect 1.0 requires Transport Layer Security
  (TLS). The chapter on <link xlink:show="new"
  xlink:href="admin-guide#chap-certs-keystores"
  xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"><citetitle>Managing
  Certificates</citetitle></link> includes some discussion of protecting
  traffic in the container where OpenAM runs. Also see the documentation for
  your web application container.</para>

  <para>Also take into account the points developed in the section on <link
  xlink:href="http://openid.net/specs/openid-connect-messages-1_0.html#security-considerations"
  xlink:show="new"><citetitle>Security Considerations</citetitle></link> in
  the OpenID Connect Messages draft specification.</para>
 </section>
</chapter>
