<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ! CCPL HEADER START
  !
  ! This work is licensed under the Creative Commons
  ! Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 3.0 Unported License.
  ! To view a copy of this license, visit
  ! http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/
  ! or send a letter to Creative Commons, 444 Castro Street,
  ! Suite 900, Mountain View, California, 94041, USA.
  !
  ! You can also obtain a copy of the license at
  ! src/main/resources/legal-notices/CC-BY-NC-ND.txt.
  ! See the License for the specific language governing permissions
  ! and limitations under the License.
  !
  ! If applicable, add the following below this CCPL HEADER, with the fields
  ! enclosed by brackets "[]" replaced with your own identifying information:
  !      Portions Copyright [yyyy] [name of copyright owner]
  !
  ! CCPL HEADER END
  !
  !      Copyright 2011-2013 ForgeRock, Inc.
  !    
-->
<chapter xml:id='chap-sso'
 xmlns='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook'
 version='5.0' xml:lang='en'
 xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'
 xsi:schemaLocation='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd'
 xmlns:xlink='http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink'
 xmlns:xinclude='http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude'>
 <title>Configuring Single Sign-On within One Domain</title>


    <!-- Given the nature of this chapter, I've set this up , esp the description of Peter's diagram,
more for newbies, mj -->

    <para>This chapter describes the configuration of <firstterm>Single Sign-On</firstterm> (SSO) services for
        multiple resources on one domain. To understand how SSO works, you need to understand some key elements of the
        HTTP cookie, as described in RFC 6525, <link xlink:show="new" xlink:href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc6265">
        HTTP State Management Mechanism</link>.</para>

    <indexterm><primary>Single Sign-On (SSO)</primary></indexterm>

    <para>With SSO a user can access multiple independent services from a single session.</para>

    <!-- Since I was clearly having trouble with definitions, I think the contrast helps (and I consulted other sources,
    -->

    <section xml:id="sso-cookies">
        <title>The Basics of the HTTP Cookie</title>

        <para>Within an HTTP cookie, you can store a single custom
        <literal><replaceable>name</replaceable>=<replaceable>value</replaceable></literal> pair, such as
        <literal><replaceable>sessionid</replaceable>=<replaceable>value</replaceable></literal>.
        Other custom names within a cookie are as follows.</para>

        <variablelist>

            <varlistentry>
                <term>Domain</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Normally set to the domain from where the cookie was issued. To work with multiple subdomains,
                    the <varname>Domain</varname> should be set to a URL like
                    <varname>Domain</varname><literal>=example.net</literal>. This is also known as the cookie domain,
                    as defined in the
                    <link xlink:href="reference#chap-config-ref" xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink">
                    <citetitle>Configuration Reference</citetitle></link> chapter of the Reference document.
                    A cookie domain set to <literal>example.net</literal> will work for subdomains such as
                    <literal>app1.example.net</literal> and <literal>service1.example.net</literal>.
                    </para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
                <term>Path</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The directory in the URL to which the cookie applies. If the <varname>Path</varname>
                    <literal>=/openam</literal>, the cookie applies to the <filename>/openam</filename> subdirectory of
                    the FQDN, and lower level directories, including <filename>openam/UI</filename> and
                    <filename>openam/UI/Login</filename>.</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
                <term>Secure</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>If the <varname>Secure</varname> name is included, the cookie can be transferred only over
                    HTTPS. When a request is made over HTTP, the cookie is not made available to the application.</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
                <term>HttpOnly</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>When the <varname>HttpOnly</varname> name is included, that cookie will not be accessible
                    through JavaScript. According to
                    <link xlink:show="new" xlink:href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc6265#section-4.1.2.6">RFC 6265</link>,
                    the noted flag "instructs the user agent to omit the cookie when providing access to cookies via
                    'non-HTTP' APIs (such as a web browser API that exposes cookies to scripts)."</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

            <varlistentry>
                <term>Expires</term>
                <listitem>
                    <para>The lifetime of a cookie can be limited, with an <varname>Expires</varname> name configured
                        with a time, based on UTC (GMT).</para>
                </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

        </variablelist>

        <note>
            <para>Be careful. Do not take a shortcut with a top-level domain. Web browser clients today are designed to
            ignore cookies set to top-level domains including <literal>com</literal>, <literal>net</literal>, and
            <literal>co.uk</literal>. In addition, a cookie with a value like <varname>Domain</varname>=
            <literal>app1.example.net</literal> will not work for similar subdomains such as
            <literal>app2.example.net</literal>.</para>
        </note>

    </section>

    <!-- From Peter's citation of
http://stackoverflow.com/questions/794243/internet-explorer-ignores-cookies-on-some-domains-cannot-read-or-set-cookies
    -->

<section xml:id="sso-process">
<title>Cookies and the SSO Session Process</title>

    <para>OpenAM uses cookies to track user sessions. The diagram shown next illustrates how OpenAM assigns and tracks
    cookies.</para>

    <itemizedlist>
        <para>In the diagram:</para>
        <listitem>
            <para>The domain shown in the description is <literal>example.net</literal></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>The protected resource application can be found on <literal>app.example.net</literal></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <para>The OpenAM server is located on <literal>sso.example.net</literal>.</para>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

<mediaobject xml:id="figure-sso-web-sequence">
    <alt>SSO with Policy Agent</alt>
    <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/ssov3.png" format="PNG"/>
    </imageobject>
    <textobject>
        <para>The sequence diagram illustrates events associated with SSO.</para>
    </textobject>
</mediaobject>

    <para>A client points his browser to a protected resource application. An agent on the
    application checks the client browser cookies for the presence of a session ID, a component of
    an SSO Token. If such a Session ID exists and is valid, the agent requests validation  (see arrow 8).</para>

    <para>If no valid session ID currently exists, the agent redirects the client to OpenAM for authentication (AuthN).
    The client is then sent to OpenAM for AuthN. If the client submits valid credentials, the AuthN service
    creates a session cookie. The SSO Token and configured domain name is embedded in that cookie. OpenAM issues an HTTP
    redirect to send the client browser back to the protected resource. The SSO Token is actually a Java Object.</para>

    <para>The agent then verifies the validity of the session with the OpenAM session service, before granting access.
    </para>

</section>

<section xml:id="sso-problems">
<title>Potential Problems</title>

<para>In general, problems with SSO relate to some sort of mismatch of domain names. For example, a cookie that is
    configured on a third-level domain such as <literal>sso.example.net</literal> will not work with an application on a
    similar domain such as <literal>app.example.net</literal>. Even if the Session ID is valid, the application will not
    receive the SSO Token. The request is then redirected to OpenAM. The client gets what appears as a SSO Token in the
    diagram, which is actually a valid SSO tracking cookie that redirects immediated, and the cycle continues.
    Other issues that may lead to similar problems are shown here.
</para>

<itemizedlist>

    <listitem>
        <para>When a cookie domain does not match a domain for the protected application</para>
        <para>Assume the application is configured on a domain named <literal>example.org</literal>. That application
        will not receive an SSO Token configured on the <literal>example.net</literal> domain.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
        <para>When a third-level domain is used for the SSO Token</para>
        <para>If an SSO Token is configured on <literal>sso.example.net</literal>, an application on
        <literal>app.example.net</literal> does not receive the corresponding cookie. In this case, the solution is to
        configure the SSO Token on <literal>example.net</literal>.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
        <para>When the <varname>Secure</varname> flag is used with a regular HTTP application</para>
        <para>If you need encrypted communications for an application protected by OpenAM, use the
        <varname>Secure</varname> flag and make sure the application is accessible over HTTPS.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
        <para>When the path listed in the cookie does not match the path for the application</para>
        <para>Perhaps the cookie is configured with an <filename>/helloworld</filename> path; that won't match an
        application that might be configured with an <filename>/hellomars</filename> path. In that case, the application
        will not receive the cookie.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
        <para>When an inappropriate name is used for the cookie domain</para>
        <para>As noted earlier, client browsers are configured to ignore first-level domains such as
        <literal>com</literal> and <literal>net</literal> as well as functional equivalents such as
        <literal>co.uk</literal> and <literal>co.jp</literal>.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
        <para>When working with different browsers</para>
        <para>The <literal><replaceable>name</replaceable></literal>=<literal><replaceable>value</replaceable></literal>
        pairs described earlier may not apply to all browsers. The requirements for an HTTP cookie sent to an IE
        browser may differ from the requirements for other standard browsers such as Firefox and Chrome. Based on
        anecdotal reports, IE does not recognize domain names that start with a number. In addition, IE reportedly
        refuses cookies that include the underscore (_) character in the FQDN.</para>
    </listitem>

</itemizedlist>

</section>

    <!-- set up separate section for procedure -->
<section xml:id="configure-sso-one-domain">
    <title>Configure SSO on One Domain</title>

    <para>Now that you have read about the SSO process, you should be able to set it up on a server configured with
        OpenAM and a web service protected by an OpenAM agent. The following procedure assumes that you know how to
        configure OpenAM, the Apache Web server, and associated OpenAM Apache agent.</para>

    <procedure xml:id="sso-one-domain-procedure">
        <title>Configure SSO on One Domain</title>

        <step>
            <para>Install OpenAM as described in the <link xlink:href="install-guide"
            xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"><citetitle>OpenAM Installation 
            Guide</citetitle></link>. This procedure uses a Server URL of 
            <literal>http://openam.example.net:8080/openam</literal>.</para>
        </step>

        <step>
            <para>Install the appropriate policy agent, as described in the <link xlink:href="agent-install-guide"
            xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"><citetitle>OpenAM Policy Agent 
            Installation Guide</citetitle></link>. This procedure uses an agent URL of 
            <literal>http://app.example.net:80</literal>, and an agent name of 
            <literal>webagent1</literal>.</para>
        </step>

        <step>
            <para>Make sure that both URLs are configured with IP addresses, as described in the chapter on
            <link xlink:href="install-guide#chap-install-core" xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink">
            <citetitle>Installing OpenAM Core Services</citetitle></link>.</para>
        </step>

        <step>
            <para>Return to the OpenAM server on <literal>http://openam.example.net:8080/openam</literal>. Log in as
                the administrative user, normally <literal>amadmin</literal>. To activate and configure the agent,
                follow the procedure described in the
                <link xlink:href="agent-install-guide" xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink">
                <citetitle>OpenAM Policy Agent Installation Guide</citetitle></link>.</para>
        </step>

        <step>
            <para>Now you can configure SSO Only mode. In the OpenAM console, click Access Control &gt;
                <replaceable>Realm Name</replaceable> &gt; Agents &gt; <replaceable>webagent1</replaceable>. Scroll down
                to SSO Only Mode and activate the Enabled box.</para>
        </step>

        <step>
            <para>Save your changes.</para>
        </step>

        <step>
            <para>Make sure you have configured the SSO domain, in this case, <literal>example.net</literal>. Click
            Configuration &gt; System &gt; Platform. Make sure <literal>example.net</literal> (or your chosen domain)
            is selected as a cookie domain.</para>
        </step>

        <step>
            <para>Save your changes.</para>
        </step>

        <step>
            <para>Restart the web server. The agent should be active. You should now be able to log out of the OpenAM
            server.</para>
        </step>

        <step>
            <para>Verify the agent URL, in this case, <literal>http://app.example.net</literal>. The OpenAM
            web agent should now redirect requests to the OpenAM server.</para>
        </step>

    </procedure>

    <para>If you want to configure OpenAM and an application on two different cookie domains, such as <literal>example.org
    </literal> and <literal>example.net</literal>, you will need to set up Cross-Domain SSO (CDSSO). For more
        information, see the chapter on
        <link xlink:href="admin-guide#chap-cdsso" xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink">
            <citetitle>Configuring Cross-Domain Single Sign On</citetitle></link>.</para>

    </section>

</chapter>