<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ! CCPL HEADER START
  !
  ! This work is licensed under the Creative Commons
  ! Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 3.0 Unported License.
  ! To view a copy of this license, visit
  ! http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/
  ! or send a letter to Creative Commons, 444 Castro Street,
  ! Suite 900, Mountain View, California, 94041, USA.
  !
  ! You can also obtain a copy of the license at
  ! src/main/resources/legal-notices/CC-BY-NC-ND.txt.
  ! See the License for the specific language governing permissions
  ! and limitations under the License.
  !
  ! If applicable, add the following below this CCPL HEADER, with the fields
  ! enclosed by brackets "[]" replaced with your own identifying information:
  !      Portions Copyright [yyyy] [name of copyright owner]
  !
  ! CCPL HEADER END
  !
  !      Copyright 2011-2014 ForgeRock AS
  !    
-->
<chapter xml:id='chap-backup-restore'
         xmlns='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook'
         version='5.0' xml:lang='en'
         xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'
         xsi:schemaLocation='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook
                             http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd'
         xmlns:xlink='http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink'>
 <title>Backing Up and Restoring OpenAM Configurations</title>

 <para>
  OpenAM stores configuration data in an LDAP directory server and in files.
  The directory service replicates configuration data between directory servers,
  allowing OpenAM to share configuration data across servers in a Site.
  During normal production operations, you rely on directory replication
  to maintain multiple, current copies of OpenAM service configuration.
  To recover from the loss of a server or from a serious administrative error,
  back up directory data and configuration files.
 </para>

 <para>
  This chapter shows how to backup and restore OpenAM configuration data
  by backing up and restoring local configuration files
  and local (embedded) configuration directory server data.
  If your deployment uses an external configuration directory server,
  then refer to the documentation for your external directory server
  or work with your directory server administrator to back up and restore
  configuration data stored in the external directory service.
 </para>

 <para>
  For OpenDJ directory server you can find more information in the chapter on
  <link
   xlink:href="${opendjDocBase}/admin-guide/#chap-backup-restore"
   xlink:show="new"
  ><citetitle>Backing Up &amp; Restoring Data</citetitle></link>.
 </para>

 <itemizedlist>
  <para>
   In OpenAM deployments where configuration directory data is replicated,
   you must take the following points into consideration.
  </para>

  <listitem>
   <para>
    Directory replication mechanically applies new changes to ensure
    that replicated data is the same everywhere.
    When you restore older backup data,
    directory replication applies newer changes to the older data.
   </para>

   <para>
    This includes new changes that the administrator sees as mistakes.
    To recover from administrative error, you must work around this behavior
    either by performing a change to be replicated that repairs the error
    or by restoring all replicas to a state prior to the error.
   </para>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
   <para>
    When preparing directory server backup and restore operations,
    also know that data replication purge operations affect
    the useful lifetime of any data that you back up.
   </para>

   <para>
    Replication relies on historical data to resolve any conflicts that arise.
    If directory servers did not eventually purge this historical data,
    the data would continue to grow until it filled all available space.
    Directory servers therefore purge older historical data.
    OpenDJ purges historical data older than 3 days by default.
   </para>

   <para>
    When the directory server encounters a gap in historical data
    it cannot correctly complete replication operations.
    You must make sure, therefore, that any data you restore from backup
    is not older than the replication purge delay.
    Otherwise your restoration operation could break replication
    with the likely result that you must restore all servers from backup,
    losing any changes that occurred in the meantime.
   </para>
  </listitem>
 </itemizedlist>

  <orderedlist>
  <para>
   This chapter aims to cover the following uses of backup data.
  </para>

  <listitem>
   <para>
    Recovery from server failure.
   </para>

   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <xref linkend="backup-for-disaster" />
     </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
     <para>
      <xref linkend="restore-after-disaster" />
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </listitem>

  <listitem>
   <para>
    Recovery from serious administrative error.
   </para>

   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <xref linkend="export-configuration-data" />
     </para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
     <para>
      <xref linkend="recover-from-serious-error" />
     </para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </listitem>
 </orderedlist>

 <procedure xml:id="backup-for-disaster">
  <title>To Back Up All Server Configuration Data</title>

  <para>
   This procedure backs up all the configuration data stored with the server.
   This backup is to be restored when rebuilding a failed server.
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <para>
    Use this procedure when the following statements are true.
   </para>

   <listitem>
    <para>
     OpenAM stores configuration data in the embedded OpenDJ directory server.
    </para>

    <para>
     The embedded OpenDJ directory server files are co-located
     with other OpenAM configuration files.
    </para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>
     If OpenAM stores CTS data in the embedded OpenDJ directory server,
     then the restore operation overwrites current CTS data with older data.
     After you restore from backup, users authenticate again as necessary.
    </para>

    <para>
     For deployments with long-lived sessions,
     you can limit the extent of re-authentication by using session failover.
     For details, see the <citetitle>Installation Guide</citetitle> chapter,
     <link
      xlink:href="install-guide#chap-session-failover"
      xlink:show="new"
      xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"
     ><citetitle>Setting Up OpenAM Session Failover</citetitle></link>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>
   If your deployment uses an external configuration directory server,
   then refer to the documentation for your external directory server
   or work with your directory server administrator to back up and restore
   configuration data stored in the external directory service.
   For OpenDJ directory server you can find more information in the chapter on
   <link
    xlink:href="${opendjDocBase}/admin-guide/#chap-backup-restore"
    xlink:show="new"
   ><citetitle>Backing Up &amp; Restoring Data</citetitle></link>.
  </para>

  <indexterm>
   <primary>Backup</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <important>
   <para>
    Understand the explanation in the introductory paragraphs of this chapter
    before you proceed.
    Directory backup validity depends on replication purge delay,
    which by default for OpenDJ directory server is 3 days.
   </para>

   <para>
    Also do not restore configuration data from a backup of
    a different release of OpenAM.
    The structure of configuration data can change from release to release.
   </para>
  </important>

  <para>
   Follow these steps for each OpenAM server that you want to back up.
  </para>

  <step>
   <para>
    Stop OpenAM or the container in which it runs.
   </para>
  </step>

  <step>
   <para>
    Backup OpenAM configuration files
    including those of the configuration directory server
    but skipping log and lock files.
   </para>

   <para>
    The following example uses the default configuration location.
    $HOME is the home directory of the user
    who runs the web container where OpenAM is deployed,
    and OpenAM is deployed in Apache Tomcat under <literal>openam</literal>.
   </para>

   <screen>
$ <userinput>cd $HOME</userinput>
$ <userinput>zip \
 --recurse-paths \
 /path/to/backup-`date -u +i5%F-%m-%S`.zip \
 openam .openamcfg/AMConfig_path_to_tomcat_webapps_openam_ \
 --exclude openam/openam/debug/* openam/openam/log/* openam/openam/stats* \
  openam/opends/logs/* openam/opends/locks/*</userinput>
...
$ <userinput>ls /path/to/backup-2014-12-01-12-00.zip</userinput>
<computeroutput>/path/to/backup-2014-12-01-12-00.zip</computeroutput>
   </screen>

   <para>
    The backup is valid until the end of the purge delay.
   </para>
  </step>

  <step>
   <para>
    Start OpenAM or the container in which it runs.
   </para>
  </step>
 </procedure>
 
 <procedure xml:id="restore-after-disaster">
  <title>To Restore All Server Configuration Data</title>

  <para>
   This procedure restores all the configuration data for a server,
   where the configuration data has been backed up as described in
   <xref linkend="backup-for-disaster" />.
   This procedure applies when rebuilding a failed server.
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
   <para>
    Use this procedure when the following statements are true.
   </para>

   <listitem>
    <para>
     OpenAM stores configuration data in the embedded OpenDJ directory server.
    </para>

    <para>
     The embedded OpenDJ directory server files are co-located
     with other OpenAM configuration files.
    </para>
   </listitem>

   <listitem>
    <para>
     If OpenAM stores CTS data in the embedded OpenDJ directory server,
     then the restore operation overwrites current CTS data with older data.
     After you restore from backup, users authenticate again as necessary.
    </para>

    <para>
     For deployments with long-lived sessions,
     you can limit the extent of re-authentication by using session failover.
     For details, see the <citetitle>Installation Guide</citetitle> chapter,
     <link
      xlink:href="install-guide#chap-session-failover"
      xlink:show="new"
      xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"
      ><citetitle>Setting Up OpenAM Session Failover</citetitle></link>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>
   If your deployment uses an external configuration directory server,
   then refer to the documentation for your external directory server
   or work with your directory server administrator to back up and restore
   configuration data stored in the external directory service.
   For OpenDJ directory server you can find more information in the chapter on
   <link
    xlink:href="${opendjDocBase}/admin-guide/#chap-backup-restore"
    xlink:show="new"
   ><citetitle>Backing Up &amp; Restoring Data</citetitle></link>.
  </para>

  <indexterm>
   <primary>Restoring</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <important>
   <para>
    Understand the explanation in the introductory paragraphs of this chapter
    before you proceed.
    Directory backup validity depends on replication purge delay,
    which by default for OpenDJ directory server is 3 days.
   </para>

   <para>
    Also do not restore configuration data from a backup of
    a different release of OpenAM.
    The structure of configuration data can change from release to release.
   </para>
  </important>

  <para>
   Follow these steps for each OpenAM server to restore.
   If you are restoring OpenAM after a failure,
   make sure you make a copy of any configuration and log files
   that you need to investigate the problem before restoring OpenAM from backup.
  </para>

  <step>
   <para>
    Stop OpenAM or the container in which it runs.
   </para>
  </step>

  <step>
   <para>
    Restore files in the configuration directory as necessary,
    making sure that you restore from a valid backup,
    one that is newer than the replication purge delay.
   </para>

   <screen>
$ <userinput>cd $HOME</userinput>
$ <userinput>unzip /path/to/backup-2014-12-01-12-00.zip</userinput>
<computeroutput>Archive:  /path/to/backup-2014-12-01-12-00.zip
replace openam/.configParam? [y]es, [n]o, [A]ll, [N]one, [r]ename: </computeroutput><userinput>A</userinput>
...
   </screen>
  </step>

  <step>
   <para>
    Start OpenAM or the container in which it runs.
   </para>
  </step>
 </procedure>

 <procedure xml:id="export-configuration-data">
  <title>To Export Only Configuration Data</title>

  <para>
   LDAP Data Interchange Format (LDIF) is a standard, text-based format
   for storing LDAP directory data.
   You can use LDIF excerpts to make changes to directory data.
  </para>

  <para>
   This procedure takes an LDIF backup of OpenAM configuration data only.
   Use this LDIF data when recovering from a serious configuration error.
  </para>

  <indexterm>
   <primary>Backup</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <step>
   <para>
    Make sure that OpenAM's configuration is in correct working order
    before exporting configuration data.
   </para>
  </step>

  <step>
   <para>
    Use the OpenDJ <command>export-ldif</command> command to run a task
    that exports only configuration data, not CTS data.
   </para>

   <para>
    You can run this command without stopping OpenAM.
   </para>

   <para>
    Find OpenDJ commands under the file system directory
    that contains OpenAM configuration files.
   </para>

   <para>
    The bind password for Directory Manager is the same
    as the password for the OpenAM global administrator (amadmin).
   </para>

   <screen>
$ <userinput>$HOME/openam/opends/bin/export-ldif \
 --port 4444 \
 --hostname openam.example.com \
 --bindDN "cn=Directory Manager" \
 --bindPassword password \
 --backendID userRoot \
 --includeBranch ${defaultRootSuffix} \
 --excludeBranch ou=tokens,${defaultRootSuffix} \
 --ldifFile /path/to/backup-`date -u +%F-%m-%s`.ldif \
 --start 0 \
 --trustAll</userinput>
<computeroutput>Export task 20141208113331302 scheduled to start Dec 8, 2014 11:33:31 AM CET</computeroutput>
   </screen>

   <para>
    When the task completes, the LDIF file is at the expected location.
   </para>

   <screen>
$ <userinput>ls /path/to/*.ldif</userinput>
<computeroutput>/path/to/backup-2014-12-08-12-1418034808.ldif</computeroutput>
   </screen>
  </step>
 </procedure>

 <procedure xml:id="recover-from-serious-error">
  <title>To Restore Configuration Data After Serious Error</title>

  <para>
   A serious configuration error is an error that you cannot easily repair
   by using OpenAM configuration tools such as OpenAM console
   or the <command>ssoadm</command> command.
  </para>

  <para>
   Use this procedure to recover from a serious configuration error
   by manually restoring configuration data to an earlier state.
   This procedure depends on LDIF data that you exported as described in
   <xref linkend="export-configuration-data" />.
  </para>

  <indexterm>
   <primary>Restore</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <step>
   <para>
    Read the OpenDJ change log to determine the LDAP changes
    that caused the configuration problem.
   </para>

   <para>
    The OpenDJ change log provides an external change log mechanism
    that allows you to read changes made to directory data
    for replicated directory servers.
   </para>

   <para>
    For instructions on reading the change log,
    see the OpenDJ <citetitle>Administration Guide</citetitle> section on
    <link
     xlink:href="${opendjDocBase}/admin-guide/#repl-change-notification"
     xlink:show="new"
    ><citetitle>Change Notification For Your Applications</citetitle></link>.
   </para>
  </step>

  <step>
   <para>
    Based on the data in the change log,
    determine what changes would reverse the configuration error.
   </para>

   <para>
    For changes that resulted in one attribute value being replaced by another,
    you can recover the information from the change log alone.
   </para>
  </step>

  <step>
   <para>
    For deleted content not contained in the change log,
    use the LDIF resulting from <xref linkend="export-configuration-data" />
    to determine a prior, working state of the configuration entry
    before the configuration error.
   </para>
  </step>

  <step>
   <para>
    Prepare LDIF to modify configuration data in a way that repairs the error
    by restoring the state of directory entries before the administrative error.
   </para>
  </step>

  <step>
   <para>
    Use the OpenDJ <command>ldapmodify</command> command
    to apply the modification.
   </para>

   <para>
    For instructions on making changes to directory data
    see the OpenDJ <citetitle>Administration Guide</citetitle> section on
    <link
     xlink:href="${opendjDocBase}/admin-guide/#write-ldap"
     xlink:show="new"
    ><citetitle>Updating the Directory</citetitle></link>.
   </para>
  </step>
 </procedure>
</chapter>
