<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ! CCPL HEADER START
  !
  ! This work is licensed under the Creative Commons
  ! Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 3.0 Unported License.
  ! To view a copy of this license, visit
  ! http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/
  ! or send a letter to Creative Commons, 444 Castro Street,
  ! Suite 900, Mountain View, California, 94041, USA.
  !
  ! You can also obtain a copy of the license at
  ! src/main/resources/legal-notices/CC-BY-NC-ND.txt.
  ! See the License for the specific language governing permissions
  ! and limitations under the License.
  !
  ! If applicable, add the following below this CCPL HEADER, with the fields
  ! enclosed by brackets "[]" replaced with your own identifying information:
  !      Portions Copyright [yyyy] [name of copyright owner]
  !
  ! CCPL HEADER END
  !
  !      Copyright 2011-2013 ForgeRock AS
  !    
-->
<chapter xml:id='chap-cdsso'
 xmlns='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook'
 version='5.0' xml:lang='en'
 xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'
 xsi:schemaLocation='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd'
 xmlns:xlink='http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink'>
 <title>Configuring Cross-Domain Single Sign On</title>

 <para>This chapter shows you how to configure cross-domain single sign on
 (CDSSO). When you have multiple domains in a single organization, CDSSO lets
 your OpenAM servers in one domain work with policy agents from other
 domains.</para>

 <para>CDSSO is an OpenAM-specific capability. For single sign on across
 multiple organizations or when integrating with other access management
 software, use OpenAM's federation capabilities.</para>

 <indexterm><primary>Cross-domain single sign on (CDSSO)</primary></indexterm>
 <para><firstterm>Cross-domain single sign on</firstterm> provides
 a safe mechanism for managing access across multiple different domains that
 you control. CDSSO lets OpenAM authenticate users redirected by policy agents
 in other DNS domains.</para>

 <para>Single sign on depends on cookies to store session information. Yet for
 for security reasons, browsers do not let a web site in one domain to get
 access to a cookie from another domain. With CDSSO, the policy agents work
 around this by negotiating with OpenAM to allow access.</para>

 <para>The Java EE policy agent allows CDSSO by using a mechanism to write
 the SSO token from OpenAM authentication to a cookie with the domain
 the host where the agent runs. The following sequence diagram illustrates
 this mechanism.</para>

 <mediaobject xml:id="figure-cdsso-jee-sequence">
  <alt>Java EE policy agent mechanism for CDSSO</alt>
  <imageobject>
   <imagedata fileref="images/cdsso-jee-sequence.png" format="PNG"/>
  </imageobject>
  <textobject>
   <para>The sequence diagram illustrates the Java EE policy agent mechanism
   for CDSSO.</para>
  </textobject>
 </mediaobject>

 <para>Whereas the Java EE policy agent has an endpoint specifically to handle
 the cookie domain translation, the web policy agent handles the request
 directly as shown in the following sequence diagram.</para>

 <mediaobject xml:id="figure-cdsso-web-sequence">
  <alt>Web policy agent mechanism for CDSSO</alt>
  <imageobject>
   <imagedata fileref="images/cdsso-web-sequence.png" format="PNG"/>
  </imageobject>
  <textobject>
   <para>The sequence diagram illustrates the web policy agent mechanism
   for CDSSO.</para>
  </textobject>
 </mediaobject>

 <procedure xml:id="enable-cdsso-jee-agent">
  <title>To Enable CDSSO For a Java EE Policy Agent</title>

  <step>
   <para>In the OpenAM console, browse to Access Control &gt;
   <replaceable>Realm Name</replaceable> &gt; Agents &gt; J2EE &gt;
   <replaceable>Agent Name</replaceable> &gt; SSO.</para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>Scroll down and enable Cross Domain SSO.</para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>Check that the CDSSO Redirect URI is set.</para>
   <para>Depending on where you deployed your Java EE agent application, the
   default is something like <literal>/agentapp/sunwCDSSORedirectURI</literal>.</para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>Set the list of URLs for CDSSO Servlet URL to the Cross Domain
   Controller Servlet URLs of the servers the agent accesses, such as
   <literal>http://openam.example.com:8080/openam/cdcservlet</literal>.</para>
   <para>If the agent accesses OpenAM through a load balancer, use the load
   balancer URLs, such as
   <literal>http://load-balancer.example.com:8080/openam/cdcservlet</literal>.</para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>Leave the CDSSO Clock Skew set to 0.</para>
   <para>Make sure instead that the clocks on the servers where you run OpenAM
   and policy agents are synchronized.</para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>Set the list of URLs for CDSSO Trusted ID Provider to the Cross Domain
   Controller Servlet URLs of the OpenAM servers the agent accesses, such
   <literal>http://openam.example.com:8080/openam/cdcservlet</literal>.</para>
   <para>This list should include one CDC Servlet URL for every OpenAM server
   the agent might access. You do not need to include site or load balancer
   URLs.</para>
  </step>
  <step performance="optional">
   <para>To protect the SSO token from network snooping, you can select CDSSO
   Secure Enable to mark the SSO token cookie as secure.</para>
   <para>If you select this, then the SSO token cookie can only be sent over
   a secure connection (HTTPS).</para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>Add the domains involved in CDSSO in the CDSSO Domain List.</para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>If necessary, update the Agent Root URL for CDSSO list on the Global
   tab page.</para>
   <para>If the policy agent is on a server with virtual host names, add the
   virtual host URLs to the list.</para>
   <para>If the policy agent is behind a load balancer, add the load balancer
   URL to the list.</para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>Save your work.</para>
  </step>
 </procedure>

 <procedure xml:id="enable-cdsso-web-agent">
  <title>To Enable CDSSO For a Web Policy Agent</title>

  <step>
   <para>In the OpenAM console, browse to Access Control &gt;
   <replaceable>Realm Name</replaceable> &gt; Agents &gt; Web &gt;
   <replaceable>Agent Name</replaceable> &gt; SSO.</para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>Enable Cross Domain SSO.</para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>Set the list of URLs for CDSSO Servlet URL to the Cross Domain
   Controller Servlet URLs of the servers the agent accesses, such as
   <literal>http://openam.example.com:8080/openam/cdcservlet</literal>.</para>
   <para>If the agent accesses OpenAM through a load balancer, use the load
   balancer URLs, such as
   <literal>http://load-balancer.example.com:8080/openam/cdcservlet</literal>.</para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>Add the domains involved in CDSSO in the Cookies Domain List.</para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>If necessary, update the Agent Root URL for CDSSO list on the Global
   tab page.</para>
   <para>If the policy agent is on a server with virtual host names, add the
   virtual host URLs to the list.</para>
   <para>If the policy agent is behind a load balancer, add the load balancer
   URL to the list.</para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>Save your work.</para>
  </step>
 </procedure>

 <procedure xml:id="show-cdsso-login-progress">
  <title>To Indicate Progress During CDSSO Login</title>

  <para>The default self-submitting form page that OpenAM presents to users
  contains hidden fields, but is otherwise blank. If you want to show users
  that the operation is in progress, then customize the necessary JSP.</para>

  <step>
   <para>Edit a copy of the file
   <filename>config/federation/default/cdclogin.jsp</filename> to add a
   clue that SSO is in progress, such as an image.</para>

   <para>You can find this file where you deployed OpenAM, such as
   <filename>/path/to/tomcat/webapps/openam/config/federation/default/cdclogin.jsp</filename>.</para>

   <para>When you add an image or other presentation element, make sure that
   you retain the form and JavaScript as is.</para>
  </step>

  <step>
   <para>Unpack <?eval ${coreWarFile}?>, and replace the file with your
   modified version.</para>

   <para>Also include any images you reference in the page.</para>
  </step>

  <step>
   <para>Pack up your custom version of OpenAM, and then deploy it in your
   web container.</para>
  </step>
 </procedure>

 <procedure xml:id="enable-cdsso-cookie-hijacking-protection">
  <title>To Protect Against CDSSO Cookie Hijacking</title>

  <para>When cookies are set for an entire domain such as
  <literal>.example.com</literal>, an attacker who steals a cookie can use it
  from any host in the domain such as <literal>untrusted.example.com</literal>.
  Cookie hijacking protection restricts cookies to the fully-qualified domain
  name (FQDN) of the host where they are issued, such as
  <literal>openam-server.example.com</literal> and
  <literal>server-with-agent.example.com</literal>, using CDSSO to handle
  authentication and authorization.</para>

  <para>For CDSSO with cookie hijacking protection, when a client successfully
  authenticates OpenAM issues the master SSO token cookie for its FQDN.
  OpenAM issues <firstterm>restricted token</firstterm> cookies for the
  other FQDNs where the policy agents reside. The client ends up with cookies
  having different session identifiers for different FQDNs, and the OpenAM
  server stores the correlation between the master SSO token and restricted
  tokens, such that the client only has one master session internally in
  OpenAM.</para>

  <para>To protect against cookie hijacking you restrict the OpenAM server
  domain to the server where OpenAM runs. This sets the domain of the SSO token
  cookie to the host running the OpenAM server that issued the token. You also
  enable use of a unique SSO token cookie. For your Java EE policy agents, you
  enable use of the unique SSO token cookie in the agent configuration as
  well.</para>

  <step>
   <para>In the OpenAM console, browse to Configuration &gt; System &gt;
   Platform.</para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>Remove the domain such as <literal>.example.com</literal> from the
   Cookies Domains list, and replace it with the server host name such as
   <literal>openam.example.com</literal>, or if OpenAM is behind a load
   balancer with the load balancer host name, such as
   <literal>load-balancer.example.com</literal>.</para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>Save your work.</para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>In the OpenAM console, browse to Configuration &gt; Servers and Sites
   &gt; Default Server Settings &gt; Advanced, and then make the necessary
   changes.</para>
   <substeps>
    <step>
     <para>Change the setting for the property
     <literal>com.sun.identity.enableUniqueSSOTokenCookie</literal> to
     <literal>true</literal>, from the default <literal>false</literal>.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>Make sure that the property
     <literal>com.sun.identity.authentication.uniqueCookieName</literal> is
     set to the name of the cookie that will hold the URL to the OpenAM server
     that authenticated the user.</para>
     <para>The default name is <literal>sunIdentityServerAuthNServer</literal>.</para>
    </step>
   </substeps>
   <para>Save your work.</para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>Browse to Configuration &gt; Servers and Sites &gt; <replaceable>Server
   Name</replaceable> &gt; Advanced, and add the property
   <literal>com.sun.identity.authentication.uniqueCookieDomain</literal>,
   setting the value to the fully-qualified domain name of the current OpenAM
   server, such as <literal>openam.example.com</literal>.</para>

   <para>Then Save your work.</para>
  </step>
  <step performance="optional">
   <para>For each Java EE policy agent, browse in the OpenAM console to Access
   Control &gt; <replaceable>Realm Name</replaceable> &gt; Agents &gt; J2EE &gt;
   <replaceable>Agent Name</replaceable> &gt; Advanced &gt; Custom Properties,
   and add <literal>com.sun.identity.enableUniqueSSOTokenCookie=true</literal>
   to the list.</para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>Save your work.</para>
  </step>
  <step>
   <para>Restart OpenAM or the container in which it runs for the configuration
   changes to take effect.</para>
  </step>
 </procedure>
</chapter>
