<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ! CCPL HEADER START
  !
  ! This work is licensed under the Creative Commons
  ! Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 3.0 Unported License.
  ! To view a copy of this license, visit
  ! http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/
  ! or send a letter to Creative Commons, 444 Castro Street,
  ! Suite 900, Mountain View, California, 94041, USA.
  !
  ! You can also obtain a copy of the license at
  ! src/main/resources/legal-notices/CC-BY-NC-ND.txt.
  ! See the License for the specific language governing permissions
  ! and limitations under the License.
  !
  ! If applicable, add the following below this CCPL HEADER, with the fields
  ! enclosed by brackets "[]" replaced with your own identifying information:
  !      Portions Copyright [yyyy] [name of copyright owner]
  !
  ! CCPL HEADER END
  !
  !      Copyright 2011-2014 ForgeRock AS
  !    
-->
<chapter xml:id='chap-authz-policy'
 xmlns='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook'
 version='5.0' xml:lang='en'
 xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'
 xsi:schemaLocation='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook
                     http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd'
 xmlns:xlink='http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink'
 xmlns:xinclude='http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude'>

 <title>Defining Authorization Policies</title>

 <para>
  <firstterm>Authorization</firstterm> is determining
  whether to grant or to deny a user access to a resource.
  <firstterm>Policies</firstterm> define how to determine
  whether to grant or deny access.
  This chapter describes how to configure authorization policies in OpenAM.
 </para>
 
 <section xml:id="what-is-authz">
  <title>About Authorization in OpenAM</title>
  <indexterm>
   <primary>Authorization</primary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
   Applications rely on OpenAM for access management,
   which breaks down into authentication,
   or determining who is trying to access a resource,
   and authorization,
   or determining whether to grant or deny access.
   This is because whether access is granted generally depends on
   what the policies about access are,
   who is trying to gain access,
   and perhaps some other conditions,
   such as whether the access itself needs to happen over a secure channel
   or what time of day it is.
  </para>

  <para>
   To return to the international airport example
   from the discussion on authentication
   the policy might be that passengers with valid passports and visas
   presenting valid plane tickets
   are allowed through to the gate where the plane is waiting to take off,
   but only under the condition that the plane is going to leave soon.
   (You cannot expect to get to the gate today
   with a scheduled departure for three months from now.)
  </para>

  <section xml:id="what-is-authz-policies">
   <title>OpenAM Policies and Applications</title>
   <indexterm>
    <primary>Policy</primary>
   </indexterm>

   <variablelist>
    <para>
     To allow OpenAM to determine whether to grant access,
     you define authorization <firstterm>policies</firstterm>.
     A policy defines the following.
    </para>

    <varlistentry>
     <term><firstterm>resources</firstterm></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The resource definitions constrain which resources,
       such as web pages or access to the boarding area,
       the policy applies to.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
     <term><firstterm>actions</firstterm></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The actions are verbs that describe
       what the policy allows users to do to the resources,
       such as read a web page, submit a web form, or access the boarding area.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
     <term><firstterm>subject conditions</firstterm></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The subject conditions constrain who the policy applies to,
       such as all authenticated users, only administrators,
       or only passengers with valid tickets for planes leaving soon.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
     <term><firstterm>environment conditions</firstterm></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The environment conditions set
       the circumstances under which the policy applies,
       such as only during work hours,
       only when accessing from a specific IP address,
       or only when the flight is scheduled to leave within the next four hours.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>

    <varlistentry>
     <term><firstterm>response attributes</firstterm></term>
     <listitem>
      <para>
       The response attributes define information
       that OpenAM attaches to a response following a policy decision,
       such as a name, email address, or frequent flyer status.
      </para>
     </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
   </variablelist>

   <para>
    When queried about whether to let a user through to a protected resource,
    OpenAM decides to authorize access or not based on applicable policies
    as described below in <xref linkend="what-is-authz-decision" />.
    OpenAM communicates its decision to the application
    using OpenAM for access management.
    In the common case, this is a policy agent
    installed on the server where the application runs.
    The agent then enforces the authorization decision from OpenAM.
   </para>

   <mediaobject xml:id="figure-realm-app-policy-overview">
    <alt>Shows the relationship between Realms, Applications and
     Policies, and how a policy agent requests authorization decisions from
     OpenAM.</alt>
    <imageobject>
     <imagedata
      fileref="images/realm-app-policy-overview.png"
      format="PNG" />
    </imageobject>
    <textobject><para>Shows the relationship between Realms, Applications and
     Policies, and how a policy agent requests authorization decisions from
     OpenAM.</para></textobject>
   </mediaobject>

   <para>
    To act as a template for the policies,
    OpenAM uses <firstterm>applications</firstterm>.
    An application can constrain the resources that its policies apply to.
    For example, an application for Example.com's HR service
    might constrain all policies to apply to resources under
    <literal>http*://example.com/hr*</literal> and
    <literal>http*://example.com/hr*?*</literal>.
    The list of applications is the first thing that you see
    when editing policies through OpenAM console.
    You create or select an application,
    and then configure the policies for that application.
   </para>

   <para>
    Applications have associated types.
    The default application type that represents web resources
    is <literal>iPlanetAMWebAgentService</literal>,
    which defines resources as URL patterns and actions as HTTP methods.
    OpenAM policy agents use a default application type based on this type,
    which is called <literal>iPlanetAMWebAgentService</literal>.
    This is the application type for policies
    that you edit through OpenAM console.
    OpenAM supports other application types as well
    that you can manage over the policy REST APIs.
   </para>

   <para>
    For applications that are not of type <literal>iPlanetAmWebAgentService</literal>,
    such as CREST applications, you must manage these applications over REST.
    OpenAM policy agents work with applications of type
    <literal>iPlanetAmWebAgentService</literal>, so your policy evaluation points (PEPs)
    should use the REST endpoints for policy decision requests.
   </para>

   <tip>
    <para>
     When you configure a policy agent,
     if the application for its policies is not named
     <literal>iPlanetAMWebAgentService</literal>,
     then you must edit the policy agent configuration,
     setting the application name to match your application.
    </para>

    <para>
     The application you specify must exist in the evaluation realm
     that you specify for the policy agent.
    </para>
   </tip>

   <para>
    When policies for an application are administered in multiple realms,
    you set up a <firstterm>referral</firstterm> between applications.
    When finding all policies that apply for a given request,
    OpenAM follows the referrals
    to locate the application's policies in other realms.
    This is useful, for example,
    when the same policy agents protect multiple applications.
    The OpenAM policy editor does allow you to manage referrals as well,
    though the referral editor is not enabled by default.
   </para>
   <!-- TODO: link to section explaining how to do this. -->
  </section>

  <section xml:id="what-is-authz-decision">
   <title>OpenAM Policy Decisions</title>

   <para>
    OpenAM relies on policies to reach authorization decisions,
    such as whether to grant or to deny access to a resource.
    OpenAM acts as the <firstterm>policy decision point</firstterm> (PDP),
    whereas OpenAM policy agents act as
    <firstterm>policy enforcement points</firstterm> (PEP).
    In other words, a policy agent or other PEP takes responsibility only
    for enforcing a policy decision rendered by OpenAM.
    When you configured applications and their policies in OpenAM,
    you used OpenAM as a
    <firstterm>policy administration point</firstterm> (PAP).
<!-- Not useful yet:
    For information used to reach policy decisions,
    OpenAM could act as or rely on a
    <firstterm>policy information point</firstterm> (PIP) as well.
-->
   </para>

   <para>
    Concretely speaking, when a PEP requests a policy decision from OpenAM
    it specifies the target resource(s),
    the application (default: <literal>iPlanetAMWebAgentService</literal>),
    and information about the subject and the environment.
    OpenAM as the PDP retrieves policies within the specified application
    that apply to the target resource(s).
    OpenAM then evaluates those policies to make a decision
    based on the conditions matching those of the subject and environment.
    When multiple policies apply for a particular resource,
    the default logic for combining decisions is that
    the first evaluation resulting in a decision to deny access
    takes precedence over all other evaluations.
    OpenAM only allows access if all applicable policies evaluate
    to a decision to allow access.
   </para>

   <para>
    OpenAM communicates the policy decision to the PEP.
    The concrete decision,
    applying policy for a subject under the specified conditions,
    is called an <firstterm>entitlement</firstterm>.
   </para>

   <para>
    The entitlement indicates the resource(s) it applies to,
    the actions permitted and denied for each resource,
    and optionally response attributes and <firstterm>advice</firstterm>.
   </para>

   <para>
    When OpenAM denies a request due to a failed condition,
    OpenAM can send advice to the PEP,
    and the PEP can then take remedial action.
    For instance, suppose a user comes to a web site
    having authenticated with an email address and password,
    which is configured as authentication level 0.
    Had the user authenticated using a one-time password,
    the user would have had authentication level 1 in their session.
    Yet, because they have authentication level 0,
    they currently cannot access the desired page,
    as the policy governing access requires authentication level 1.
    OpenAM sends advice, prompting the PEP
    to have the user re-authenticate using a one-time password module,
    gaining authentication level 1,
    and thus having OpenAM grant access to the protected page.
   </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="what-is-authz-example">
   <title>Example Authorization</title>

   <para>
    Consider the case where OpenAM protects a user profile web page.
    An OpenAM policy agent installed in the web server
    intercepts client requests to enforce policy.
    The policy says that only authenticated users
    can access the page to view and to update their profiles.
   </para>

   <para>
    When a user browses to the profile page,
    the OpenAM policy agent intercepts the request.
    The policy agent notices that the request is to access a protected resource,
    but the request is coming from a user who has not yet logged in
    and consequently has no authorization to visit the page.
    The policy agent therefore redirects the user's browser
    to OpenAM to authenticate.
   </para>

   <para>
    OpenAM receives the redirected user,
    serving a login page that collects the user's email and password.
    With the email and password credentials,
    OpenAM authenticates the user, and creates a session for the user.
    OpenAM then redirects the user to the policy agent,
    which gets the policy decision from OpenAM for the page to access,
    and grants access to the page.
   </para>

   <para>
    OpenAM and the policy agent use cookies set in the user's browser
    to share an opaque reference to the session with OpenAM.
    While the user has a valid session with OpenAM,
    the user can go away to another page in the browser,
    come back to the profile page,
    and gain access without having to enter their email and password again.
   </para>

   <para>
    Notice how OpenAM and the policy agent handle the access in the example.
    The web site developer can offer a profile page,
    but the web site developer never has to manage login,
    or handle who can access a page.
    As OpenAM administrator, you can change
    authentication and authorization independently of updates to the web site.
    You might need to agree with web site developers
    on how OpenAM identifies users
    so web developers can identify users by their own names when they log in.
    By using OpenAM and policy agents for authentication and authorization,
    your organization no longer needs to update web applications
    when you want to add external access to your Intranet for roaming users,
    open some of your sites to partners,
    only let managers access certain pages of your HR web site,
    or allow users already logged in to their desktops to visit protected sites
    without having to type their credentials again.
   </para>
  </section>
 </section>
 
 <section xml:id="policy-resolution">
  <title>How OpenAM Reaches Policy Decisions</title>
  
  <para>OpenAM has to match policies to resources to take policy decisions.
  For a policy to match, the resource has to match one of the resource patterns
   defined in the policy. The user making the request has to match a subject.
   Furthermore, at least one condition for each condition type has to be
   satisfied.</para>
  
  <para>If more than one policy matches, OpenAM has to reconcile differences.
  When multiple policies match, the order in which OpenAM uses them to make a
  policy decision is not deterministic. However, a deny decision overrides an
  allow decision, and so by default once OpenAM reaches a deny decision it
  stops checking further policies. (If you want OpenAM to continue checking
  despite the deny, see Configuration &gt; Global &gt; Policy Configuration
  &gt; Continue Evaluation on Deny Decision.)</para>
 </section>

 <section xml:id="configure-authz-apps">
  <title>Configuring Applications, Policies, and Referrals</title>

  <para>You can configure applications, policies and referrals by using the
   policy editor in the OpenAM console, by using the REST interface,
   or by using the <command>ssoadm</command> command.</para>
  <para>This section explains how to use the OpenAM console to configure
   applications, policies and referrals to protect a web site or web
   application.</para>
  <para>To configure applications and policies to protect
   other types of resource, you must use the REST API or
   the <command>ssoadm</command> command. For more information on the REST API,
   see the <citetitle>Developer's Guide</citetitle> chapters
   <link xlink:href="dev-guide#rest-api-authz-applications"
         xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink">
    <citetitle>Defining Applications</citetitle></link> and
   <link xlink:href="dev-guide#rest-api-authz-policies"
         xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink">
    <citetitle>Managing Policies</citetitle></link>. For more
   information on the <command>ssoadm</command> command,
   see the <citetitle>OpenAM Reference Guide</citetitle> chapter
   <link xlink:href="reference#ssoadm-1"
         xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink">
    <citetitle>ssoadm</citetitle></link>.</para>

  <xinclude:include href="sec-configure-apps-with-console.xml">
   <xinclude:fallback>
    <para>
     Configuring Applications with the OpenAM Console missing:
     /sections/sec-configure-apps-with-console.xml
    </para>
   </xinclude:fallback>
  </xinclude:include>

  <xinclude:include href="sec-configure-policies-with-console.xml">
   <xinclude:fallback>
    <para>
     Configuring Policies with the OpenAM Console missing:
     /sections/sec-configure-apps-with-console.xml
    </para>
   </xinclude:fallback>
  </xinclude:include>

  <xinclude:include href="sec-configure-referrals-with-console.xml">
   <xinclude:fallback>
    <para>
     Configuring Referrals with the OpenAM Console missing:
     /sections/sec-configure-referrals-with-console.xml
    </para>
   </xinclude:fallback>
  </xinclude:include>

  <section xml:id="policy-patterns-wildcards">
   <title>Specifying Resource Patterns with Wildcards</title>
   <xinclude:include href="../shared/itemizedlist-wildcard-syntax.xml">
    <xinclude:fallback>
     <para>
      wildcard syntax missing shared/itemizedlist-wildcard-syntax.xml
     </para>
    </xinclude:fallback>
   </xinclude:include>
  </section>

  <xinclude:include href="sec-import-export-policies.xml">
   <xinclude:fallback>
    <para>
     Importing and Exporting Policies missing:
     /sections/sec-import-export-policies.xml
    </para>
   </xinclude:fallback>
  </xinclude:include>

 </section>

 <section xml:id="delegate-policy">
  <title>Delegating Policy Management</title>

  <indexterm>
   <primary>Policy</primary>
   <secondary>Delegating management</secondary>
  </indexterm>

  <para>
   To delegate policy management and other administrative tasks, use privileges.
   You set privileges in OpenAM console on the Privileges page for a realm.
  </para>

  <para>
   For details see the procedure,
   <link
    xlink:href="admin-guide#chap-realms"
    xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink"
   ><citetitle>To Delegate Administration</citetitle></link>.</para>
 </section>
</chapter>
