<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  ! CCPL HEADER START
  !
  ! This work is licensed under the Creative Commons
  ! Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 3.0 Unported License.
  ! To view a copy of this license, visit
  ! http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/
  ! or send a letter to Creative Commons, 444 Castro Street,
  ! Suite 900, Mountain View, California, 94041, USA.
  !
  ! You can also obtain a copy of the license at
  ! src/main/resources/legal-notices/CC-BY-NC-ND.txt.
  ! See the License for the specific language governing permissions
  ! and limitations under the License.
  !
  ! If applicable, add the following below this CCPL HEADER, with the fields
  ! enclosed by brackets "[]" replaced with your own identifying information:
  !      Portions Copyright [yyyy] [name of copyright owner]
  !
  ! CCPL HEADER END
  !
  !      Copyright 2011-2013 ForgeRock, Inc.
  !    
-->
<chapter xml:id='chap-authz-policy'
 xmlns='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook'
 version='5.0' xml:lang='en'
 xmlns:xsi='http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance'
 xsi:schemaLocation='http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://docbook.org/xml/5.0/xsd/docbook.xsd'
 xmlns:xlink='http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink'>
 <title>Defining Authorization Policies</title>

 <para><firstterm>Authorization</firstterm> is determining whether to grant or
 deny a user access to a resource. <firstterm>Policies</firstterm> define how
 to determine whether to grant or deny access. This chapter describes how to
 configure authorization policies managed by OpenAM.</para>
 
 <section xml:id="what-is-authz">
  <title>About Authorization in OpenAM</title>
  <indexterm><primary>Authorization</primary></indexterm>
  <indexterm><primary>Policy</primary></indexterm>
  
  <para>Applications rely on OpenAM for access management, which breaks down
  into authentication, or determining who is trying to access a resource,
  and authorization, or determining whether to grant or deny access. This
  is because whether access is granted generally depends on what the rules
  about access are, who is trying to gain access, and perhaps some other
  conditions, such as whether the access itself needs to happen over a
  secure channel or what time of day it is. To return to the international
  airport example, the rule may be that passengers with valid passports and
  visa presenting valid plane tickets are allowed through to the gate where the
  plane is waiting to take off, but only under the condition that the plane
  is going to leave soon. (You cannot expect to get to the gate today with a
  scheduled departure for three months from now.)</para>
  
  <para>To allow OpenAM to determine whether to grant access, you define
  authorization policies. A policy includes <firstterm>rules</firstterm>
  that match what resources a user aims to access in what way and whether to
  grant or deny that access, <firstterm>subjects</firstterm> to whom the
  policy applies, and potentially <firstterm>conditions</firstterm> under
  which the policy applies. When queried about whether to let a user through
  to a protected resource, OpenAM decides to authorize access or not based on
  the applicable policy. OpenAM then communicates its decision to the
  application using OpenAM for access management, or in the common case to the
  policy agent installed in the server where the application runs. The
  application or the agent then enforces the authorization decision from
  OpenAM.</para>
  
  <para>For example, consider the case where OpenAM protects a web site
  page that users access to update their profiles. An OpenAM policy agent
  installed in the web server intercepts client requests to enforce policy.
  The policy says that authenticated users can access the page to update their
  profiles as long as they come in over HTTPS, rather than HTTP.</para>
  
  <para>When a user browses to the page to update her profile, the OpenAM
  policy agent intercepts the request. The policy agent notices that the
  request is to access a protected resource, but the request is coming from a
  user who has not yet logged in and has no authorization to visit the page.
  The agent therefore redirects the user to OpenAM.</para>
  
  <para>OpenAM receives the redirected user, serving a login page that
  collects her email and password. With the email and password credentials,
  OpenAM authenticates the user, and gives her a session. OpenAM then redirects
  the user to the policy agent, which gets the policy decision from OpenAM for
  the page she wants to access, and grants access to the page. OpenAM and the
  policy agent use cookies set in the user's browser to reference her session.
  While the user has a valid session with OpenAM, she can go away to another
  page in her browser, come back to the update profile page, and gain access
  without having to enter her email and password again.</para>
  
  <para>Notice how OpenAM and the policy agent handle the access in the
  example. The web site developer can offer a profile page, but the web site
  developer never has to manage login, nor has to handle who can access a page.
  As OpenAM administrator, you can change authentication and authorization
  independently of updates to the web site. You might need to agree with web
  site developers on how OpenAM identifies users so web developers can find
  their particular profiles, or identify the user by her own name when she logs
  in. Yet your organization is now spared from new web site development
  projects when you want to add external access to your Intranet for roaming
  users, open certain of your sites to partners, only let managers access
  certain pages of your HR web site, or allow users already logged in to their
  desktops to visit protected web sites without having to type their user names
  and passwords again.</para>
  
  <para>When OpenAM denies a request due to a condition that could be corrected
  by further authentication, OpenAM can send advice to the policy agent, and
  the policy agent can then take remedial action. For instance, suppose a
  user comes to a web site having authenticated with an email address and
  password, which is configured as authentication level 0. Had the user
  authenticated over the VPN which relies on one-time password authentication,
  she would have had authentication level 1 in her session. Yet, because she
  has authentication level 0, she currently cannot access the page she wants,
  which requires authentication level 1. OpenAM can send advice in this case,
  prompting the agent or application to redirect her to authenticate again with
  a one-time password, gaining authentication level 1, and thus having OpenAM
  grant her access to the protected page.</para>
  
  <para>Policies can include <firstterm>response providers</firstterm>.
  Response providers extend HTTP headers with additional information beyond
  an "allow" or "deny" decision. For example, a response provider can return
  a message about why access was denied.</para>

  <section xml:id="configure-policy-wildcard">
   <title>About Wildcards</title>
   <para>OpenAM allows the use of wildcards. Wildcards allow the policy to be generic so 
   that it can be analyzed against established resources. Use a wildcard in the 
   <literal>Resource Name</literal> when establishing the rules for a policy. For example, 
   the resource name <filename>http://website.example.com:80/*</filename>
   uses the <literal>*</literal> to allow the policy to analyze against all resources 
   associated with <filename>http://website.example.com:80/</filename>. OpenAM supports 
   both single- and multi-level wildcards.</para>
   
   <para>The following tables defines the expected behavior for wildcards.</para>

    <table xml:id="wildcard-bahavior" pgwide="1">
     <title>Expected Wildcard Behavior</title>
     <tgroup cols="3">
      <thead>
       <row>
        <entry>Wildcard <footnote><para>All reserved and unreserved characters within 
        the URI follow the guidelines provided in 
        <link xlink:show="new" xlink:href="http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc2396#section-2.2">sections 2.2 and 2.3 of RFC 2396</link>.</para></footnote></entry>
        <entry>Level</entry>
        <entry>Behavior</entry>
       </row>
      </thead>
      <tbody>
       <row>
        <entry><literal>*</literal> (single asterisk)</entry>
        <entry>Multi-level wildcard</entry>
        <entry>
         <para>Can be used within the protocol, host, port, path and query string parts</para>
         <para>Matches any character except <literal>?</literal> and spans across levels</para>
         <para>Can be used to assist query string matching</para>
         <para>It cannot be used in the same URL as a <literal>-*-</literal></para>
       </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry><literal>-*-</literal></entry>
        <entry>Single-level</entry>
        <entry>
         <para>Can only be used in the URL path</para>
         <para>Matches all characters except <literal>?</literal> and /</para>
         <para>It cannot be used in the same URL as <literal>*</literal></para>
       </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry><literal>/</literal> (single forward slash)</entry>
        <entry>Multi-level wildcard</entry>
        <entry>
         <para>Separates different levels with a rule</para>
         <para>Does not match a single forward slash</para>
         <para>Example: <literal>mult/*/dirs</literal> matches
         <literal>mult/iple/dirs</literal>, but not <literal>mult/dirs</literal></para>
        </entry>
       </row>        
       <row>
        <entry><literal>/ /</literal> (multiple forward slashes separated by text) </entry>
        <entry>Single-level wildcard</entry>
        <entry>
         <para>Trailing forward slashes will be ignored</para>
         <para>Example: <literal>http://www.website.example.com:80/</literal> will be
         read as <literal>http://www.website.example.com:80</literal></para>
        </entry>
       </row>        
       <row>
        <entry>Query Strings</entry>
        <entry>Not applicable</entry>
        <entry>
         <para>Does not match <literal>?</literal>	</para>
         <para>Requires a single <literal>*</literal> at the end to run</para>
         <para>Example: <literal>http://www.website.example.com/a?*</literal> will match
         <literal>http://www.website.example.com/a?b=c</literal> and 
         <literal>http://www.website.example.com/a?d=e</literal></para>
       </entry>
       </row>
       <row>
        <entry>General Wildcards (defined by RFC 2396)</entry>
        <entry>Single- and Multi-level Wildcards</entry>
        <entry>
         <para>Different wildcards cannot be mixed within a single rule</para>
       </entry>
       </row>
      </tbody>
     </tgroup>
    </table>

   <para>In order to match resource URLs with policies, OpenAM normalizes
   both the policy URL pattern you provide and the actual requested resource
   URL. OpenAM does the following during URL normalization.</para>

   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>OpenAM includes default port numbers if they are missing.</para>

     <para>The URL <literal>http://www.example.com/index.html</literal> becomes
     <literal>http://www.example.com:80/index.html</literal>.</para>

     <para>The URL <literal>https://www.example.com/index.html</literal> becomes
     <literal>https://www.example.com:443/index.html</literal>.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
     <para>OpenAM sorts the query string field-value pairs by field name.</para>

     <para>The query string
     <literal>?subject=SPBnfm+t5PlP+ISyQhVlplE22A8=&amp;action=get</literal>
     becomes
     <literal>?action=get&amp;subject=SPBnfm+t5PlP+ISyQhVlplE22A8=</literal>.</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
     <para>OpenAM removes extra slashes, including trailing slashes.</para>

     <para>The URL <literal>http://www.example.com//blog/</literal> becomes
     <literal>http://www.example.com:80/blog</literal>.</para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>

   <para>By default, comparisons are not case sensitive. The delimiter,
   wildcards and case sensitivity are configurable. To see examples of other
   configurations, browse in the OpenAM console to Configuration &gt; Global
   &gt; Policy Configuration &gt; Resource Comparator.</para>
  </section>
 </section>
 
 <section xml:id="configure-authz-policy">
  <title>Configuring Policies</title>
  
  <para>An OpenAM authorization policy defines who can access what, under what
  conditions. The OpenAM agents enforcing policy call upon OpenAM to make
  policy decisions. Decisions from OpenAM can be as simple as "allow" or
  "deny." Decisions from OpenAM can alternatively provide additional
  information required for policy enforcement. OpenAM policies use response
  providers to return such additional information.</para>
  
  <procedure xml:id="create-policy">
   <title>To Create a Policy</title>
   
   <step>
    <para>In the OpenAM console, select Access Control &gt; <replaceable>Realm
    Name</replaceable> &gt; Policies, then click New Policy.</para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>Provide at minimum a name for the policy.</para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
  
  <procedure xml:id="configure-url-policy">
   <title>To Configure a Policy For a Web Site</title>
   <indexterm>
    <primary>Authorization</primary>
    <secondary>Configuring</secondary>
   </indexterm>
   <indexterm>
    <primary>Policy</primary>
    <secondary>Configuring</secondary>
   </indexterm>
   <para>Once a policy is created, you can further specify rules, subjects,
   conditions, and response providers.</para>
   
   <itemizedlist>
    <para>OpenAM has, by default, three kinds of resources that you can protect
    with a policy.</para>
    <listitem>
     <para>A <firstterm>Discovery Service</firstterm>, used in federated access
     management, locates the web service providing the data needed to complete
     an operation. Your policy protects what clients can look up and what they
     can update.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>A <firstterm>Liberty Personal Profile Service</firstterm>, used in
     federated access management, provides an identity's basic profile
     information. Your policy protects what clients can query and what they
     can modify.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>A <firstterm>URL Policy Agent</firstterm> protects resources on a
     specific web site or web application. Your policy protects what URLs
     client applications can access with HTTP GET and POST operations.</para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   
   <para>Follow these steps to configure a policy to protect a web site or web
   application.</para>
   
   <step>
    <para>In the OpenAM console, select Access Control &gt; <replaceable>Realm
    Name</replaceable> &gt; Policies &gt; <replaceable>Policy
    Name</replaceable> to display the policy to edit.</para>
   </step>
   <step xml:id="define-rules">
    <para>In the Rules table, click New... to create a rule, identifying
    a URL to protect.</para>
    <substeps>
     <step>
      <para>Select URL Policy Agent (with resource name), and click Next.</para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>Name the new rule, add the URL to protect in the Resource Name
      field, and set whether to allow or deny HTTP GET and POST requests
      to the URL.</para>

      <para>Your Resource Name can use wildcards as described in <xref linkend="configure-policy-wildcard" />.</para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>Click Finish.</para>
      <para>The new rule is not yet saved until you click the Save button
      in the Edit Policy screen.</para>
     </step>
    </substeps>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>In the Subjects table, click New... to define a subject, identifying
    the users to whom the policy applies.</para>
    <substeps>
     <step>
      <para>In the Select Subject Type screen, make your selection,
      and then click next.</para>
      <itemizedlist>
       <listitem>
        <para>Authenticated Users refers to users who have authenticated
        with OpenAM, even if they do not have profiles in the realm where
        you define the policy.</para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para>OpenAM Identity Subject refers to users or groups you can find
        under Access Control &gt; Realm Name &gt; Subjects.</para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para>Web Services Clients are for federated access management.</para>
       </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>Name the subject.</para>
     </step>
     <step performance="optional">
      <para>If you want to apply the policy to everyone but the subjects
      you identified, then select Exclusive.</para>
      <para>For example</para>
     </step>
     <step performance="optional">
      <para>If you selected OpenAM Identity Subject, use the Filter section
      to find and add to your list the subjects to whom to apply the
      policy.</para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>Click Finish.</para>
     </step>
    </substeps>
   </step>
   <step performance="optional">
    <para>In the Conditions table, click New... to create a condition,
    constraining the circumstances under which the policy applies.</para>
    <substeps>
     <step>
      <para>Select the Condition Type from the list.</para>
      <itemizedlist>
       <listitem>
        <para>Active Session Time lets you make the policy depend on how
        long the user's session has been active, and even to terminate the
        session if deemed too old, such that the user must authenticate
        again.</para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para>Authentication by Module Chain lets you make the policy depend
        on the realm where the user authenticated, and on the authentication
        chain used to authenticate.</para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para>Authentication by Module Instance lets you make the policy depend
        on the realm where the user authenticated, and on the authentication
        module used to authenticate, as well as setting timeouts for
        application authentication.</para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para>Authentication Level (greater than or equal to) lets you
        make the policy depend on the realm where the user authenticated,
        and on a minimum acceptable authentication level.</para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para>Authentication Level (less than or equal to) lets you
        make the policy depend on the realm where the user authenticated,
        and on a maximum acceptable authentication level.</para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para>Authentication to a Realm lets you make the policy depend on
        the realm where the user authenticated.</para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para>Current Session Properties lets you make the policy depend on
        attributes set in the user's session.</para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para>Identity Membership lets you make the policy depend on a list
        of OpenAM subjects that you select, and whether the user belongs to
        the list of users or is a member of a group you selected.</para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para>IP Address/DNS Name lets you apply the policy to clients in
        specific IP address ranges or coming from a particular DNS
        domain. It also lets you choose between IPv4 and IPv6 address versions.</para>
        <itemizedlist>
         <listitem>
          <para>For IPv4, fill in the fields for the From and To with four sets of
          four characters.</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
          <para>For IPv6, fill in the fields for the From and To with eight sets of
          four hexadecimal characters. The default separator between each set of
          IPv6 hexidecimal characters is a colon.</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
          <para>For a hybrid address, select IPv6. Fill in the first four fields for the 
          From and To with four characters of the IPv6 address, then change
          the punctuation to a . and add the four IPv4 characters in the remaining three 
          fields.</para>
         </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para>LDAP Filter Condition lets you make the policy depend on whether
        the user's entry can be found using the LDAP search filter you specify
        in the directory configured for the policy service, which by default
        is the identity repository. See Configuration &gt; Global &gt; Policy
        Configuration &gt; Realm Attributes &gt; Primary LDAP Server.</para>
        <para>Alternatively you can set this for the realm under Access Control
        &gt; <replaceable>Realm Name</replaceable> &gt; Services &gt; Policy
        Configuration.</para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para>Resource/Environment/IP Address lets you make the policy apply
        using a complex condition such as whether the user is making a request
        from the localhost and has authenticated with the LDAP authentication
        module. This address also works with IPv4, IPv6, or a hybrid of the two.</para>
       </listitem>
       <listitem>
        <para>Time (day, date, time, and timezone) lets you make the policy
        depend on when the policy is evaluated.</para>
       </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>Based on the Condition Type you choose, configure the condition,
      and then click Finish.</para>
     </step>
    </substeps>
   </step>
   <step performance="optional">
    <para>In the Response Providers table, click New to set up a response
    provider that adds attributes retrieved from the user entry in the identity
    repository into the headers of the request at policy decision time.</para>
    <substeps>
     <step>
      <para>Name the provider.</para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>Add static attributes having the form
      <literal><replaceable>attribute</replaceable>=<replaceable>value</replaceable></literal>.</para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>Add dynamic attributes having the form
      <literal><replaceable>responseAttr</replaceable>=<replaceable>repoAttr</replaceable></literal>,
      where <replaceable>responseAttr</replaceable> is the attribute name
      to be put into the header of the request, and
      <replaceable>repoAttr</replaceable> is the attribute name used in the
      identity repository.</para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>Click Finish.</para>
     </step>
    </substeps>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>Save your work.</para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </section>
 
 <section xml:id="policy-resolution">
  <title>How OpenAM Reaches Policy Decisions</title>
  
  <para>OpenAM has to match policies to resources to take policy decisions.
  For a policy to match, the resource has to match a resources identified in
  a rule. The user making the request has to match a subject. Furthermore, at
  least one condition for each condition type has to be satisfied.</para>
  
  <para>If more than one policy matches, OpenAM has to reconcile differences.
  When multiple policies match, the order in which OpenAM uses them to make a
  policy decision is not deterministic. However, a deny decision overrides an
  allow decision, and so by default once OpenAM reaches a deny decision its
  stops checking further policies. (If you want OpenAM to continue checking
  despite the deny, see Configuration &gt; Global &gt; Policy Configuration
  &gt; Continue Evaluation on Deny Decision.)</para>
 </section>
 
 <section xml:id="script-policy">
  <title>Managing Policies Outside the Console</title>
  <indexterm>
   <primary>Authorization</primary>
   <secondary>Configuring</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
   <primary>Policy</primary>
   <secondary>Configuring</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <para>When you first create policies, the OpenAM console helps you to get
  started quickly. Yet, when you have many policies to manage you might find
  it easier to script operations, starting from policies originally created
  in the console, then exported to XML.</para>
  
  <procedure xml:id="export-policy-to-xml">
   <title>To Export Policies From the Console</title>
   
   <para>You can export policies created in the console to an XML Policies
   document.</para>
   
   <step>
    <para>Use the <command>ssoadm list-policies</command> command.</para>
    <screen>$ ssoadm
 list-policies
 --realm "/"
 --adminid amadmin
 --password-file /tmp/pwd.txt 

Policy definitions were returned under realm, /.
&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?&gt;
&lt;!DOCTYPE Policies 
PUBLIC "-//OpenSSO Policy Administration DTD//EN"
"jar://com/sun/identity/policy/policyAdmin.dtd"&gt;

&lt;!-- extracted from realm, / --&gt;
&lt;Policies&gt;
&lt;Policy name="URL Policy" createdby="id=amadmin,ou=user,o=openam"
 lastmodifiedby="id=amadmin,ou=user,o=openam" creationdate="1312553988059"
 lastmodifieddate="1315403023466" referralPolicy="false" active="true" &gt;
&lt;Rule name="Allow GET with parameters"&gt;
&lt;ServiceName name="iPlanetAMWebAgentService" /&gt;
&lt;ResourceName name="http://www.example.com/ching/*?*" /&gt;
&lt;AttributeValuePair&gt;
&lt;Attribute name="GET" /&gt;
&lt;Value&gt;allow&lt;/Value&gt;
&lt;/AttributeValuePair&gt;
&lt;/Rule&gt;
&lt;Rule name="Allow GET and POST"&gt;
&lt;ServiceName name="iPlanetAMWebAgentService" /&gt;
&lt;ResourceName name="http://www.example.com/ching/*" /&gt;
&lt;AttributeValuePair&gt;
&lt;Attribute name="POST" /&gt;
&lt;Value&gt;allow&lt;/Value&gt;
&lt;/AttributeValuePair&gt;
&lt;AttributeValuePair&gt;
&lt;Attribute name="GET" /&gt;
&lt;Value&gt;allow&lt;/Value&gt;
&lt;/AttributeValuePair&gt;
&lt;/Rule&gt;
&lt;Subjects name="Subjects:1312553593870WmIuFvI=" description=""&gt;
&lt;Subject name="All Authenticated Users" type="AuthenticatedUsers"
 includeType="inclusive"&gt;
&lt;/Subject&gt;
&lt;/Subjects&gt;
&lt;/Policy&gt;
&lt;/Policies&gt;</screen>
   </step>
  </procedure>
  
  <procedure xml:id="import-policy-from-xml">
   <title>To Import Policies Using the Command Line</title>
   
   <para>In a production environment where you manage operations using scripts
   rather than the console, use exported, file-based policies edited for your
   needs, and then import the policies using <command>ssoadm</command>.</para>
   
   <step>
    <para>Create your XML policy file.</para>
    <screen>$ cat policy.xml
&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?&gt;
&lt;!DOCTYPE Policies 
PUBLIC "-//OpenSSO Policy Administration DTD//EN"
"jar://com/sun/identity/policy/policyAdmin.dtd"&gt;
&lt;!-- New policy, same as the old policy --&gt;
&lt;Policies&gt;
&lt;Policy name="New Policy" referralPolicy="false" active="true" &gt;
&lt;Rule name="Allow GET with parameters"&gt;
&lt;ServiceName name="iPlanetAMWebAgentService" /&gt;
&lt;ResourceName name="http://www.example.com/ching/*?*" /&gt;
&lt;AttributeValuePair&gt;
&lt;Attribute name="GET" /&gt;
&lt;Value&gt;allow&lt;/Value&gt;
&lt;/AttributeValuePair&gt;
&lt;/Rule&gt;
&lt;Rule name="Allow GET and POST"&gt;
&lt;ServiceName name="iPlanetAMWebAgentService" /&gt;
&lt;ResourceName name="http://www.example.com/ching/*" /&gt;
&lt;AttributeValuePair&gt;
&lt;Attribute name="POST" /&gt;
&lt;Value&gt;allow&lt;/Value&gt;
&lt;/AttributeValuePair&gt;
&lt;AttributeValuePair&gt;
&lt;Attribute name="GET" /&gt;
&lt;Value&gt;allow&lt;/Value&gt;
&lt;/AttributeValuePair&gt;
&lt;/Rule&gt;
&lt;Subjects name="Subjects" description="Everybody authenticated"&gt;
&lt;Subject name="All Authenticated Users" type="AuthenticatedUsers"
 includeType="inclusive"&gt;
&lt;/Subject&gt;
&lt;/Subjects&gt;
&lt;/Policy&gt;
&lt;/Policies&gt;</screen>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>Use the <command>ssoadm create-policies</command> command.</para>
    <screen>$ ssoadm
 create-policies
 --realm "/"
 --adminid amadmin
 --password-file /tmp/pwd.txt
 --xmlfile policy.xml

Policies were created under realm, /.</screen>
   </step>
  </procedure>
 </section>
 
 <section xml:id="delegate-policy">
  <title>Delegating Policy Management &amp; Decisions</title>
  <indexterm>
   <primary>Authorization</primary>
   <secondary>Delegating</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <indexterm>
   <primary>Policy</primary>
   <secondary>Delegating</secondary>
  </indexterm>
  <para>You use a <firstterm>referral</firstterm> to delegate policy
  management, and to delegate policy decision making.</para>
  <para>Referrals are covered in the <link xlink:href="admin-guide#chap-realms"
  xlink:role="http://docbook.org/xlink/role/olink">chapter on
  Realms</link>.</para>
 </section>
</chapter>
